<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT><record id="00015435" dt="2015-10-02"><version>4</version><date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2014-10-24</date><date_nonpreferred_format>2014-10-24</date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id>MS2015-007_VTLGBTQ_ElmoreTori</cms_record_id><title>Oral History with Tori Elmore, October 24, 2014 (Ms2015-007)</title><accession></accession><duration>00:54:49</duration><collection_id>Ms2015-007</collection_id><collection_name>The Virginia Tech LGBTQ Oral History Collection</collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Virginia Tech Special Collections</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewee>Tori Elmore</interviewee><interviewer>Ellen Boggs</interviewer><file_name>Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_ElmoreTori</file_name><sync>1:|19(2)|28(11)|36(14)|46(5)|61(2)|77(12)|95(2)|103(10)|109(17)|123(7)|132(3)|144(8)|154(6)|162(3)|181(9)|191(5)|206(9)|222(16)|234(6)|249(2)|266(3)|281(7)|296(9)|308(4)|324(6)|336(5)|349(10)|357(14)|364(2)|372(4)|381(1)|393(2)|402(3)|410(12)|419(11)|427(5)|435(12)|451(13)|459(13)|467(4)|473(16)|484(13)|500(2)|508(16)|520(12)|539(9)|554(3)|568(10)|576(1)|590(8)|602(9)|617(11)|639(8)|650(1)</sync><media_id></media_id><media_url>http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/files/original/3409/Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_ElmoreTori_OralHistory.1.mp3</media_url><mediafile><host>Other</host><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>audio</clip_format></mediafile><language></language><index><point><time>0</time><title>Introductions</title><partial_transcript>Ellen Boggs: Alright. My name is Ellen Boggs, I’m here with Tori Elmore and David Atkins. This is part of the oral history project for Dr. Cline’s class for the LGBTQ. Would you like to introduce yourself?

Tori Elmore:  As Ellen said, I am Tori Elmore. I am twenty-eight years old, originally from Wytheville Virginia just down the road. [I] Graduated from Virginia Tech in Mechanical Engineering in 2009 and I’ve been working up the road in Giles County ever since. 
</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>52</time><title>Childhood</title><partial_transcript>ELMORE: I was born in Charlotte and lived there until I was almost nine. Pretty normal upbringing, [I] went through various phases of Ninja Turtles and Power Rangers and just ran around outside, built Legos, which was probably a sign I was going to be an engineer one day. Nothing uncommon, I never really thought about anything like ‘who am I supposed to be?’ It just never crossed my mind. I never really thought about it. I was just too busy doing stuff, learning stuff. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>434</time><title>Feeling Different</title><partial_transcript>ELMORE: coming to college forced me to open my mind a little bit more about the world as it is, and the first couple years I kind of stayed in my little bubble.  But then I just got tired of it.  I felt repressed in the sense of not really having control over my own life and letting other people do it for me—and that’s definitely just friends and not my parents, they’re amazing. I started kind of branching out and doing various illegal activities [laughs] and it started freeing my mind up to think about things outside of a certain context.  When I did that— I think that’s when some really high level anxiety started.  I started to get a sense of something was just not right. I just feel different for some reason, just off—not like a [air quotes] ‘normal’ person.  </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>701</time><title>Depression and Self-Destruction</title><partial_transcript>ELMORE: My anxiety got worse and my depression got worse—a lot worse.  I was just doing a lot of really destructive things and not really caring. I wasn’t— what was the word?— my aunt, she’s a social worker in Baltimore, she described it as being passively suicidal;  where you’re not going to go actively cut yourself or jump off a bridge or anything, but if a situation could come up that would cause you harm, whatever who cares, whatever.  I was very apathetic about it; and that’s where I was getting. I would do things like go get hammered at the bar and be like fuck it, I can still drive home, and I don’t care, it’s fine. And then I wrecked the truck, and had some really close calls with DUIs, and had to get friends to come get me at four in the morning.  It was just a downward spiral and eventually just reached a point where I was sitting in my kitchen, just chugged a bunch of vodka or something, this was fall of 2012, and I was looking at my little island of steak knives and just kind of picked one up and just thought, you know, this would just make so many things so much easier.</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>801</time><title>'Maybe I Need to Try This Hormone Thing'</title><partial_transcript>ELMORE: I called up my best friend and we talked about it and she was like you’ve got to do something different. And I was like, maybe I need to try this hormone thing, maybe that’s why I’m so upset.  I started to think about how if I didn’t like it I could just stop.  It’s no harm, no foul, it’s kind of a no-lose situation. Even just the act of me saying, ‘yes I’m going to give this a try’ just completely shifted how I was feeling about life.  I just instantly became happier and more excited and hopeful.  </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>894</time><title>Roller Derby</title><partial_transcript>ELMORE:  The roller derby team was great with it.

BOGGS:  Oh, please talk about that.

ELMORE: [Laughs] Yes!  Whenever we would have formal occasions, which we would have randomly, I could dress how I wanted, everybody was totally fun with it and we had a blast, and they were just completely open.  ‘Just do you,’ they kept saying. I originally joined the team in 2009; me and my roommate went to recruitment night and I figured, well I’m graduated, I guess I need a hobby or something because I have extra time now, this seems like fun.  I couldn’t play because it’s a women’s sport, but I could referee.  </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>1245</time><title>Job at Celanese Plant</title><partial_transcript>BOGGS: Where do you work again? Sorry.

ELMORE: It’s Celanese. It’s a chemical plant about thirty minutes away in Giles County, between Pearisburg and Narrows. Or ‘Narras’ [pronounces with an accent] as the locals call it.

BOGGS: What do you do?

ELMORE: I’m a Maintenance Engineer. So things break and I figure out why, and if things break frequently I try to dig more into it and see what’s really causing it. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>1342</time><title>Deciding to Start Hormone Treatments</title><partial_transcript>ELMORE: One of the sessions with my therapist when I was debating whether to start hormone treatments I made a pro and con list–here’s all the reasons why it would be good and here’s all the reasons why it would be bad. Then we would talk about it and some of them would be more facetious than others. Then eventually the right one won out. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>1531</time><title>Being Trans in 'Blue Collar Boys Club USA'</title><partial_transcript>ELMORE: I really think the best outreach that I do is just showing up to work everyday in blue collar boys club USA. 

BOGGS: Yeah how’s that?

ELMORE: I thought they would chase me out of town with torches and pitchforks. Somewhere in the back of my head I thought ‘yeah that’s gonna happen,’ but no everybody’s been great. I had a hunch that people are generally better than we give them credit for, especially in terms of Appalachian culture. We want to do right by people even if something seems kind of weird or strange. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>1647</time><title>Living a Double Life</title><partial_transcript>ELMORE: I actually started having a Dexter style double life where I would go out dressed certain ways with certain company and have to keep pictures untagged on Facebook like ‘don’t tag me on Facebook! I swear don’t do it,’ because I would be friends with people at work and they would see it and bad things would happen. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>1874</time><title>Coming Out at Work</title><partial_transcript>ELMORE: So I sat down with my boss, my former boss, they work closely and in similar roles and I just set up a meeting with a nebulous title like ‘discussing the future.’ They were like ‘so you called us in here. What is this for?’ </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>2546</time><title>Trouble Finding an Endocrinologist</title><partial_transcript>BOGGS: You mentioned that you had to go to UVA to see an endocrinologist? 

ELMORE: Yeah. 

BOGGS: Why did you have to go so far?

ELMORE: Uh, I tried a couple of endocrinologists around here. One guy in Princeton thought, when I said on the phone I was looking for hormone replacement, that I was low on testosterone and needed to boost it and I was like ‘Oh no, no, no, no, no I want to go the other way with it.’ He said ‘Oh I don’t have any training for that.’ </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>2714</time><title>Transition Experiences</title><partial_transcript>BOGGS: When you first started it did you notice anything changing immediately, or did it take time?

ELMORE: It took some time, but I just instantly felt better. Like–ahhhh [sigh of relaxation], like I was finally doing the right thing. 

BOGGS: So it wasn’t really the treatment; it was just that you knew you were headed in the right direction?

ELMORE: Yeah, it was very much a psychological impact, but then I’d say three months or so in my chest started hurting and that’s when I was kind of like yea! Things are happening!</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>2984</time><title>Family Support</title><partial_transcript>BOGGS: Did you ever talk to your aunt about anything?

ELMORE: Mmhm, she was great. I could tell her that I had a secret urge to go slice up people and put them in dumpster and she’d be like, ‘Oh why do you want to do that?’ She couldn’t be phased. So, she was always my go to for, I feel something strange and I want to talk to someone about it.

BOGGS: So in your family it was mainly your mom and your aunt?

ELMORE: Mmhm, my dad hasn’t had a problem with this, but he’s always been the more pragmatic one. When I first told him I’m transgender after he processed it, he was more concerned about things like my career, the job I was at and how that would be affected. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>3075</time><title>Dating</title><partial_transcript>BOGGS: So, as far as dating–you don’t have to talk about it if you don’t want to but, how has that changed?

ELMORE: I avoided it mostly over the past couple years since I knew something was probably on the horizon, so I avoided dating like the plague. That’s not to say that there weren’t forays in the night, but I didn’t actively pursue a relationship. I actually had a date last weekend. That was my first date in a good couple of years. 
</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>3201</time><title>Gaining Acceptance</title><partial_transcript>ELMORE: Yeah in general I think I have been amazed at how–I’m not sure if accepting is the right word, but willingness to roll with – or maybe it is acceptance, I don’t know. When I think about people, real Appalachian people have really been with this whole thing.</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point></index><type></type><description>Tori Elmore grew up in Wytheville, VA, and graduated from Virginia Tech in 2009 with a BS in Mechanical Engineering. Elmore currently lives in the Blacksburg area and works as a maintenance engineer at the Celanese chemical plant in Narrows, VA. In the Spring of 2013, Elmore began hormone treatments to transition from a man to a woman and the following Fall she came out publicly at her place of work. Elmore plays for the Christiansburg Roller Derby team and is an active member of the New River Valley chapter of PFLAG, a national organization that provides support and education for parents, friends and allies of LGBTQ individuals. In her oral history, Elmore discusses her struggle with depression, the transition process, playing on a Roller Derby team, coming out at work and gaining acceptance in a blue collar Appalachian community. </description><rel /><transcript>Ellen Boggs: Alright. My name is Ellen Boggs, I'm here with Tori Elmore and
David Atkins. This is part of the oral history project for Dr. Cline's class for
the LGBTQ. Would you like to introduce yourself?

Tori Elmore:  As Ellen said, I am Tori Elmore. I am twenty-eight years old,
originally from Wytheville Virginia just down the road. [I] Graduated from
Virginia Tech in Mechanical Engineering in 2009 and I've been working up the
road in Giles County ever since.

BOGGS: We've already covered your name, date of birth. Oh did you cover your
date of birth?

ELMORE: I was born on August 14th 1986.

BOGGS: Alright. If you could tell us more about where you're from and the people
you interacted with there [Wytheville] and throughout your childhood?

ELMORE: I was born in Charlotte and lived there until I was almost nine. Pretty
normal upbringing, [I] went through various phases of Ninja Turtles and Power
Rangers and just ran around outside, built Legos, which was probably a sign I
was going to be an engineer one day. Nothing uncommon, I never really thought
about anything like 'who am I supposed to be?' It just never crossed my mind. I
never really thought about it. I was just too busy doing stuff, learning stuff.
Though my mom did tell me when I was coming out of diapers and she as taking me
to get my big boy underpants, cause that's apparently a big day, she asked me
what I wanted and I said 'pink'. She thought I just didn't know what I was
talking about and we never broached the subject ever again, well until a few
years ago, but we will get to that. Yeah a pretty normal childhood. Then moved
here to Wytheville, which is quite a change of scenery from being just outside
Charlotte. Really I remember, let's see [pause]. I remember having a hard time
with my older brother because I've always been more introverted and he would
make fun of me a lot and his friends would also and they would call me names, it
was less than pleasant. I tried to avoid him at all costs, but it doesn't really
work out. You can't avoid someone in the same house. But I had my own friends. I
was in the [school] band and ran cross country and track and stuff. I think some
of my best friends were in the band. Cross country was just my outlet to do
physical things or I'd get cranky and feel like I didn't know what I was doing
with my life. I dated some; I was mostly just scared to talk to girls. Really
awkward in general, in case you can't tell. That part of things was pretty clear
to me as far as who I was attracted to that hasn't really been much of a
question. Some of the other things in my life didn't come up until maybe my
early twenties. I probably started letting myself ask those questions. There was
a lot of repression, I think, in my teenage years. I'm sorry if I'm jumping
around or anything.

BOGGS: No that's fine. Could you say why you moved to Wytheville was it for your family?

ELMORE: Yeah it was for my dad, he got a job there. So he went from [pause] he
was a shift supervisor at Eastman Chemical Company and he got a Plant Manager
position at, they've changed so many names now, it was Morton Powder Coatings
then it got bought by Roman Hoss and then Dow for a while now it's Axon of Bell
[sp]. It was a chance for him to better himself and a better life for us, so we
jumped on it.

BOGGS: In high school were you more into the math and science as an engineer
coming into Tech?

ELMORE: Oh yeah, I was definitely a mathlete. I was on the math competition
team, which was really fun for me. I filled in for the science team a couple
times and everyone just kind of expected me to sit there and I got a few
questions right. I was just like, okay.

BOGGS: As far as your band friends how close would say you were with them?

ELMORE: I never really talked much with them about seriously deep stuff with
really much anybody, but I would say they were my best friends.

BOGGS: For homecoming dances or anything, did you go to those, prom?

ELMORE: Yeah they were a good time. I went just mostly to have fun; asking a
girl to go with me was just kind of a chore, like well I guess I have to.

BOGGS: How did that go?

ELMORE: Some occasions better than others, but overall I just had a good time
with it. I usually tried to ask friends, cause I wasn't really romantically
interested with anyone at my own school for some reason. All my dating
experiences were with people at other schools nearby.

BOGGS: So how would you meet them?

ELMORE: Friends of friends, traveling to different competitions or sporting
events stuff like that.

BOGGS: Pretty basic, everyone does that. What was the application process like
to get into Tech anything really stuck out?

ELMORE: There was no essay so I was like 'I'll apply there cause I don't have to
write an essay and I really don't want to do that.' It was just right up the
road, so I applied for early decision and got accepted and was like 'alright
well that's done, moving on.' So I didn't really have to worry about it from
that point on.

BOGGS: Well now if you just want to talk about how college was different than
high school?

ELMORE: In high school I was really religious.  I've developed some theories
about why, but it was what it was, and coming to college forced me to open my
mind a little bit more about the world as it is, and the first couple years I
kind of stayed in my little bubble.  But then I just got tired of it.  I felt
repressed in the sense of not really having control over my own life and letting
other people do it for me, and that's definitely just friends and not my parents,
they're amazing. I started kind of branching out and doing various illegal
activities [laughs] and it started freeing my mind up to think about things
outside of a certain context.  When I did that, I think that's when some really
high level anxiety started.  I started to get a sense of something was just not
right. I just feel different for some reason, just off, not like a [air quotes]
'normal' person.  I felt uncomfortable in general and just really awkward and I
felt like I needed to do things, like drink a lot, to be able to socialize well.
As time went on in my later years of college I started to get more of a sense
of what was going on; that things weren't right and I really did feel like
someone else, but I didn't treat it that way at first.  At first I treated it as
this super secret thing I did in private and then didn't tell anyone about, as
far as expressing my inner [short pause] desires, if that's the right word?

BOGGS: Is there any specific moment that you can think of where you kind of
transitioned from thinking of yourself one way to the next?

ELMORE: Not really one specific moment, it-

BOGGS: Just a collective?

Tori:  Yeah, an evolution of thought.  It very much evolved from I'm comfortably
male to I'm just really awkward and uncomfortable for some reason to oh, I
apparently really enjoy pretending to be a woman.  I thought oh that's weird,
but okay it's fun so I'll roll with it, but keeping that private, and then going
to places like the park or go with a friend that just happened into my life at
just the right moment to somewhere like Asheville for a night.  Then that turned
into, I like who I'm seeing in the mirror this way more than otherwise.  Then
[laughs] that turned into me talking with my mom saying, 'hey I was thinking
about getting a therapist.'  [She asked] 'Why?' [I replied] 'Oh there's this
thing I like to do sometimes', and then she's like 'oh okay, well that's fine.'
She wasn't really sure what to make of it because it came out of nowhere. But
then I was like I don't want to do any [laughs] hormones or surgeries or
anything, I swear!  That turned into, maybe a year or two later, me saying to
her that 'so I think I kind of need to do this hormone thing [laughs].'

BOGGS: Was that from a doctor telling you to do that, or just something you
thought about yourself?

ELMORE: Both. My anxiety got worse and my depression got worse, a lot worse.  I
was just doing a lot of really destructive things and not really caring. I
wasn't, what was the word?, my aunt, she's a social worker in Baltimore, she
described it as being passively suicidal;  where you're not going to go actively
cut yourself or jump off a bridge or anything, but if a situation could come up
that would cause you harm, whatever who cares, whatever.  I was very apathetic
about it; and that's where I was getting. I would do things like go get hammered
at the bar and be like fuck it, I can still drive home, and I don't care, it's
fine. And then I wrecked the truck, and had some really close calls with DUIs,
and had to get friends to come get me at four in the morning.  It was just a
downward spiral and eventually just reached a point where I was sitting in my
kitchen, just chugged a bunch of vodka or something, this was fall of 2012, and
I was looking at my little island of steak knives and just kind of picked one up
and just thought, you know, this would just make so many things so much easier.
Just the fact that I thought that just made me step back and go, 'what the fuck
am I doing with my life, I have got to do something.  I can't keep doing this.'
I called up my best friend and we talked about it and she was like you've got to
do something different. And I was like, maybe I need to try this hormone thing,
maybe that's why I'm so upset.  I started to think about how if I didn't like it
I could just stop.  It's no harm, no foul, it's kind of a no-lose situation.
Even just the act of me saying, 'yes I'm going to give this a try' just
completely shifted how I was feeling about life.  I just instantly became
happier and more excited and hopeful.  I would tell people when they asked how
I'm doing I would say I'm [stuttering the word] ha-hap-happy, like [laughs] it
was some foreign concept I could never understand.  Or, am I describing this
about myself?  That's not right.  It fits, but it doesn't seem like it's
supposed to fit.' If that makes sense.

BOGGS:  It does, it does make sense. So, with the friend that you called, she
had an idea of how you were feeling at the time?

ELMORE:  Yeah, we talked about everything.  She had a master's in Women and
Gender Studies, so she was a good best friend to have, still is.

BOGGS:  Was there anyone else you had talked about it with?

ELMORE:  The roller derby team was great with it.

BOGGS:  Oh, please talk about that.

ELMORE: [Laughs] Yes!  Whenever we would have formal occasions, which we would
have randomly, I could dress how I wanted, everybody was totally fun with it and
we had a blast, and they were just completely open.  'Just do you,' they kept
saying. I originally joined the team in 2009; me and my roommate went to
recruitment night and I figured, well I'm graduated, I guess I need a hobby or
something because I have extra time now, this seems like fun.  I couldn't play
because it's a women's sport, but I could referee.  I thought, alright, let's
see what happens; who knows, there might be some fringe benefits and we'll see
how it goes.  Just to try something.  I guess maybe I just had a hunch it was
the right place for me to be because it's a very eclectic kind of culture. I
just got addicted to it, hooked on it, just loved it.  Over time, over the next
few years, I would open up more and more about myself.  Some of the girls on the
team kept saying, 'you know if you just went ahead and started taking hormones
you could be playing with us.' [I replied], 'oh I don't know, that's scary, I
don't know.' Then I eventually did and I'm playing now!

BOGGS:  So where is the derby team at, where do you guys practice and play?

ELMORE:  Yeah, we're based out of Christiansburg up until recently when
Adventure World, the rink in Christiansburg, went out of business.  So we're in
Roanoke right now until we either have a new rink open up in Christiansburg, or
can find a big warehouse space to rent, just some big flat enclosed area.

BOGGS: Do you guys travel at all, where do you get to go?

ELMORE: This year I've been to Fredericksburg, Lancaster Pennsylvania,
Charleston West Virginia.   I'm going to Johnston City later today. In the past
we've gone to Virginia Beach and Wilmington, Charlotte, Winston Salem, just kind
of all over the place- Harrisonburg, Charlottesville, Richmond.

BOGGS: How does that happen? Do you guys set it up yourselves or-

ELMORE: Mhmm.

BOGGS: How do you network for that?

ELMORE: Internet helps. I don't know how it could be done without the internet;
I just can't imagine it. Every team puts there information out there and every
team has an interleague coordinator who sets up the schedule and works with
other teams to figure out their open dates and our open dates. It's like okay
well we can play you on this date and then other teams will play you on this
date. We look at the history of where did we play last time, was it home last
year or away last year and try to reach the best solutions for everyone.

BOGGS: Do you make friends just on your team?

ELMORE: No I've got friends everywhere. Tomorrow we have a 'bout,' we call them,
against the team from Beckley. I'm really good friends with, probably close to,
half their team. I've just known them for the last few years. I've got some good
friends on the Charlottesville team, other West Virginia teams like Charleston,
Lewisburg, some on Johnston City's team, just kind of everywhere. I traveled as a
referee, not just for our team, I would get Facebook messages 'hey there is a
bout next weekend in, pick-a-place, and we need an extra ref.' I would be like
'yeah sure I'll do it.' Over the years just networked and just met some really
great people.

BOGGS: What do you guys do outside of Derby?

ELMORE: I don't know, just hangout, grab dinner, drinks. We've got random PR
events we'll do, or fundraising events. That's pretty much it, but that's pretty
much all I do with anybody [laughter].

BOGGS: Can you think of any challenges you faced either here at Tech or after
you graduated with derby or in the workplace. Anything you would want to talk about?

ELMORE: The only time there were really challenges was when the plant would shut
down from lack of electricity, which is important, electricity is important. And
so then I'd have to go on night shift for a month and start the place back up
and that would impact my ability to go to practice and I would have to ask my
boss if I could have a day off to go ref a bout, or this year to go play in one,
and then go back to work the next night. Those have really been the only times
it's been an impact . They've been really great to work with because other
people do things like, they've got kids who play football or softball. One of the
guys on my hall at work he's one of the coaches at Christiansburg High's
football team. So he just comes in earlier so he can leave earlier and go be at
practice. We just make our little arrangements like that.

BOGGS: Where do you work again? Sorry.

ELMORE: It's Celanese. It's a chemical plant about thirty minutes away in Giles
County, between Pearisburg and Narrows. Or 'Narras' [pronounces with an accent]
as the locals call it.

BOGGS: What do you do?

ELMORE: I'm a Maintenance Engineer. So things break and I figure out why, and if
things break frequently I try to dig more into it and see what's really causing
it. Are there process issues? Is it metallurgy concerns? Are there adjustments
that are supposed to be made that are not getting made? A lot of
troubleshooting, investigating, also trying to engage our mechanics in safety
culture which is not the most fun part of my job. I would rather get greasy and
dirty and solve problems, so I guess that's why I became an engineer.

BOGGS: You mentioned you would play with Legos in your childhood, so you kind of knew

ELMORE: Oh yeah.

BOGGS: But how did that evolve with your personal identity, or if it had any
intersection at all?

ELMORE: Having that sense of I like to fix things and solve problems and put
things in their right place, I think, helped because it gave me an outlet to
figure out what was going on in my head like in a rational sort of sense. One of
the sessions with my therapist when I was debating whether to start hormone
treatments I made a pro and con list: here's all the reasons why it would be good
and here's all the reasons why it would be bad. Then we would talk about it and
some of them would be more facetious than others. Then eventually the right one
won out.

BOGGS: Was there a deciding factor?

ELMORE: Just kind of feeling, intuition.

BOGGS: Was it on your list?

ELMORE: No it wasn't [laughs]. I wanted to be as rational about it as I could.
But once we talked through, especially talked through the cons, and realized
that those downsides that I had really weren't that big a deal things that I
really cared about, I just was like 'yeah, I think this is what I need to do.'
Something went off in my brain like Finally! You've finally gotten the message!
We've been onto you for this for years even tried to drop you some hints when
you were twelve and you wouldn't listen.' Like when puberty started, I hated it!
Oh god, the hair on my face and everywhere else and I was like eww this is ugh .
Get this away from me, get this off me. But the brain is really adaptable so I
just kind of dealt with it and things sort of worked themselves out. Sort of, I
guess [laughs].

BOGGS: I'd say so. When you were at Tech here were you involved with the Hokie
Pride? I'm not sure if it was called

ELMORE: Not at all.

BOGGS: Did you know anyone who was?

ELMORE: Yeah. I had some gay friends and it was just one of those things like,
'oh that's cool. You gotta do whatcha gotta do.' It wasn't a community I had any
interest in doing anything with, just no vested interest in it. Yeah I just
didn't really have any vested interest in it at the time.

BOGGS: Are you involved in it now?

ELMORE: Yeah much more now. Not so much at Virginia Tech, I'm still trying to
figure out am I too old to be doing anything with the university because I'm just
an alum and I'm 28. But when this transition started becoming more and more real
my mom reached out to New River Valley PFLAG and so I started going with her and
met some really great people there. That's kind of gotten me branching out and
helping with the rest of the LGBTQ community, so this isn't the first interview
that I've done before. I really think the best outreach that I do is just
showing up to work everyday in blue collar boys club USA.

BOGGS: Yeah how's that?

ELMORE: I thought they would chase me out of town with torches and pitchforks.
Somewhere in the back of my head I thought 'yeah that's gonna happen,' but no
everybody's been great. I had a hunch that people are generally better than we
give them credit for, especially in terms of Appalachian culture. We want to do
right by people even if something seems kind of weird or strange. If they care
about you then they'll just may not necessarily agree with what your doing,
which a lot of people at work are that way. They still won't treat me any
differently and they'll have fun with me. One day, the first day I came in with
these really tall boots, someone made a joke like 'dang you bringing in your
Durango boots today,' I said 'well they show off my legs.' When I came out
someone was like 'Ok so you're going to be a girl now. Can we still fuck around
with you?' [ELMORE replies] 'Oh, it would be weird if you didn't.' [worker
replies] 'Okay, cool, just wanted to be sure.'

BOGGS: So this was happening while you were at work?

ELMORE: Yeah so I've worked there since 2009 and as time went on, I guess
starting in maybe 2011, the time frame's a little fuzzy, there was rampant
alcohol abuse that makes the time frame a little fuzzy, which I actually really
hate. I actually started having a Dexter style double life where I would go out
dressed certain ways with certain company and have to keep pictures untagged on
Facebook like 'don't tag me on Facebook! I swear don't do it,' because I would
be friends with people at work and they would see it and bad things would
happen. Whenever I would go out I would have to shave all my body hair. I
couldn't do it in the summer because then I'd be wearing t-shirts and people
would be going 'why are your arms so bare?' So I had to play it seasonally, like
'oh winter is coming I actually get to do this stuff now,' which ironically
broke my heart when it started to get warmer because then I had to kind of let
that hibernate for a while. Then I just couldn't do that anymore, it was
exhausting. It was not who I was and so I started figuring out how I was gonna
come out in a place that has a fifteen on the Human Rights Council score. I'd
heard snippets of conversations from people about 'so and so's gay it ain't no
big deal,' just in passing not about me. Just conversations in general, you hear
certain things people say and you store it in your mind for later processing or
like that's an interesting data point. Things started to come together. They
[Celanese] had a new CEO that was really trying to have a big diversity push. We
had gotten a new Plant Manager who was from Sweden and I thought 'oh she's gonna
bring some European sensibilities here.' And just my gut instinct from what I
knew of the people that, 'I think this is going to be okay. I think the timing
is right.' So once I had given myself enough hormone time- whenever I had to
tell my boss 'hey I'm gonna need to have Friday off, I need to go to UVA.' [boss
replies] 'What do you have to go to UVA for? Is everything okay?' 'Yeah, yeah everything is fine I have to see an endocrinologist.'
 'What the-an endo what?' 'They deal with glands and stuff.'
'Oh alright, everything's alright though?' 'Yeah I just have to
get some stuff  looked at.' 'Oh okay. Cool.' So they were great about
that, but I wouldn't tell them why until, so I started hormoning in April and my
plan was around the end of the year I should be transitioned enough that the
face would look less masculine and things would develop and I would just be,
what's the word for when babies develop in the womb? 

BOGGS: Oh gosh, I have no idea.

ELMORE: [Laughs] Alright well I had cooked long enough, let's go with that. So I
sat down with my boss, my former boss, they work closely and in similar roles
and I just set up a meeting with a nebulous title like 'discussing the future.'
They were like 'so you called us in here. What is this for?' I had this cup of
coffee and was shaking like it was gonna spill everywhere and they said 'c'mon
you're shaking like a leaf. What's going on?' So I told them what I had been up
to over the past year and what my desires were going forward. I said 'for the
last nine months I have been taking estrogen and testosterone blockers and it's
the best thing I've ever did and I've never been so happy.' They said 'oh,
really?' 'Yeah, yeah, yeah, so I'm gonna be like a woman now.'
They were like 'that is so cool! I've never known anyone that's done that, how
did you know?' So I told them the whole story and they said 'that's really
fascinating, wow.' So we talked about what we would say to HR and how to move
forward and when we talked to HR they didn't really know what to do. No one had
apparently done this before in the entire seventy year history of Celanese, this
was a first, which blew my mind. So I gave our HR department some reference
material some different organizations to talk to, gave them PFLAG information,
gave them some Allen Equal [sp] I think it was their website and contact
information. So they talked with some corporate HR people and it turned out
there was already the beginnings of an LGBTQ diversity initiative. So we just
kind of jumped in with that, so we worked out a plan; we were gonna wait until
the New Year when people are back from holidays and just kind of make an
announcement to the management. Then we would do little small group sessions
with all the mechanics that I work with, then maintenance. There's about one
hundred or so mechanics I work with on a routine basis, so we figured small
group sessions. That way if anyone had any questions or concerns or religious
fervor, there was some of that, not as much as I thought there would be, but
there was some. Meeting with the management people I was horrified, terrified,
just completely frightened, but our HR manager said what was going on and people
were just so happy for me. Our operations manager said 'I've never been so proud
of you before. It takes a lot of guts to do what you're doing especially in a
place like this.' People kept saying how brave I was, how courageous I was. But
it didn't feel like that for me; for me I was just doing what I gotta do, not
trying to make a statement or anything. I'm just trying to live, it's this or
the alternative and the alternative is much colder and more eternal and I didn't
want to do that. So I started having the small group sessions with our
maintenance personnel, who are all most of them have side enterprises as farmers
or mechanics auto mechanics, so it is very blue collar, very well-to-do kind of
people. I've built up a good relationship with them over the years and joke
around with them about stuff. I already had a reputation as being kind of
strange for roller derby, so most of the questions I got when we, me and my boss
and their foremen, had these meetings, most of the questions were around 'what's
your name gonna be?' 'What bathroom are you going to use?' Regarding that, there
are unisex bathrooms scattered around, so we figured well that's probably the
easiest thing for now and we'll figure out when to start using the female ones
sometime later when we're all used to this, which that time is now and we're
working on that. I let people know early on that they could ask me anything,
anything, nothing's off the table here. So they ask me everything that you would
expect, maybe not expect people to ask, but what you would secretly want to ask
but don't want to be rude about it. So some people were more tactful about the
questions than others. One person was just very blunt about the question, he
said 'so can I ask you something?' I said 'yeah oh god what is it Aaron?' 'so you gonna get your dick cut off?' [Laughs] I said 'that's why I like
you.' I was just like 'I don't know. It's taken me this long to figure out what
the hell I'm doing in life, I'll deal with that later.'

BOGGS: Do you think that since you were so open about it, that's why people were
so accepting?

ELMORE: I think so.

BOGGS: If you had been more repressed it might have been

ELMORE: I think it would have been more uncomfortable, but I came into it with a
sense of humor and I let everyone know I didn't want to have the vibe of 'if you
say anything about this you're gonna be in trouble.' I wanted to have the sense
of 'yeah, it's really weird. It's totally uncomfortable for everybody. It's new,
lets just figure it out together and have some fun with it.' But there was some
backlash, a few people, one guy was like 'Well I don't believe in any of this
stuff, you mean I gotta work with him?' I just thought 'whoa dude.' So then my
boss jumped in and just snarled at him and said 'Yes that's exactly what you're
going to do.' I thought 'yay. Go Chuck, yay.' And then one guy said something
about, this is all because of Obama's America [laughter] and we have all turned
from the Lord Jesus Christ. I thought 'I'm telling you I'm becoming a chick. How
does Obama come into this?' Things that just make you go buh? [exasperated
noise]! So yeah that really happened. There were other people though that as
these meetings were spaced out over a week that rumors and stories spread
around. So we got this little meting coming up and this is what it is going to
be about. So some people would give me warnings like, 'now I believe in the Holy
Bible and I believe in the Lord Jesus and everything the book says, so I just
want to know if you're sure that this is what you want to do. It may have
eternal consequences.' I kept a poker face, but I would just roll my eyes and my
head like oh dear God. But I thought about it, and I think if they didn't care
about me at all they wouldn't have even bothered, but because they did believe
that that was a thing, a risk, a worry and that they expressed it, that they
actually cared about me as a person, because they didn't say it from a place of
damnation or you're going to hell for this. It was more from a place of concern,
like genuine concern. So I tried to understand people's meaning and context more
than the actual words that they were saying. One guy gave me a whole big list of
pages of Bible verses to read and study over. So it is coming from a place of
concern not judgment.

BOGGS: Did you read the list?

ELMORE: I did. Some of them contradicted each other, surprise! But, it was what
they believed and that's fine. Our working relationships haven't really changed
much. People have told me, since I started coming to work how I want to,
that, they would just look at me and say 'you just look so much happier. You're
just so much brighter and cheerier and just seem so happy.' I told them 'I am.'
So I think that people are understanding that it's not just a choice people make
it's something that you just gotta do. That they see how I was before and how I
am now and they think about how much happier I am as a person and how much that
makes it easier to work with someone when they're happy and people want other
people to be happy. Its just been a really, mostly great experience.

BOGGS: You mentioned that you had to go to UVA to see an endocrinologist?

ELMORE: Yeah.

BOGGS: Why did you have to go so far?

ELMORE: Uh, I tried a couple of endocrinologists around here. One guy in
Princeton thought, when I said on the phone I was looking for hormone
replacement, that I was low on testosterone and needed to boost it and I was
like 'Oh no, no, no, no, no I want to go the other way with it.' He said 'Oh I
don't have any training for that.' I wanted to be like I've read what the
training is, it's really not that hard. Prescribe a couple things and watch
levels, but whatever you're a doctor I'm not. And then I tried this other guy
and he seemed on the edge of senility and I didn't get a sense of comfort that
he knew what he was doing. He told me, the guy from Princeton told me, my
therapist had told me you'll probably have to go to UVA for this. So I ended up
having to go to UVA for this, but gotta do it. So they were really top notch,
still are and it's a good two and a half hours away just to go see a doctor,
which in a sense seems ridiculous. I have a friend that went female to male and
he is having to go to Lynchburg for his shots. I just think why can't, why don't
doctors know this stuff. I mean I know malpractice and liability's a concern but
come on, you know, a couple hours of training and I'm sure that would be
sufficient. Why is that not more prevalent?

BOGGS: Where did you, you said that you read the training, where did you get that?

ELMORE: [I] read some documents from the Endocrine Society and WPATH, I can't
remember what it stands for its World something Association for Transgender
Health. There's guidelines about what the patient should exhibit and what in
terms of gender dysphoria and how to start treatment. I think there were even
specifics on doses, recommended starting doses and blood testing frequency and
then you just kind of make adjustments from there until things get in a certain
range. So it seemed like it made sense to me but I'm a mechanical engineer not a
doctor of humans.

BOGGS: When you first started it did you notice anything changing immediately,
or did it take time?

ELMORE: It took some time, but I just instantly felt better. Like 'ahhhh [sigh of
relaxation], like I was finally doing the right thing.

BOGGS: So it wasn't really the treatment; it was just that you knew you were
headed in the right direction?

ELMORE: Yeah, it was very much a psychological impact, but then I'd say three
months or so in my chest started hurting and that's when I was kind of like yea!
Things are happening! So, [aside] Sorry my contact is misbehaving.

BOGGS: I understand that

ELMORE: I might need to take a minute. [pause] Ok I think I got it [laughter].
So, I think the level of emotions I've had has been the most different, multiple
emotions at the same time. Where I don't know how I'm feeling, am I sad, am I
angry, am I frustrated? It's all of them. Surprise, this happens.

BOGGS: You think that's more from the hormones?

ELMORE: I think so. I've cried more in the last sixteen months than I have in
the last sixteen years. Over silly things like, let's see I missed the deadline
to take the PE Exam.

BOGGS: What's that?

ELMORE: Professional Engineering Exam. So then I cried. In hindsight I'm like
that's a stupid reason to cry, but it just happens. Every now and then I get
home from work and I'm having a bad day and I'm like I'm just gonna curl up on
the couch and watch something sad and cry, just gotta have a cry.

BOGGS: I understand that.

ELMORE:But I like it more. I actually get a sense that I can express my emotions
instead of before when I would feel angry or frustrated it would just brew and
there was no outlet for it. Now it's like I feel the negative emotion, I get it
out and I move on with life. It's such a bea- I almost just said better and
easier, beasier [laughs] way of way of dealing with it, in my experience.

BOGGS: You mentioned your mother took you to PFLAG, so was that something she
just did on her own? You had no idea?

ELMORE: Yeah, she just reached out on her own. I think she wasn't surprised that
something was going to be happening. After some research and study, reflecting
on her own family experience, her sister is very, I don't even know the right
word, I think she had some Bi [sexual] tendencies. Very gender queer kind of
fluidity. So, then we did some research we found out when my grandmother was
trying to get pregnant with my mother she took a pregnancy drug called DES. It
was some kind of synthetic estrogen that has a long complicated name and they
have since banned it. But I think they still use it with farm animals. They
found that first generation, second generation, and some third generation
offspring had statistically higher than normal chances of gender dysphoria, and
homosexuality. So, I heard that and I was like 'Oh! Well there we go, okay that
makes sense now.'

BOGGS: So you kind of embraced that?

ELMORE: Yeah, well I guess I'm just kind of stuck with it. It's the genetic
lottery. My mom didn't get it, my brother didn't get it, but yay I did.

BOGGS: Did you ever talk to your aunt about anything?

ELMORE: Mmhm, she was great. I could tell her that I had a secret urge to go
slice up people and put them in dumpster and she'd be like, 'Oh why do you want
to do that?' She couldn't be phased. So, she was always my go to for, I feel
something strange and I want to talk to someone about it.

BOGGS: So in your family it was mainly your mom and your aunt?

ELMORE: Mmhm, my dad hasn't had a problem with this, but he's always been the
more pragmatic one. When I first told him I'm transgender after he processed it,
he was more concerned about things like my career, the job I was at and how that
would be affected. But that's who he is and he knew that if it was gonna make me
happier, then it's what I needed to do. So they've been outstandingly
supportive. My mom and me have a better relationship now than I think we ever
have just because we have so much in common. We went and got our feet done
yesterday; we just hang out a lot and go shopping, and have wine nights together
and it's just like this whole new experience.

BOGGS: No kidding. So, as far as dating, you don't have to talk about it if you
don't want to but, how has that changed?

ELMORE: I avoided it mostly over the past couple years since I knew something
was probably on the horizon, so I avoided dating like the plague. That's not to
say that there weren't forays in the night, but I didn't actively pursue a
relationship. I actually had a date last weekend. That was my first date in a
good couple of years.

BOGGS: How did it go?

ELMORE: Great, it was really great. She was really cool. We met after a derby
bout; she bought me a shot cause she saw me play and said 'you kicked ass out
there, I need to buy you a shot!' I was like 'okay.'

BOGGS: Have you talked to her since?

ELMORE: Yeah we talk a lot. We've talked about how we are going to do our next
date because she lives in Fredericksburg, so we talked about maybe doing a home
and home sort of thing where I go to Fredericksburg one weekend and she comes to
Blacksburg one weekend. So we're working it out.

BOGGS: What would you do, what would you want to do as a date?

ELMORE: I have no idea, just kind of figure it out as we go along. Things like
the weather would have a play in it. Maybe we go to the Cascades that's always
fun, especially when it's frozen.

BOGGS: Yeah

ELMORE: It just depends. Maybe there's something crazy going on that weekend
that we can check out.

BOGGS: I don't have anymore questions. Is there anything else you want to talk
about? This has been incredibly interesting and great.

ELMORE: Let me think. I don't know, are there any common themes that you've
found in other interviews?

BOGGS: Well you're our first.

ELMORE: Oh! Patient zero. Yeah in general I think I have been amazed at how I'm
not sure if accepting is the right word, but willingness to roll with, or maybe
it is acceptance, I don't know. When I think about people, real Appalachian
people have really been with this whole thing. I think a lot of it has to do
with how happy someone really is when they go through with it and realizing that
you're basically the same person just kind of different on the outside and maybe
a few different mannerisms, but sense of humor goes a long way with people. That
is probably the biggest thing that I have observed and experienced with how to
deal with people you might be leery of being yourself around.

BOGGS: Well thank you so much. This was a great first interview.

ELMORE: Good happy to do it.

 </transcript><rights>Permission to publish material from the Virginia Tech LGBTQ Oral History Collection must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech</rights><fmt>audio</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation>MS2015-007_VTLGBTQ_ElmoreTori.xml</xmllocation><xmlfilename>MS2015-007_VTLGBTQ_ElmoreTori.xml</xmlfilename><collection_link>http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/collections/show/86</collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>