<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT><record id="00015317" dt="2015-08-05"><version>4</version><date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2014-11-05</date><date_nonpreferred_format>2014-11-05</date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id></cms_record_id><title>Interview with Michael Sutphin, November 5, 2014</title><accession>Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_SutphinMichael</accession><duration></duration><collection_id>Ms2015-007</collection_id><collection_name>The Virginia Tech LGBTQ Oral History Collection</collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Virginia Tech Special Collections</repository><repository_url /><subject>sexual minorities</subject><subject>university history</subject><subject>local/regional history and appalachian south</subject><interviewee>Michael Sutphin</interviewee><interviewer>Molly Lash</interviewer><file_name>Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_SutphinMichael_OralHistory.mp3</file_name><sync>1:|31(2)|51(9)|71(13)|87(12)|115(9)|141(3)|157(9)|172(5)|193(11)|217(4)|230(3)|249(5)|277(10)|294(5)|325(2)|341(15)|361(5)|373(11)|391(6)|416(3)|444(14)|464(8)|478(8)|498(10)|518(7)|530(10)|549(9)|562(5)|593(1)|611(2)|638(2)|654(6)|690(16)|710(9)|730(11)|753(11)|779(8)|799(1)|828(15)|859(7)|874(12)|894(1)|925(3)</sync><media_id></media_id><media_url>http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/files/original/76/Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_SutphinMichael/Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_SutphinMichael_OralHistory.mp3</media_url><mediafile><host>Other</host><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>audio</clip_format></mediafile><language>English</language><index><point><time>100</time><title>Identity</title><partial_transcript>LASH: Cool, okay, so how would you say you identify yourself?

SUTPHIN: I identify as gay. Is that what you‚Äôre looking for? Or do you want, like broader than that like middle class or something?</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>129</time><title>Coming Out in high school</title><partial_transcript>SUTPHIN: Yeah, so I came out when I was 15 to my friends in high school. I told my best friend first, then I told a few other friends and then it kind of spread to everyone else because it‚Äôs high school. I told my parents a year later when I was 16. I don‚Äôt remember if I was a sophomore or a junior, I remember being 16 years old when I told my parents. I told my parents in a letter‚Ä¶I don‚Äôt know if that‚Äôs useful information or not. I‚Äôve just always been a writer and it‚Äôs just easier</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>364</time><title>Coming to Tech</title><partial_transcript>LASH: And when you got here in 2002 was there a large gay community, like LGBT support?

SUTPHIN: Yeah, so when I first came, my freshman year, when I first started in college, my biggest social support actually came from my hallmates. I lived in Thomas Hall. At the time it was all male and it wasn‚Äôt a cadet dorm.
</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>407</time><title>Joining the LGBTA and attending Board of Visitors protest in Spring 2003</title><partial_transcript>I did, my first semester, join the LGBTA, it‚Äôs now changed its name this year to Hokie Pride, so I got involved with that. I was just kind of like a member who just came to the meetings and sat in the back for a while, but then I got really interested when, the Spring of 2003, my freshman year there was a‚Äîwell, I should‚Äîyeah I‚Äôll just start there. There was a controversy because the Virginia Tech Board of Visitors removed sexual orientation from the non-discrimination policy. And there was a whole series of protests and I went to this one big protest in front of Buruss Hall, so after that I got really excited about being involved. For like background, there was a faculty member, Shelli Fowler, who, they didn‚Äôt approve her‚Ä¶
</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>498</time><title>Becoming an officer in the LGBTA and organizing Freedom to Marry Day</title><partial_transcript>SUTPHIN: But I got like really interested after that. So they were having like an election for officers at the end of my freshman year for‚Ä¶did they? Well, they had an opening because someone left and then for this position it was like Presidential Advisor or Presidential Counselor or something like that. It was just like an at-large officer position. So, I ran for that and got that. And then I became the office manager for the LGBTA and during that time I organized in 2004 the Freedom to Marry Day‚Äî
</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>584</time><title>LGBTA President and the SafeWatch Program</title><partial_transcript>LASH: And then, when I was looking into that, it said that you helped start the Safe Watch?

SUTPHIN: Yeah, so when I was president in 2005, we started a campaign, we called it the ‚ÄúGive a Damn‚Äù campaign‚Äî</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>901</time><title>Interest in local government and Running for Blacksburg Town Council</title><partial_transcript>SUTPHIN: So, apart from the LGBT history things, so, I wrote for the Collegiate Times about local government, so that‚Äôs how I got interested. My mother did some lobbying and advocacy work, so even when I was in high school, sometimes I went to the general assembly with her when she was meeting with delegates and senators, and I saw her testify before a senate subcommittee hearing, and things like that. So I‚Äôve always been kind of interested in politics more generally, and LGBT issues specifically. But I‚Äôve also, before I was elected, for a year I was on the town‚Äôs long range planning committee, which does the town‚Äôs comprehensive plan, which is a vision for the future, and I was on the town‚Äôs housing board before I was elected, so I was always interested in kind of other things that were happening in the town. So I realize it was kind of trendsetting. Before I was elected, there had only been five LGBT elected officials in Virginia</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>1117</time><title>Town of Blacksburg starts offering same-sex partner benefits to town employees</title><partial_transcript>SUTPHIN: But thankfully, after the Supreme Court kind of non-decision recently, those problems have all been fixed.

LASH: Yeah, which is awesome.
      
SUTPHIN: It was within a couple days that the town of Blacksburg started offering same-sex partner benefits. So, similar to Virginia Tech, did the same thing. 
           </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>1222</time><title>Equality Virginia</title><partial_transcript>LASH: [Laughter] So, can you tell us more about your work with Equality Virginia?
      
SUTPHIN: Yeah, sure. So I joined in 2010. So I lost my race in 2009 because there were too many people running. There were ten people on the ballot for like three and a half seats. I could explain‚Äî
      </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>1458</time><title>Changes in LGBT support since college</title><partial_transcript>LASH: Yeah, do you feel like overall since were in college or since when you came out for example, do you feel like it has changed‚Äî

SUTPHIN: Oh, yes. 

LASH: from facing the bad things to focusing on good things that can be changed?

SUTPHIN: Oh yeah, definitely. There‚Äôs been‚Äîeven if you look at polling numbers, way more people are in support of LGBT issues now. And the country itself has probably moved, even though I know the Senate just became Republican. The country itself has moved, especially on LGBT issues, to the left. And social issues in general, I think. Yeah, it feels like a very different climate to me than it was even ten years ago. 
</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point></index><type></type><description></description><rel /><transcript>Interview with Michael Sutphin

Date of Interview: November 5, 2014 Interviewer: Molly Lash Assistant: Amanda
Lilly Place of Interview: Michael Sutphin's residence, Blacksburg, Virginia
Length: 43:20 Transcribers: Molly Lash, Amanda Lilly, Claire Gogan

Amanda Lilly: Yeah, go ahead.

Molly Lash: It's November 5th, 2014. This is Molly Lash and I'm interviewing
Michael Sutphin in his home in Blacksburg, Virginia.

LILLY: You're good.

LASH: Cool, okay, so I'm just going to start with some basic questions. Can you
tell us your name, place of birth, and about, like, your family and where you
were raised?

Michael Sutphin: Sure, I'm Michael David Sutphin. I was born in Knoxville,
Tennessee at the University of Tennessee Memorial Hospital. I lived in Tennessee
for about three years, then after that my family moved to Asheville, North
Carolina and then I lived there for about seven years, so when I was 10 or 11 we
moved to just outside of Williamsburg, Virginia. So I went to middle school and
high school in Williamsburg.

LASH: I'm from Newport News

SUTPHIN: Oh yeah?

LASH: So, really close by [laughs].

SUTPHIN: I went to Lafeyette High School. Let's see, then I came to Virginia
Tech in 2002 and graduated in 2006. Since then I've worked for the Universityó

SUTPHIN: Let's see, about my family and other biographical information?

LASH: Yeah, just about how you were raisedó

SUTPHIN: Um, I'm an only child, my parents are still married. Let's see, my
mother was a teacher for about ten years, then she did some lobbying when I was
in high school. And my dad designed nuclear submarines for a living.

LASH: That's awesome [laughs]

SUTPHIN: So, he retired a couple years ago from doing that.

LASH: Cool, okay, so how would you say you identify yourself?

SUTPHIN: I identify as gay. Is that what you're looking for? Or do you want,
like broader than that like middle class or something?

LASH: [Laughter] No, just related to the project. So when you were growing up in
the Williamsburg area, were you out in high school or was that something that
happened more when you came to Tech?

SUTPHIN: Yeah, so I came out when I was 15 to my friends in high school. I told
my best friend first, then I told a few other friends and then it kind of spread
to everyone else because it's high school. I told my parents a year later when I
was 16. I don't remember if I was a sophomore or a junior, I remember being 16
years old when I told my parents. I told my parents in a letterÖI don't know if
that's useful information or not. I've just always been a writer and it's just easier

LASH: To write down things

SUTPHIN: To write out your thoughts than tell them in person sometimes. So, I
gave my mom the letter then my mom gave it to my dad so, it was the same thing.

[Front door opens and closes]

LASH: So how was that experience for you?

SUTPHIN: Let's see, so that would have been in like, 1999, 2000 kind of era so
it was a little bit different than the country is now, I would say. So people
were a little bit less tolerant. I did lose this group of friends that I hung
out with. I wasn't friends with them anymore when I first came out. I found
another group of friends. And they never explicitly said ìwe're not hanging out
with you because you're gayî or something like that. It justÖthey were friends
that went away. Um, I wouldn't be surprised if you've heard similar stories from
other people, that kind of thing. Ummmómy parents were very accepting. I grew up
in a very liberal house. I wasn't raised in a church or anything like that, so I
didn't have any religious hang ups or anything. Let's see, it's kind of an
interesting story that the day I came out to my parents, because I was almost
suspended from school that day for something completely unrelatedó

 [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: So I broke into the computer system at my high school just to, like,
play a prank. So, then, I was caught and the assistant principal called my mom
and my mom kept asking me why I was acting out. And I said, ìcan I write it in a
letter?î And so that was why I wrote the letter. My mom read the letter and she
came and she talked to me for a little bit, and then when my dad came home from
work she gave the letter to him. I could hear themó I was in the bedroom above
where the living room is so I could hear what they were saying, then my dad came
upstairs and like the first thing he said to me was, ëhow did you hack into the
school computer system?'

 [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: He was more intrigued by this, soó

 

LASH: But I feel likeóI feel like that's good. I would be more intrigued by
that, too, to be honest

SUTPHIN: [laughs] Yeah.

LASH: That's a pretty elaborate prank! [laughs]

SUTPHIN: My dad, when he was still working for Newport News Shipbuilding

LASH: Oh yeah.

SUTPHIN: It was owned by Northrop Grumman at the time, and they used to have,
where they did Pride Month, where they put posters around the buildings to
celebrate June is Pride Month for LGBT awareness. And when the company spinned
off into its own company and they stopped doing that and instead just sent out
an email, they didn't put up posters, and my dad didn't like that so he made his
own Pride Month posters he designed and put them around the building. I don't
know if it was to show support for his son or to anger some of his conservative
co-workers or something like that [laughs].

 

LASH: That's pretty funny, though. Because, yeah, that area thoughóthat would
anger people, but yeah, I like that. [laugh] So, when you got to Tech was it a
transition from you from after that in high school?

SUTPHIN: I liked going to college much more than high school

LASH: Yeah

SUTPHIN: for sure. Because even though my high school had 1400 people, suddenly
in college it was

LASH: Thousands

SUTPHIN: 30,000 people or whatever it was, 25,000 people. So there's a whole lot
more, like in my high school, I don't remember there being other, there were
certainly other gay people, there weren't other openly gay people like me. But
going to college, there were a lot more. People would be in my friend group, or
dating group, or whatever, so, yeah, college was definitely much better.

LASH: And when you got here in 2002 was there a large gay community, like LGBT support?

SUTPHIN: Yeah, so when I first came, my freshman year, when I first started in
college, my biggest social support actually came from my hallmates. I lived in
Thomas Hall. At the time it was all male and it wasn't a cadet dorm.

LASH: Yeah

SUTPHIN: And it was kind of separated from the rest of campus, so we were kind
of out in the wilderness of Virginia Tech's campus. So I made friends with them.
I don't remember if any of them specifically were gay, but they were definitely
more accepting than my high school had been. They knew I was gay. I did, my
first semester, join the LGBTA, it's now changed its name this year to Hokie
Pride, so I got involved with that. I was just kind of like a member who just
came to the meetings and sat in the back for a while, but then I got really
interested when, the Spring of 2003, my freshman year there was aówell, I
shouldóyeah I'll just start there. There was a controversy because the Virginia
Tech Board of Visitors removed sexual orientation from the non-discrimination
policy. And there was a whole series of protests and I went to this one big
protest in front of Buruss Hall, so after that I got really excited about being
involved. For like background, there was a faculty member, Shelli Fowler, who,
they didn't approve herÖ

LASH: Spousal

SUTPHIN: Öyeah, her spousal hire around that time as well. I think that actually
happened the semester before I came but it was still like an issue because of
this discrimination thing. And thankfully after a month the Board of Visitors
reversed its decision. So the Collegiate Times article the next day from that
protest, it was in March, said that the protestors had stormed Buruss Hall. I
was there and I don't know if there was much storming. We did go inside Buruss
Hall, but I still like to think that I stormed Buruss Hall.

LASH: [Laughter] A little bit of empowerment

SUTPHIN: It wasn't like, no one was arrested or anything like that. There was
just signs and speeches and stuff like tható

LASH: Yeah

SUTPHIN: But I got like really interested after that. So they were having like
an election for officers at the end of my freshman year forÖdid they? Well, they
had an opening because someone left and then for this position it was like
Presidential Advisor or Presidential Counselor or something like that. It was
just like an at-large officer position. So, I ran for that and got that. And
then I became the office manager for the LGBTA and during that time I organized
in 2004 the Freedom to Marry Dayó

LASH: You mentioned tható

SUTPHIN: They had had Freedom to Marry Day events before, but they were usually
like a table in front of Squires to have people sign a petition saying that
there should be marriage equality. So, I stepped it up a bit and had a protest
that we organized on the Drillfield kind of in the format of a wedding, but it's
obvioulsy, no one's actuallyó

LASH: Yeah, I think I saw the pictures of tható

SUTPHIN: Yeah, so people instead of exchanging vows they exchanged vows to fight
for marriage equality kind of thing. So I organized the first one of those
demonstrations and it carried on. It's no longer relevant, I don't think they'll
have it anymore since we have marriage equality, but it was a tradition for a
little while there. So I was very excited to organize that. And then I was the
president of the LGBTA the year after that.

LASH: And then, when I was looking into that, it said that you helped start the
Safe Watch?

SUTPHIN: Yeah, so when I was president in 2005, we started a campaign, we called
it the ìGive a Damnî campaignó

 [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: We actually had these bracelets. John Gray has one of the bracelets.
Mine got lost. So I gave a speechówe had been organizing it for a few months to
kind of raise awareness about harassment on campus and it was sort of like a
precursor to the ìIt Gets Betterî campaign, but there wasn't anything called ìIt
Gets Better.î But it was trying to do that kind of work with dealing with
harassment and bullying on campus, and there had been a series of incidents that
had happenedónot to me, specifically, but to other people I knew or that were in
the LGBT community, where we didn't think that the university administration was
responding adequately to it. It wasn't their fault, but they're also responsible
for creating a safe environment. And a safe campus climate. So I gave a speech
at the celebration of diversity, which is an event they used to have in Burruss,
where different groups did like shows and speeches, or things like that, and
that kicked offóand in the speech, I used the phrase ìgive a damnî at one
pointóand somehow, I didn't name this campaign, I would have probably named it
something else without profanity. Yeah.

 [Laughter]

And so, after that we kind of organized to raise awareness about this and we had
several meetings with the university administration, so the provost called these
meetings with us because we were doing this campaign, this anti-harassment
campaign. Out of that came a program called Safe Watch, which was kind of a
centralized way of how the university handled harassment. Students, faculty,
staff, anyone could, if they saw something, they could report it and it would
get handled centrally. There was a website and they had a process for handling
those sorts of things. It doesn't exist anymore, it's kind of folded in with the
other anti-harassment efforts. And after that, with the April 16th shootings in
2007, the university changed again how it was handling reporting incidents. So
it became less relevant, but it was a big deal for us in 2005. It was very
empowering that we wereó

LASH: No, that's awesome

SUTPHIN: dealing with our issue.

LASH: Yeah. I think that's really smart, actually, and I think that's a good way
to have people be able to report things.

SUTPHIN: Yeah

LASH: But so, you were also a Collegiate Times writer, correct?

Sutphin. Yeah, I was theóI started out as a staff writer for the Collegiate
Times, and then over the summer I became the News Editor. And then there was an
opening for News Editor that fall because someone left, so I was the News
Editor. The fall of my senior year. And then we split up the News Editor
position, and there were multiple News Editor positions, and I became the City
Editor. So I covered everything off campus that happened, so, Blacksburg. I went
to the town council meetings and now I'm on the town council.

LASH: Yeah

SUTPHIN: So I've been interviewed by Collegiate Times reporters and gone full circle.

LASH: [Laughter] That must be interesting

SUTPHIN: Yeah

LASH: But so obviously you stayed after you graduated and you work for the
veterinary school now?

SUTPHIN: Yeah, so, after I graduated, I searched for jobs all around the state
and all around the Mid Atlantic area, and I was offered two positions, one was
to be like a local government and breaking news reporter for the Northern
Virginia Daily, which would have been really fun, I really like government, and
I like breaking news stories sort of stuff, but the hours for that job were
going to be 3 to 11 pm Monday through Friday, and like, every third Saturday,
and they wanted to pay me $24,000 a year to live in Northern Virginia, which
would have been the rent

LASH: [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: So even though I, I like flirted with the idea of taking this job, I
didn't end up taking it. But I was offered, thankfully, two days later after I
turned down that one, well I guess a few days after the interview, I think it
was actually the same day I turned down that offer, I got the call for the offer
for the Virginia Tech job. So I worked, I was a writer for the communications
department in the college of Ag and Life Sciences, and I did that for five
years, and then in 2011, I became the public relations coordinator for the vet
school. So it's a similar job, but for a different college.

LASH: Gotcha. That's pretty cool. Yeah, so, obviously now you're on town
council. So while I wasówe do research on you guys, not to be creepy

SUTPHIN: Mmm hmm. You Googled me?

LASH: Just a little bit. But yeah, I thought it was really interesting, when I
was reading about when you ran in 2013, correct?

SUTPHIN: Uh, 2011

LASH: 2011?

SUTPHIN: So, I ran twice. I ran in 2009 and lost and 2011 and won.

LASH: Okay, so, but I thought it was interesting because there was all this
information that you gave us, but it was also around, while you were a student
you were very very involved

SUTPHIN: Mmm hmm

LASH: with the LGBTQ and obviously still involved. But, that you ran more on
campaignólike, you ran more for like, the town and more about that.

SUTPHIN: Yeah, I ran more about local government and land use types of issues
than I did on LGBT issues.

LASH: Yeah

SUTPHIN: So, apart from the LGBT history things, so, I wrote for the Collegiate
Times about local government, so that's how I got interested. My mother did some
lobbying and advocacy work, so even when I was in high school, sometimes I went
to the general assembly with her when she was meeting with delegates and
senators, and I saw her testify before a senate subcommittee hearing, and things
like that. So I've always been kind of interested in politics more generally,
and LGBT issues specifically. But I've also, before I was elected, for a year I
was on the town's long range planning committee, which does the town's
comprehensive plan, which is a vision for the future, and I was on the town's
housing board before I was elected, so I was always interested in kind of other
things that were happening in the town. So I realize it was kind of
trendsetting. Before I was elected, there had only been five LGBT elected
officials in Virginia

LASH: And they were all in Northern Virginia

SUTPHIN: Yeah, they were all in like a Washington, DC suburb of some sort. So I
was the first kind of outside of that area. Since then, there's been one other
in Virginia Beach, who I know, actually.

LASH: That's cool

SUTPHIN: Yeah, so I ran, my campaign focused on smart growth types of issues, so
for land use patterns in Blacksburg so the growth is kind of in the center, near
downtown, as opposed to encouraging sprawl. I was very interested in
environmental friendliness, economic development, working together with other
local governments as a region, so those are the sorts of issues I ran on. And
Virginia, Virginia's what's actually called a Dillon Rule state, I don't know if
you've ever heard this term before. So, local governments can have one of two
different types of relationships with the state government. So, one's called
Homestead, which is, they kind of work it out together, sort of like states and
the federal government, divide everything up through Federalism. This is way too
technical and I apologize, you can cut it out of the transcript if you want.

LASH: No, it's fine [laughter]

SUTPHIN: So in Virginia, that's not the case. For a local government to do
something, the state government has to give them permission to do it. Dillon was
the name of a Supreme Court justice in the 19th century who wrote this opinion.
Because of that, civil rights types of laws, like LGBT types of issues, aren't
under the purview of local governments. So, on the Blacksburg town council, I
wouldn't be able to even do, like I couldn't start, like, having the Town of
Blacksburg issue marriage licenses. Or change the adoption rules, or something
like that. Or even do like, banning companies from discriminating based on
sexual orientation. All of that is under the purview of the state government.
And state governments haven't given local governments permission to be able to
do that. I have been able to, other than being an out LGBT elected official,
there has been some progress on some issues. Some of it actually started before
I was elected. The Blacksburg town council's very progressive and liberal. So,
before I was elected, there was a resolution, so the town passed a resolution
asking the state to change its nondiscrimination policies to protect LGBT
people, including sexual orientation and gender identity. So that happened. And
the town worked to make its town code gender neutral, so instead of saying ìheî
or ìshe,î in the language in the actual town code, to get rid of some of that.
But it was kind of hamstrung on some other things, like offering employee
benefits, because those are all done through the state law. But thankfully,
after the Supreme Court kind of non-decision recently, those problems have all
been fixed.

LASH: Yeah, which is awesome.

SUTPHIN: It was within a couple days that the town of Blacksburg started
offering same-sex partner benefits. So, similar to Virginia Tech, did the same thing.

LASH: Very cool. I didn't know it was in a couple days. I feel like there would beó

SUTPHIN: Yeah, so they like immediatelyó

LASH: take action like immediately though.

SUTPHIN: Yeah, so the Town Council didn't even have to do anything. I just sent
some emails checking up to make sure that they did it. I was actually, when they
did the Supreme Court opinion, I was sitting next to the town attorney and I
like, read it on my smartphone while I was at this conference in Roanoke and the
town attorney who was sitting next to me was like, ìDoes this mean we can offer
same-sex partner benefits?î and I was like, ìOh, I don't know. Let me check on
that.î And then he gets back to me that afternoon, ìYes, we can.î People have
been trying to do that for decades and then I look over and ask someone and send
an email and then suddenlyó

LASH: You can.

SUTPHIN: We can do it. And it required no actual vote or anything like that
because the Supreme Court recalls the lower court's opinion was that those
marriages were recognized and suddenly they're all recognized. So that was good.
And I do most of my LGBT organizing today through my work on Equality Virginia's boardó

LASH: Yea, I saw that too.

SUTPHIN: Not through the town council. Although the Town Council does go every
year to the General Assembly to lobby them kind of on behalf of the town
government and every time, I bring up LGBT issues. Mostly the workplace
discrimination law, which fails every time. But it's worth asking anyway.

LASH: Yea, I actually interned at the General Assembly when I was in high schooló

SUTPHIN: Oh, did you?

LASH: And I remember the Legislative Aid for the senator I worked for
complaining about that.

SUTPHIN: Yeah

LASH: So yeah. But yeah, it was fun. The General Assembly is an interesting place.

SUTPHIN: [Laughter]

LASH: [Laughter] So, can you tell us more about your work with Equality Virginia?

SUTPHIN: Yeah, sure. So I joined in 2010. So I lost my race in 2009 because
there were too many people running. There were ten people on the ballot for like
three and a half seats. I could explainó

LASH: [Laughter] Three and a half?

SUTPHIN: So there were three real seats and then there was this special election
to fill only a two year term, it's usually a 4 year term. So there were ten. It
was a very confusing election. There were too many people running, it was the
first time the election moved from May to November. Which is good because more
people could vote and students were actually in town and they could vote. Yeah
and it was right after Obama's 2008 election so people were more interested in
politics than they probably are right now. So there were too manyóthere were all
these factors going on at once so I wasn't able to distinguish myself from the
other candidates but I ran again in two years and was much more successful. But,
after I lost the first time, a friend of mine, Molly McClintock, said ìHey, you
didn't get on the Town Council but would you be interested in serving on
Equality Virginia's board? I'm on my third term or third two-year term.î So, she
didn't want to do it anymore and there's term limits. So she asked if I would
represent this area for Equality Virginia's board and I said yes. So I've been
doing that since then and I was elected as Vice Chair last year on Equality
Virginia's board. And presumably, I'll be the chair next year. Although I didn't
time it very well because I'll also be running for reelection next year.

LASH: So that'll be a fun year. [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: Yeah. [Laughter]

LASH: So what are some of theówhat does EqualityVA work to do?

SUTPHIN: Yeah, so it's the statewide LGBT education and advocacy group. The
three major areas that we focus onóand we're the largest LGBT group in the state
of Virginia and we have maybe 25,000 members. That's not to say there's only
25,000 LGBT people in Virginiaó

LASH: That's just how many are part of it.

SUTPHIN: Yeah, 25,000 people. LGBT people and their allies are involved in the
organization. And we focus on three main areas. The first is workplace fairness,
and that involves passing a law that says that you can't fire someone for being
L, G, B, or T. And the second isóI'm probably going to get them out of order,
but that's okayóthe second is like school types of issues and community types of
issues. So ensuring school bullying policies, things like that, include
protections for LGBT people. And the third is family recognition, so that would
include marriage, adoption types of issues. So we look at a whole, kind of broad
range of LGBT issues. Some of it's very political, like we have an annual
lobbying day at the General Assembly that we go and visit every single senator
and delegate every year to talk about upcoming legislation. It's actually
gottenówe probably started in this direction before I came on, but since I've
come on, Equality Virginia's no longer having to fight bad things that come up.
Instead we're pushing for good things to happen. So previously, like when I was
in college, there was a whole variety of really bad bills that came up in the
General Assembly. Like an anti-gay marriage license plate, like a license plate
that says you're against gay marriage. Or aó

LASH: Did that fail?

SUTPHIN: Yeah, that failed.

LASH: Okay, thank goodness.

SUTPHIN: [Laughter]

LASH: [Laughter] You never know sometimes! SUTPHIN: I'll fact check it. I think
failed. And then there was a proposal to ban Gay Straight Alliances in high
schools, so high school students couldn't get together, but I think that failed
also. But anyway, the point is, instead of fighting bad things, we're now trying
to fix laws that don't include LGBT. Which is a better place to be in. The other
side's on the defensive. [Laughter]

LASH: Yeah, do you feel like overall since were in college or since when you
came out for example, do you feel like it has changedó

SUTPHIN: Oh, yes.

LASH: from facing the bad things to focusing on good things that can be changed?

SUTPHIN: Oh yeah, definitely. There's beenóeven if you look at polling numbers,
way more people are in support of LGBT issues now. And the country itself has
probably moved, even though I know the Senate just became Republican. The
country itself has moved, especially on LGBT issues, to the left. And social
issues in general, I think. Yeah, it feels like a very different climate to me
than it was even ten years ago.

LASH: So when you were at Tech, since you were so involved with the LGBT
community, was it a really comfortable place for you? Did it feel like a safe
place? Or since you were fighting so many issues, was itó

SUTPHIN: I felt generally safe. But other than being gay, I do come from a
position of privilege, where I'm white and male and middle class and my parents
paid for my college, so those sorts of things. So I'd imagine for other people
it wouldn't be so safe. Like I said, I had lots of friends and other people who
were involved in the community. Like I know someone who, he went to a party and
was coming back, he was holding his boyfriend's hand while leaving a fraternity
party and some kids decided to pick him and beat him up a little bit. So there
were things like that that happened and I haven't heard stories like that
happening in the last like, five years. It's definitely, I think it's a better
climate. And I think if you polled Virginia Tech students, a large number of
them would be in favor of LGBT issues. I'm not sure you would get the same
result when I started in 2002.

LASH: So afteróobviously the transition from being on campus to being in the
Blacksburg community, is there an LGBTQA community in Blacksburg? Or does it
kind of tie into the one on campus?

SUTPHIN: There is but it ties in pretty heavily with the one on campus. So when
I started, when I first came here in 2002, the LGBTA was the one big
organization, though I suppose there was an LGBT Faculty/Staff caucus at the
time, but I think it was a small number of people. It still is a small number of
people, I've been to some of those meetings.

LASH: [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: But the LGBTA was the big organization and everyone participated in
that. Since then, there's been a whole variety of other organizations pop up.
HokiePRIDE is still the biggest, I think, but there's a group called Queer
Grads, Professionals, and Allies. It's still like a smaller group that maybe has
ten or fifteen members, but they meet regularly at Rivermill or somewhere like
that. To me, it does that young professional or graduate student demographic. I
think the LGBT Faculty/Staff caucus has become bigger. There's a PFLAG group, I
think it's the New River Valley PFLAG, which is for parents, friends of lesbians
and gays. So that has a lot of community members go to that especially parents
who their children came out and they want to find resources for them or
sometimes their kids come with them, that sort of thing. So there's that and
that's become more active over the years. And there's a group called OSTEM, Out
in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math, for LGBT kids and their allies
who are interested in geeky things.

LASH: [Laughter] Yeah, so, the transition was very tied in to the school?

SUTPHIN: Yeah, so I think it was, I've talked to a lot of people in Blacksburg
who are my age, who went to some other school and they came here to work, and
their experience is very different than mine, because I already had a group of
friends. Like, a lot of them left because it's Blacksburg, it's a college town

LASH: [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: But some of them stayed around, like John Gray, for instance.

LASH: Yeah

SUTPHIN: He did leave for two years, but came back.

LASH: [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: So my transition felt kind of seamless, personally. I mean, the group
of people I hang out with from college aren't the same group of people I'm with now.

LASH: Mmm hmm. But finding a space where you feltó

SUTPHIN: Yeah it was much easier to find a space because of that.

LASH: So, were there a lot of places, or are there currently, like in
Blacksburg, where you feel is like a meeting place for the gay, the LGBT
community, or a safer place for them, or do you feel like in generally the wholeó

SUTPHIN: Like, where are the gayest bars? [Laughter] Rivermill, maybe?

LASH: [Laughter] Well not even that, but just like, was there a place on campus,
or a place now, that is kind of a safe place?

SUTPHIN: Well there's things like the Hokie Pride office, and their meeting
locations, wherever they meet, and some of the events that they have, and those
sorts of things. There's not, like, one meeting place. When I was in college,
Sharky's used to be, not in the space it is now, but next door, the tall one
that's, empty right now. Sharky's is actually owned by a lesbian, and she used
to have, every Thursday night was gay night at Sharky's. Unfortunately, I was
not 21 at the time, so I would go sometimes, but they kind ofówhen they moved
from that location to next door, I don't think they really had that much anymore.

LASH: Yeah

SUTPHIN: So there used to be that. There's The Park in Roanoke. A lot of people
go to that. I probably went to it more in college than I do after college, though.

LASH: That makes sense.

SUTPHIN: Yeah

LASH: But yeah, so, you've talked about all these different things that you're
involved in, and is there a primary community that you would associate yourself
with? Do you, like, first and foremost associate yourself with the LGBT community?

SUTPHIN: Probably, yeah. I would say that. I think I've become broader in my
associations, such as in running for Town Council.

LASH: Yeah

SUTPHIN: I used to be able to remember everybody's names, and then when I first
ran for Town Council in 2009óbecause the major way to run for office in this
community is to knock on people's doors. After knocking on everyone's door in
Blacksburg, I no longer remember, like I don't even, are you Amanda? I don't
know. I'm just kidding.

LASH: [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: [Laughter] So yeah, it's definitely become broader, and I've, like I
know some of my neighbors. I know people who workókind of a lot of people who
are involved in local politics, obviously I know the other town council members,
but other people who are a part of like local groups, like the downtown
merchants for example.

LASH: Yeah. And you've done a lot of cool work downtown.

SUTPHIN: Yeah. The town when I first got on did the College Avenue promenade
redevelopment and stuff like that. So I've had a lot of interaction with the
downtown merchants in the business community. Because when you're elected to the
Town Council, they appoint you to all these other committees to represent the
town on. So I'm on, my biggest ones are the MPO, which stands for Metropolitan
Planning Organization, I don't know why this is considered metropolitan, but,
there's a federal law that named it, and they're all called the MPO, wherever
you go. So I've gotten to know other elected officials in the region who are
doing transportation types of things. I'm also on theóI was appointedówhen was
that, last year? I don't know. I was appointed to theóI don't even know. Do you
know how many committees I'm on? Because I don't. You Googled me, soó

LASH: [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: I was appointed to the Board of Directors for the Blacksburg
Partnership, which is an economic development group in town, so I not only now
have a lot of familiarity with people like the downtown merchants, but kind of
the broader, kind of, business community.

LASH: This is not really related to the project, but how do you manage all those
different committees?

SUTPHIN: Not very well. [Laughter]

LASH: Not very well? [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: Some of the committees I'm on meet very infrequently, like the
Agriculture and Forestry District Advisory Committee has only met once while I'm
in office.

LASH: Well, that makes it easy for you.

SUTPHIN: That makes it easy.

LASH: [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: The Local Emergency Planning Committee, and this is absolutely
terrifying, hasn't met since 2012. Let's hope there's not a local emergency. [Laughter]

LASH: [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: Because this committee is not ready to spring to action. I think it's,
like, a state requirement that they have this committeeó

LASH: But not a state requirement that it actually meet.

SUTPHIN: Yeah, probably not, no.

LASH: [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: But the hardest part about managing it is working it within my work
schedule at the vet school, so I have to take off every first and third Tuesday
for a few hours, or a couple hours, part of it's over my lunch break, to go to
work sessions. Like the Town Council, we actually see each other once a week, so
we have work sessions the first and third Tuesday in the middle of the day, and
then we have the full council meetings on the second and fourth Tuesday, and the
council meetings can last anywhere fromólike, five minutes was the shortestóto
we had one like a month or two ago that lasted three hours and eight minutes,
not that I was counting butó[Laughter]

LASH: [Laughter] Just a little bit.

SUTPHIN: [Laughter] Yeah, so it does take up a lot of time. I probably have to
use about half of my annual leaveómy vacation time

LASH: to go to Town Council

SUTPHIN: To go to town-related meetings. And the other council membersóJohn
Bush, who's on the council, who's a staff architect for Virginia Tech, has the
same issue that I do. But the others, like Susan Anderson who's a faculty
member, her schedule's more flexible. She doesn't have to request off specific
hours to go to a meeting. So it is a challenge. And the mayor owns his own
insurance company, so I assume he can work whenever he wants.

LASH: Mmm hmm. That's nice. But, soó

SUTPHIN: I got way off the topic of LGBT issues.

LASH: No, but now I'm like trying to think of how you would manage that many
different meetings. But, so, when you came into office, and when you were on the
Town Council, was there any kind of like push, about you being openly gay? Or
was everyone kind of just like, cool.

SUTPHIN: I think actuallyóand this wasn't, like, covered in the newspaperóbut
probably more significant than me being openly gay, I'm the youngest person
every elected to the Blacksburg Town Council, allegedly.

LASH: Allegedly [laughter]

SUTPHIN: I don't think anyone's done a study where they looked back. After I was
elected, I had coffee with the mayor, Ron Rordam. And he said, you know, when I
first, when the mayor, before he was the mayor, when he first ran for town
council in 1996óI think it was 1996óyou would want to fact-check that if that
were in, like, a history textbook or somethingówhen he first ran for Town
Council, when he was elected, everyone kept telling him that he was the youngest
person who had ever been elected to the town council. They've got this young
professional on, it's so exciting! He was forty years old when he was elected.
And then in 2009, in the election, I lost, someone won, Krisha Chachra, who is
in her thirties. And then I won, I was twenty-seven years old, elected to the
Ttown Council. So there's a running joke that soon an eighteen year old will be

LASH: On the Town Council

SUTPHIN: Running the Town Council. It's unlikely, butó

LASH: [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: It was very different being on the Town Council and the youngest
person. I'm also the only one on the Town Council who's been an undergraduate
student at Virginia Tech. So, the mayor Ron Rordam, and John Bush both have
graduate degrees here, but none of them were here as anó

LASH: Undergrad

SUTPHIN: Undergraduate student. Although, Cecile Newcomb is now taking classes.
So, I don't know if I can say that anymore. But so I definitely come from a
unique perspective of seeing the life in Blacksburg, versus a college student,
and now as kind of a long-term resident living in the community. There wasn't
much push-back for being gay. Right after I was elected, there was a newspaper,
The Washington Blade, which is an LGBT newspaper based out of Washington, DC.
Did an article, kind of like an election recap, saying that, it was talking
about all the openly gay people who were elected, all around theóI don't know if
it's all around the country, I think it focused mostly outside of the
Washington, DC areaóand it mentioned me. They, like, interviewed me and included
it, and I posted it on twitter, and I've noticed that anything I tweet, the
Roanoke Times notices it.

LASH: [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: Several times I've tweeted things and it just shows up in theó

LASH: Are you one of the only people that tweets?

SUTPHIN: [Laughter]

LASH: Are you one of the only Town Council members that tweets?

SUTPHIN: I'm the most active member on twitter on the Town Council

LASH: That's probably why [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: Yeah. So I tweeted this, and so the Roanoke Times called me and they
wanted to do this story about how I was the first openly gay person in the area
who'd been elected. I was like, okay. So they interviewed me to do this story,
and they also send out a photographer to get some photos of me, and these photos
were not very good. I was wearing flannelóI didn't have much notice. So I was
wearing flannel and I'm in front of the town hall and the, like, lighting is
really bad, and I'm in front of those white statues.

LASH: Yeah [laughter]

Sutphin. Yeah anyway. So, I saw the article online, it was posted that night.
And then the next day, I heard, some people sent me some emails about it, like,
ëhey, I saw you in the paper, congratulations.' This was like two weeks after I
was elected, before I took office. You don't take office immediately.

LASH: Yeah

SUTPHIN: I think it was, like, November and you take office January 1st. And
then, I go to a coffee shop with my boss, Eric, and we look at theóI'm like ëOh,
I'm going to pick up a copy of the paper cause I'm in it.' When I was first
elected, the election results were on page 8 or something like that. Like, it
was notóthe Blacksburg Town Council election didn't make it

LASH: Not a big deal?

SUTPHIN: There was another election at the same time.

LASH: Mmm hmm

SUTPHIN: So, that much larger election got first billing. When I saw the paper,
I was on the front page of the papers, saying Blacksburg councilman said
sexuality isn't an issue or something like that. I was like, for one I don't
remember actually saying that [laughter]

LASH: [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: It was veryólike, front page, above the fold

LASH: In your flannel.

SUTPHIN: That scary photo of me, I'm like, oh god, what have I done.

LASH: [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: After that, well several people congratulated me. Chris Tuck, who was
on the Board of Supervisors, congratulated me, which I thought was interesting,
because he's a Republican running for theóhe's a Republican politician in the
area, so I thought that was very kind of him. I was expecting to get hate mail
or something like that, but that didn't happen. I get hate mail about other
things all the time, like putting fluoride in the water, or, I don't know, all
sorts, a variety, I have a folder of hate mail. [Laughter] and I use the term
ìhate mailî loosely

LASH: [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: But I've never received anything against me for being gay. Someone did
ask to meet with me and we, so we go get lunch, because he wanted to, he said he
saw the article about me and he wanted to talk. And then I realized like halfway
through the lunch that it was actually a date that he had asked me on, and I
didn't quite realize it. [Laughter]

LASH: [Laughter]

SUTPHIN: So suddenly I was on a date with someone. [laughter]

LASH: From your flannel newspaper article [laughter]

SUTPHIN: So at least one person really liked it. [Laughter]

LASH: Yeah, the picture couldn't have been that bad. [Laughter] But, so, it
sounds like the Blacksburg community was very accepting.

SUTPHIN: Yeah, I think so

LASH: They were like, okay, whatever.

SUTPHIN: And the people who weren't didn't tell me, so, that's good.

LASH: That's good. Keep their opinions to themselves. So is there anything that,
for you, has been really important for shaping how you've identified with the
LGBT community, or just your view of being gay in general?

SUTPHIN: Probably coming out early helped shape my view and it gave me a
different perspective than some of the other people who came out later in life.
Because over half of my life, I've been out to my friends, where I knew other
people who are older, and they may have also come out fifteen years ago, but
they were, like, in their mid forties or fifties or something like that when
they came out. So their experience is very different than my experience and
sometimes theyópeople who come out later are a little bit more jaded, because
they felt like society was pressuring them to be in the closet, and since I
didn't have those pressures, I was very lucky and fortunate in the environment I
grew up in. My experience has been very different. I don't know if that's
helpful or not.

LASH: No, that is helpful. And do you think that the fact that you were very
involved, too, when you came to Virginia Tech and have stayed involved, do you
think that's kept you positive about LGBT issues? Do you think that's better
than not being involved or maybe notó

SUTPHIN: Oh yeah. I think everyone should be involved.

LASH: Yeah

SUTPHIN: I know that's unrealistic, and not going to happen. But even if it's
small things, like doing a mentorship programóa mentorship program isn't a small
thingóbut, or just like helping out one person who's coming through the coming
out process with something like that. I think it's very important to stay
involved. I've been involved in all areas of my life, though, from running for
the Collegiate Times, to Town Council and local government, to my LGBT types of
activism. So I think that's just a part of my personality, to always be involved
and stay involved, and I realize not everyone's going to do that, but it is
important. It's probably affected my perspective on LGBT issues significantly,
though, because people who aren't involved are seeing it primarily as like a
social thing. Like, they're going to a bar, they're hanging out with their
friends. Whereas I'm going to a protest or signing a petition or something like
that. So that probably affects my perspective a little bit differently. I still
go to bars and hang out with friends, butó

LASH: [Laughter] you alsoó

SUTPHIN: It's also more, like, heavily politicized for me than for other people.

LASH: So, if you had any sort of advice to give to, maybe, if it was your
younger self, or a younger person going through the same situationó

SUTPHIN: Don't wear flannel.

LASH: [Laughter] don't wear flannel for your cover photo!

SUTPHIN: [Laughter]

LASH: But, would you have any type of advice that you would want to give someone
maybe struggling through coming out, or just coming to terms with the fact that
they're gay?

SUTPHIN: I would sayóbecause I did have that experience where I lost a bunch of
my friends in high schoolóthat if people aren't going to accept you because of
your sexual orientation, they weren't your friends in the first place. I know
that's a little bit cliche to sayó

LASH: I mean, it's true

SUTPHIN: But it's absolutely true. Like, they weren't, like if they won't accept
they whole you, then they're not your friends. So, that's what I would tell my
younger self.

LASH: Okay, well, thank you

SUTPHIN: Is that it?

LASH: Yeah, I'móout of questions, you have a lot to, I want to ask you more
about city council, butó

SUTPHIN: Oh, you can [laughter]

LASH: [Laughter] But yeah no, I just didn't know there were so many committees
for Town Council

SUTPHIN: There are lots of committees. There's probably a couple dozen or
something like that.

LASH: Are you good?

LILLY: Uh, we'll see. 1

 

 

</transcript><rights></rights><fmt>audio</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation></xmllocation><xmlfilename></xmlfilename><collection_link></collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>