<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT><record id="00015438" dt="2015-10-02"><version>4</version><date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2014-10-26</date><date_nonpreferred_format>2014-10-26</date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id>Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_HernandezDavid</cms_record_id><title>Oral History with David Hernandez, October 26, 2014 (Ms2015-007)</title><accession></accession><duration>01:06:50</duration><collection_id>Ms2015-007</collection_id><collection_name>The Virginia Tech LGBTQ Oral History Collection</collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Virginia Tech Special Collections</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewee>David Hernandez</interviewee><interviewer>Dara Green</interviewer><file_name>Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_HernandezDavid</file_name><sync>1:|13(31)|13(164)|25(12)|37(63)|45(4)|55(42)|67(4)|79(4)|92(7)|101(7)|117(14)|129(12)|144(16)|158(6)|166(14)|179(15)|193(2)|214(12)|225(6)|235(7)|245(9)|254(11)|264(14)|278(7)|291(7)|301(3)|314(5)|323(3)|336(3)|345(7)|355(3)|371(9)|380(1)|393(2)|405(8)|414(6)|431(7)|442(10)|457(9)|467(5)|480(3)|490(3)|500(5)|512(7)|524(3)|532(15)|546(10)|561(14)|574(1)|582(2)|591(5)|618(5)|627(3)|639(2)|657(12)|667(7)|676(8)|686(5)|703(1)|715(12)|729(3)|738(5)|745(13)|759(5)|774(9)|784(9)</sync><media_id></media_id><media_url>http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/files/original/3412/Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_HernandezDavid_OralHistory.1.mp3</media_url><mediafile><host>Other</host><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>audio</clip_format></mediafile><language></language><index><point><time>1</time><title>Introductions</title><partial_transcript>Dara Green: My name is Dara Green, and I am a student of Dr. David Cline, and I am here today with David Hernandez to talk about the history of the LGBTQ community here at Virginia Tech, and we so appreciate you coming in to talk with us—</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>87</time><title>Upbringing</title><partial_transcript>HERNANDEZ: My up bringing I would say—so I’m a first generation American. My parents are Filipino immigrants. They emigrated from the Philippines in 1985 to escape the Marcos totalitarian regime. I’m certainly very thankful for that. So that certainly colored a bit of my upbringing in terms of having that part of Filipino culture in me, as well as how I was raised sort of religiously. My parents were both—or they are both practicing Catholics, and that was a fairly major part of my childhood, going to Sunday school and all that. But yeah, so that’s just a little brief history of my upbringing. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>162</time><title>Identity</title><partial_transcript>HERNANDEZ: So I’ve a very interesting viewpoint on the notion of identities and labels. I think the closest I identify, with regards to my sexual orientation, would be that I am pansexual. But once again, that’s a very difficult thing to confine, because it’s trying to put boxes on a spectrum, right? Or not even a spectrum—a series of spectrums. Attraction is very hard to classify. But we as humans try to do our best in doing that, and the scientists try to do our best doing that, right?</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>323</time><title>Coming Out</title><partial_transcript>HERNANDEZ: Oh yeah, yeah, it was difficult. Middle-schoolers are really, really shitty individuals. Yeah, so coming out at thirteen it’s not really the—I wouldn’t say that it’s the smartest idea but that’s a really poor choice of words. I would say that it was a very difficult decision, and it had a lot of really poor consequences because being somebody different, in a middle school a setting, sets you up for being bullied and all that, right? You become a target. So I came out when I was thirteen, eighth grade, end of middle school. And the other kids just sort of ate that up. ‘Oh here is the different kid. Let’s make fun of him.’ Stuff like that. And it sucked. Let’s face it, it sucked. I’m not going to beat around the bush. It was a horrible experience. I won’t say that I wish I didn’t do it because frankly it’s something that needed to happen at that point in time. I needed to sort of accept that I was different than some of my other peers, right? </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>532</time><title>Parents' Reaction</title><partial_transcript>HERNANDEZ: So my parents wanted to send me to some flavor of conversion therapy, when I first came out. After talking to a priest, who we were relatively close with, it was clear that that was definitely not the answer, and that he said that we should try to work things out as a familial unit, which we did. We um—it took a while for my parents to sort of understand this notion of not being straight [laugh]. And it took a while. My mother was actually in tears when she found out because she was worried that kids where going to bully me at school, which obviously, we know, did happen. Not too much you can do about that. My dad on the other hand, had a very null reaction because he just didn’t know how to react. It was as if I was an alien, from another planet almost, because it was so foreign to him in his world, this notion of non-heterosexuality. But over the years, we worked it out together. My parents are very accepting of me now. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>818</time><title>Coming to College</title><partial_transcript>GREEN: Did you know about the LGBTQ community here at Tech before you came? 

HERNANDEZ: Um I had done a mild amount of research. Once again, thanks internet! 

GREEN: Yeah. 

HERNANDEZ: So I looked up on some aggregate websites that rate colleges on how LGBT friendly they are. Virginia Tech seemed to be pretty friendly, despite being in Southwest Virginia. And so I just sort of came at it with a relatively blank mindset. Although I will admit that when I first started college, I did re-closet myself. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>1094</time><title>Inspiration for Virginia Tech Chapter of oSTEM</title><partial_transcript>HERNANDEZ: So I traveled out to this conference, it was called OUTC, Out for Undergrad Tech Conference, and it was there that I met an individual named Eric Patridge [sp?] who was then a PhD candidate at Yale University and is presently the president of OSTEM, the national organization. 
So after talking with him, and meeting up with a bunch of other individuals that were part of this national network, really, of LGBT students in STEM fields, it sort of planted this idea in my head that, you know, maybe there should be something like this on Virginia Tech’s campus, because, although we may have students organizations that cater to LGBTQ individuals, there’s not really, at the time, there weren’t really any resources for LGBTQ individuals to grow themselves as professionals. 
So, I come back, finish the year, and over the summer, this is just brewing in my head, that, you know, this is something that the university sort of needs.</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>1253</time><title>Founding of oSTEM</title><partial_transcript>HERNANDEZ: I believe it was September 2012, or so, I went and established the Virginia Tech chapter of Out in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics with two of my peers. 
And from there it’s just been, you know, it’s been very interesting starting an organization that’s really fresh, very new, even nationally. The organization, I guess had its roots from a focus group back in 2005, but there wasn’t any sort of chapter-level growth until 2011, one year prior to when we started establishing the Virginia Tech chapter here. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>1413</time><title>The Work and Mission of oSTEM</title><partial_transcript>HERNANDEZ: Yes it’s about fighting prejudice in the workplace and it’s about empowering students to be truly comfortable as themselves in the workplace, because I’ve heard so many stories and I’ve had so many friends who have gone on to be professionals, but they’ve had to seclude themselves, they’ve had to re-closet themselves, they’ve had to put up the fortress, so to speak, and that’s something that I believe isn’t really that healthy for both emotional well being as well as professional growth. Because if you’re not going to be comfortable as yourself as a whole, if you spend energy trying to shield yourself away, or keep secrets, right, that’s less energy that you can use to being a better professional, being a better individual, and so, it sort of takes away from your integrity.</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>2088</time><title>Atmosphere in the Local Community</title><partial_transcript>HERNANDEZ: As I staid here, for more time, as I got to know the people, you realize that sure they might have their own view points, somebody might be a Christian or Catholic, or some other sort of stereotypically antigay religious affirmation, but as you get to know people more, you realize that a lot of people are still accepting despite whatever prejudices you yourself might think of based off of where they’re from or what their background is, right. That’s a very interesting lesson that I learned over the past four or five years, was that, although this area is quote on quote pretty red,  end quote, the people here are still very friendly to you because at the end of the day we’re all people, right. It’s not alienating to be lesbian, or gay, or bisexual, or queer, or transgender, or anything like that. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>2323</time><title>SafeZone Program</title><partial_transcript>HERNANDEZ: So the idea behind a Safe Zone; it’s an individual—or it’s a space—where individuals are free to be themselves without fear of discrimination. You don’t have to worry about being targeted because of your sexual orientation, your gender identity, your gender expression, your sex, your race, any of that. It’s a ‘Safe Zone.’  
And so how it works is individuals apply for certification to be a safe zone. They go through trainings. And admittedly it does eat up a bit of time but I think that it’s valuable for the community, for faculty, staff, and even students who—students can also apply for this program—to let others know that they are a ‘Safe Zone.’ They are safe individuals to speak with. 
</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>2696</time><title>Smith Career Center improves Out for Work Certification</title><partial_transcript>HERNANDEZ: I know that for example the Smith Career Center has gotten better certifications for how much they support the LGBTQ community through this national organization called Out for Work. 
Out for Work gives career centers at universities one of four classifications: bronze, silver, gold, or like gold plus, something like that, A+gold, I don’t know. It’s really good is what it is. And so prior to all of this stuff, me talking with John Gray, starting OSTEM, getting the Aspire! Award, Virginia Tech’s Smith Career Center was at a bronze certification, right. And so how it sort of works is if you have the gold plus certification you’ve got 100 out of 100, that’s your score. If you have gold, it’s like 90 to 100—or 90 to 99, silver is like 70 to 90, and then bronze is like you applied. 
</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>2835</time><title>Receiving the Aspire! Award</title><partial_transcript>HERNANDEZ: John Gray, among other individuals, nominated me for the Award for Creative Leadership. But nobody told me about it! 

GREEN: [laughs]

HERNANDEZ: So I get an email in February, March maybe, saying ‘hey you’ve been nominated for this award. We’d like to recognize you for your excellence in Creative Leadership, etc. etc.’ So for me, in a sense, it was sort of a validation to myself that what I was doing, this work with OSTEM, was making a meaningful impact on the university, that I wasn’t just some kid making his own special interest club just for the heck of it. That what I was doing was having a real impact on the university. And that for me was—let’s face it, it was gratifying. It was awesome! Like, I felt so good about it, but I did not like waking up at 8am to go to Owens Banquet Hall for that reception. 
</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>3190</time><title>Fighting for LBGT Issues Starts From the Ground Up</title><partial_transcript>GREEN: I think historically, with almost all LGBT issues, it’s always come from the ground up, you know, it’s always come from students and the public putting pressure on the institutions that be. 

HERNANDEZ: Yes! That’s definitely it. And I hope that anybody that listens to this very longwinded discussion that, you know, you step up because it’s all about you. It’s the grass roots movements. Because you can’t really expect anything to come down from the sky above, even though that’s how gravity works. It starts with us as individuals before we bring it to larger organizations, and institutions, and even further up than that, like federal initiatives, national initiatives. It all has to start with us as the individuals. 
</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>3291</time><title>Sexuality and Filipino Culture</title><partial_transcript>HERNANDEZ: in the Philippines, at least to my knowledge, in the culture there, there is not a lot of understanding about non-cis-gendered, or non-heterosexual individuals. The notion that gender and sexuality have to be linked for individuals, for men in particular, that find themselves to be homosexual, but due to societal pressures, they have to act and live as women, right, almost like a forced gender dysphoria. 
I think that that’s something that I find very strange about Filipino culture. And I think that’s certainly one of the things that went through my parents’ minds was that ‘oh he’s gay, what if he wants to be a woman next.’ I obviously wouldn’t know if this is true because I never asked them about that. But it’s always something that’s lurked in the back of my mind. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>3678</time><title>Changes in LGBTQ Visibility on Campus</title><partial_transcript>HERNANDEZ: So thirty five years ago, an organization that wanted to support LGBTQ individuals could not be granted a space on campus to meet. Absolutely unacceptable. Heathenist! Blasphemy! 
But it happened in 1979, if memory serves, with Lambda Horizons. And that was sort of a key moment for the community where they could start gathering. It began the visibility. There was no more secretive hush hush cabals in somebody’s dorm room or apartment. Now there’s a organized visible space for people to meet, and to grow the community. And from then on it’s sort of gone up. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>3857</time><title>The Future of the Virginia Tech LGBTQ Community</title><partial_transcript>HERNANDEZ: there’s a lot of things going on. The landscape is evolving here at Virginia Tech. Over with MPS, now that there are all these organizations popping up left and right that support the LGBTQ community in different ways. We’re trying to organize under some flavor of umbrella in order to pool resources and to strengthen the community. That didn’t exist before. 
Before it was Catherine Cortrupi, in her role as the LGBT coordinator at MPS, sort of herding cats together, almost like. But now there is so much collaboration between the organizations, like OSTEM and QGPA, they’re having a movie screening in the near future, jointly together, cosponsoring. You’ve got all the organizations cosponsoring the Lavender Ceremony, which is an LGBTQ graduation ceremony that happens the Thursday before graduation. So I think what the future holds is just a lot of collaboration between individuals instead of there being these isolated pockets of communities or individuals. 
</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point></index><type></type><description>David Hernandez attended Virginia Tech from 2010 to 2014 and graduated with a degree in Computer Science. In Fall 2012, Hernandez founded the Virginia Tech chapter of Out in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (oSTEM), an organization that provides professional support for LGBTQ students and faculty pursuing careers in the STEM fields. In 2013, the Virginia Tech Division of Student Affairs awarded Hernandez with the Aspire! Award for Courageous Leadership for his work with oSTEM. In his oral history, Hernandez discusses defining his identity and sexuality at a young age as a Filipino-American, his work with oSTEM and other LGBTQ programs and organizations on campus, the changing visibility and resources for LGBTQ students at Virginia Tech and his hopes for the Hokie Nation in the future.</description><rel /><transcript>Dara Green: My name is Dara Green, and I am a student of Dr. David Cline, and I am here today with 
David Hernandez to talk about the history of the LGBTQ community here at Virginia Tech, and we so appreciate you coming in to talk with us

David Hernandez: I'm very glad to be here.

GREEN: This is great. Can we start off by having you tell me your name, your
date of birth, and your place of birth?

HERNANDEZ: Certainly. So like you stated Dara, my name is David Hernandez. Born December 4th 1991, and I believe my birth-certificate states that I was born in Washington D.C.

GREEN: Can you tell me a little bit about your upbringing?

HERNANDEZ: Certainly. Depends on what you mean by a little bit, because I could go all the way back to I was born in this hospital, and then raised in this part of the world for however many number of years. Ok, sure, so I was born in D.C., like I said, but grew up for a few years in Oxon Hill Maryland. Right across the fence from where the Gaylord National Convention Center is now. Staid there until about 1994-1995, and then I moved to Arlington, Virginia, which is now my permanent place of residence. My up bringing I would say so I'm a first generation American. My parents are Filipino immigrants. They emigrated from the Philippines in 1985 to escape the Marcos totalitarian regime. I'm certainly very thankful for that. So that certainly colored a bit of my upbringing in terms of having that part of Filipino culture in me, as well as how I was raised sort of religiously. My parents were both or they are both practicing Catholics, and that was a fairly major part of my childhood, going to Sunday school and all that. But yeah, so that's just a little brief history of my upbringing. What else should I talk about? [laugh]

GREEN: Well anything that you think is pertinent to the interview.

HERNANDEZ: Ok.

GREEN: Jumping right into it: I know that you are an activist here on campus for
the LGBT community, and I'd just like to ask you for the record, how you
identify yourself within that?

HERNANDEZ: So I've a very interesting viewpoint on the notion of identities and
labels. I think the closest I identify, with regards to my sexual orientation,
would be that I am pansexual. But once again, that's a very difficult thing to
confine, because it's trying to put boxes on a spectrum, right? Or not even a
spectrum, a series of spectrums. Attraction is very hard to classify. But we as
humans try to do our best in doing that, and the scientists try to do our best
doing that, right?

GREEN: Right. Absolutely. When did you start realizing this about yourself?

HERNANDEZ: Well that's one hell of a story, if I may say so.

GREEN: Absolutely, let's hear it.

HERNANDEZ: So I first began discovering my sexuality when I was about eight years old, maybe nine years old, stumbled upon some adult materials. And from there I sort of discovered that I sort of had passing physical attractions to my male peers, right? Things that I wouldn't, you know, expect to have. And certainly for a while, between then and until say' I was twelve or thirteen, I was in the 'it's just a phase' sort of mindset. That I just have this passing physical attraction and that I'll be straight and normal like all the other
boys. And, you know, that wasn't really the case, and I developed romantic
feelings for a close friend of mine when I was thirteen. So from there, I
identified as gay, because that's sort of all I really knew back then. But, over
the years I've come to realize that my viewpoint is very fluid. It's very
difficult for me to say I am strictly attracted to men, I'm strictly attracted
to women, I'm strictly attracted to cis-gender or transgender individuals. So
it's become a very difficult thing to sort of box in, that's why I opt to use
the pansexual identifier, as of the past few years. Now that I've been in
college, I've learned more about myself, and how these sorts of things work.

GREEN: Absolutely. Was that difficult for you, when you're developing feelings when you're thirteen, for this friend of yours, when you were in D.C. or
Arlington schools?

HERNANDEZ: Oh yeah, yeah, it was difficult. Middle-schoolers are really, really
shitty individuals. Yeah, so coming out at thirteen it's not really the- I
wouldn't say that it's the smartest idea but that's a really poor choice of
words. I would say that it was a very difficult decision, and it had a lot of
really poor consequences because being somebody different, in a middle school a setting, sets you up for being bullied and all that, right? You become a target. So I came out when I was thirteen, eighth grade, end of middle school. And the other kids just sort of ate that up. 'Oh here is the different kid. Let's make fun of him.' Stuff like that. And it sucked. Let's face it, it sucked. I'm not going to beat around the bush. It was a horrible experience. I won't say that I wish I didn't do it because frankly it's something that needed to happen at that point in time. I needed to sort of accept that I was different than some of my other peers, right?

GREEN: Absolutely. For a lot of people that's very early. People struggle with
that, identifying themselves, for a really long time.

HERNANDEZ: Certainly. Yeah, for me I believe I started puberty at about the same
age, as I mentioned earlier, when I was about eight or nine. A little earlier
than most other males from a, I guess, scientific stand point.

GREEN: Mhmm.

HERNANDEZ: So I guess I sort of had that cognizance a little earlier than most.
Having access to the internet also certainly helped with that because I was able
to read up on things like 'homosexual attraction, what's gay sex?' And even the
basics like 'what's a condom? How to use a condom,' you know, safe sex stuff. So
I think that that combination of things lead me to be a little more cognizant
of things of that nature, of any sort of sexual or romantic nature.

GREEN: Absolutely. And I know that a lot of gay and lesbian people struggle with
depression, that I'm sure is linked to that kind of bullying and ostracization.
Did you experience that when you were a teenager?

HERNANDEZ: Oh certainly, of course. I do experience depression from bullying in
general. Or I did I should say, when I was younger because I was, I look a
little different. I was overweight compared to the rest of my peers. I was a
smart kid, so it made me an easy target for bullying, certainly. Being even more
different with, you know, not being straight in a hetero-normative society, also
sort of added a little fuel to the fire. Middle school really bad, high school,
you know, not as terrible because I had more peers, more people to sort of
communicate with, less isolated. I think college was really when I hit my
stride, when I really became comfortable with who I was. And I adopted this
notion of not having to come out anymore. I just am who I am.

GREEN: So when you say you came out: To your friends, to parents, your
community? How did the people close to you react?

HERNANDEZ: So my parents wanted to send me to some flavor of conversion therapy,
when I first came out. After talking to a priest, who we were relatively close
with, it was clear that that was definitely not the answer, and that he said
that we should try to work things out as a familial unit, which we did. We um, it took a while for my parents to sort of understand this notion of not being
straight [laugh]. And it took a while. My mother was actually in tears when she
found out because she was worried that kids where going to bully me at school,
which obviously, we know, did happen. Not too much you can do about that. My dad
on the other hand, had a very null reaction because he just didn't know how to
react. It was as if I was an alien, from another planet almost, because it was
so foreign to him in his world, this notion of non-heterosexuality. But over the
years, we worked it out together. My parents are very accepting of me now. My
close friends are very accepting of me now. Coming out to my peers in middle
school, you know, everything blew up cause middle schoolers are shitty.

GREEN: Right.

HERNANDEZ: But you find other friends. You find people that empathize with you
more, and you move on.

GREEN: Was that a conversation that you had with your parents, or was this
something that came about finding internet searches, or how did this develop?

HERNANDEZ: Um so, my mother found out. Because I was talking with another
student, a classmate in middle school, who is also closeted, so he was asking me
about coming out, about accepting your identity, your sexual identity, or your
sexuality. And my mother comes in and she asks me 'what's up?' I try to hide it
from her. She freaks out. I freak out. She reads the chat logs between me and
this classmate. And yeah, she's incredibly shocked, to the point of tears. Like
not necessarily a negative reaction, but just she was very surprised. Sort of
like, if you're in a haunted house and the little ghost pops up from around the
corner, something like that, where you just don't know how to react at first,
and you just find yourself very surprised. After that, after talking with my
mother, she said that I should talk to my dad, right. And so I did that. I
remember the scene very clearly: He was sitting in his lazy boy watching
television. I came up to him and I said 'hey dad, uhhhh, I think I'm gay.' And
he's got this very blank expression on his face but it's the kind of blank
expression where you know that he's trying to figure out what to say but he
doesn't know what to say. And so he's like 'are you sure?' and I'm like 'yeah.'
Then I go back to my room and play video games [laugh].

GREEN: wow.

HERNANDEZ: Yeah so that took a little longer. Sort of like a defrosting almost,
sort of engaging the conversation.

GREEN: Do you think that their background being supplanted in America, was that
different culturally from?

HERNANDEZ: Yeah I would say so. Although they were immigrants in America,
there's still a community of other Filipino immigrants and they're all a part of
that, right? So although they're no longer in the Philippines, they still have
that community of fellow Filipino Americans, the Fil-Am community. So they
still, you know, were in this, I don't want to say they were in this mindset but
I'm at a loss for a better way to phase it, of just like everybody's straight and
if you're not straight than I don't know what is going on anymore, that kind of
thing. That's a very grand simplification of some attitudes towards gender and
sexuality among conservative Filipinos, but that's a massive digression, right.

GREEN: Right. So by the time you got to Tech, you already had established this
as part of your identity, and your feelings, you knew yourself pretty well. Did
you know about the LGBTQ community here at Tech before you came?

HERNANDEZ: Um I had done a mild amount of research. Once again, thanks internet!

GREEN: Yeah.

HERNANDEZ: So I looked up on some aggregate websites that rate colleges on how
LGBT friendly they are. Virginia Tech seemed to be pretty friendly, despite
being in Southwest Virginia. And so I just sort of came at it with a relatively
blank mindset. Although I will admit that when I first started college, I did
re-closet myself. I said I'm not really going to tell anybody that doesn't need
to know because I sort of made the mistake of being very obnoxiously open about
it high school and I didn't want to repeat the same mistakes by driving people
away by quote on quote 'forcing' my identity out into the open. So, I think that
was a bit of an over correction, but I guess it worked out in the end because I
was able to sort of reevaluate my identity then. No longer am I the exclusively
homosexual macho guy blah, blah, blah. I used to be not very cognizant of trans
issues, for example, coming out of high school. So in college I got the
opportunity to relearn that.

GREEN: That's really interesting because a lot of people who come out in
college. That's their first opportunity, being away from home and feeling like
they can explore.

HERNANDEZ: Yeah I guess where I come from in Arlington is an incredibly liberal
place. So I had the opportunity to be open there, but coming out is really a
continual process, you enter a new community, where there are a significant
number of unknowns. I go from my class of fifteen hundred students, only maybe
seven of which are going here to Virginia Tech, and so I enter an environment
with more than forty-thousand individuals, right, when you take into account
students, faculty, staff, residents. And I only know maybe ten of them, right.
So there's this completely vast number of unknowns. So naturally, my reaction
back then, well I guess my natural reaction back then, was to play it a little
safe, so to speak, just see what everybody is like before I divulge such information.

GREEN: You think people will make assumptions about you before they really get
to know you? Was that the fear?

HERNANDEZ: Um I suppose yeah. And at the same time, people tend to do that.
Profiling is a way to efficiently figure out what people are like before you
talk to them. Because getting to know every single individual you meet on the
street is a very costly operation, right. That's why we as humans do this thing
called profiling.

GREEN: Yes absolutely. And just for the record, you came to Tech in 2010, is
that right? You're a senior?

HERNANDEZ: I came to Tech, yes, Fall 2010.

GREEN: Ok, and you'll be graduating in the Spring, yes?

HERNANDEZ: I graduated last Spring

GREEN: Oh you already graduated. That's right. I wasn't sure. All the
information I was reading up on on the Division of Student Affairs is very dated.
[laughs] So they were talking about you as a junior and I was like ok, is he a senior?

HERNANDEZ: Yeah that was from 2013, yeah.

GREEN: But while you were here, you started OSTEM? And you're the president and
founder of the chapter here? Can you tell me about the experience of doing that?

HERNANDEZ: Certainly, yeah. And so, let's give a little background to this
story, cause everybody loves exposition. So, I believe it was February 2012, I
went to a conference for LGBT students in technology, in the technological
fields. I graduated with a degree in computer science, and so back then I was a
student in computer science. And so I traveled out to this conference, it was
called OUTC, Out for Undergrad Tech Conference, and it was there that I met an
individual named Eric Patridge [sp?] who was then a PhD candidate at Yale
University and is presently the president of OSTEM, the national organization.
So after talking with him, and meeting up with a bunch of other individuals that
were part of this national network, really, of LGBT students in STEM fields, it
sort of planted this idea in my head that, you know, maybe there should be
something like this on Virginia Tech's campus, because, although we may have
students organizations that cater to LGBTQ individuals, there's not really, at
the time, there weren't really any resources for LGBTQ individuals to grow
themselves as professionals. So, I come back, finish the year, and over the
summer, this is just brewing in my head, that, you know, this is something that
the university sort of needs. I think. So I come back, it's August 2012, and I
talk to an individual named John Gray Williams, who had recently finished his
Master's at the University of Delaware, I believe. He was also a Hokie alum,
graduated undergrad in two thousand and something. I'm not gonna say what,
because if he hears this he's going to destroy me if I mess up when he graduated.

GREEN: Like I just did. [laughs] Sorry.

HERNANDEZ: So we talk about this notion. I gather a couple other individuals who
were also interested in the idea of establishing a professional organization
that supports LGBTQ individuals that, you know, are in the STEM fields.
Admittedly, the STEM fields part was a bit of an unnecessary constraint on the
needs of the university, because overall, just there weren't any professional
organizations at all that assisted LGBTQ individuals. The STEM part was just a
rather convenient way because it was already an established national
organization. There are resources to help me establish a chapter here. And so
in, I believe it was September 2012, or so, I went and established the Virginia
Tech chapter of Out in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics with two
of my peers. And from there it's just been, you know, it's been very interesting
starting an organization that's really fresh, very new, even nationally. The
organization, I guess had its roots from a focus group back in 2005, but there
wasn't any sort of chapter-level growth until 2011, one year prior to when we
started establishing the Virginia Tech chapter here. And so, it's hard, starting
a new organization. Networking with the proper faculty and staff to get, you
know, resources to be able to put the word out there that 'hey, there's this
organization that can help you be comfortable as an LGBTQ professional,' rather
than organizations that I guess are more student-based, right. Because back
then, there were only three organizations. There was the LGBTA, which is now
known as Hokie Pride, there was QGNA, the Queer Grads and Allies, which is now
QGPA, Queer Grads, Young Professionals and Allies, and then there's the LGBT
Caucus, which supports faculty staff. And so, you got this, I guess, horizontal
stratification of age groups, demographics, things like that. And 2012 was the
year when more specialized vertically-integrated groups came in. Things like
OSTEM, which supported STEM students, so people that wanted advice
professionally. There was QPOC, which, you know, goes across all three strata,
that supports queer people of color. At the time there was talk of establishing
a trans working group. I actually don't know what the status of that is. But
once again, another type of organization that ignores what your academic status
is, and really pinpoints a more, I want to say permanent part of your identity,
or a more, I guess, a less transient part of your identity, so to speak.

GREEN: And so, this organization, for you, OSTEM, is about fighting prejudice in
the workplace?

HERNANDEZ: Yes it's about fighting prejudice in the workplace and it's about
empowering students to be truly comfortable as themselves in the workplace,
because I've heard so many stories and I've had so many friends who have gone on
to be professionals, but they've had to seclude themselves, they've had to
re-closet themselves, they've had to put up the fortress, so to speak, and
that's something that I believe isn't really that healthy for both emotional
well being as well as professional growth. Because if you're not going to be
comfortable as yourself as a whole, if you spend energy trying to shield
yourself away, or keep secrets, right, that's less energy that you can use to
being a better professional, being a better individual, and so, it sort of takes
away from your integrity.

GREEN: What kind of activities does the group engage in, or how does it support
its members? How's it reach out to the community?

HERNANDEZ: So, back when we first started, it was just meetings, you know, 'hey
let's meet at a room in Squires every two weeks and discuss, you know, X topic,'
for example. It was very loose back then because it was a new organization. And
it's still a very young organization. There was a week where we talked about
laws pertaining to non-discrimination acts, things like that. There's this book
called the Corporate Equality Index that the Human Rights Campaign puts out
every year and we talked about that as well as other resources that individuals
can use when they're researching the friendliness or the comfort of the
environment that they are going to be in when they're applying to work for a
company. There was stuff like what's interesting research in the field right
now, what's interesting in terms of academics, and so as its grown we've also
started sending people to our national conference. It happens once a year, all
of the O-STEM chapters get together and discuss things that not only affect the
national organization but things like how to run more effectively run individual
chapters, things that are pertinent in the environment today such as workplace
equality. How to get a grant, for example, even things like that, that aren't
necessarily LGBT specific but are still very useful for individuals in the STEM
fields, and basically providing resources to educate and inspire students and
other STEM affiliated individuals to do their best, be themselves and go on to
do great things without being hindered by the 'closet,' quote on quote.

GREEN:  And you have some great collaborators, I understand you were working
with Google and Opower and you have been drawing on their resources, they're
supportive of the organization?

HERNANDEZ:  Yeah, and so that's always something that's very reassuring to see
as a student is that there are these employers that do recognize the importance
of being leaders when it comes to workplace equality, companies such as Google,
Opower, IBM, the CIA even. So if you go to the O-STEM national website there's a
list of national sponsors and at least for the past couple years, the CIA has
been incredibly supportive of us, there's just all sorts of companies out there.
ALCOA, aluminum manufacturing, like, where did that come from?  Or like BASF,
which is, I believe, a chemical engineering company. But there are all of these
individuals and when these organizations, these corporations, these companies,
they show their support, it's very encouraging for students to see that there
are organizations that embrace and support who you are and on the more practical
side, they also provide resources such as funding, mentorship, swag so to speak,
you know, promotional materials I believe is the technical term for that, but
lets face it, we call it swag, right. Things like that.

GREEN: That's awesome that you've gotten that started here. And I understand
that your work with the faculty here, and staff, was a really positive
experience in starting OSTEM.

HERNANDEZ: Oh yeah absolutely. Because it's not just the corporate sponsors that
are important, because not everybody wants to go work in the industry after they
graduate. It's also important to have faculty and staff that are supportive of
an organization for individuals that wish to pursue academia further, right. A
lot of people worry about even going to grad school, people worry about
re-closeting themselves. I know of an individual who has had trouble publishing
her own papers because she was formally a he, so to speak, right. And so this
individual, when she transitioned from male to female, there were so many
problems, not just with publishing but, like, the atmosphere among her
colleagues. And so, it's not just about the importance of workplace equality,
but also about how things are in academia, because in some senses if you do
chose to become an academic, you want to be a professor, or you wish to do
interesting research, that's also a work place, right. That's something that is
often over looked. So having the support of faculty, staff members from all over
the place, whether it be with Career Services, Department of Engineering, or
Department of Science. Or I should say the College of Engineering or the College
of Science. Or even, I have an acquaintance in the College of Business that acted
as a mentor for me when I was doing some efforts with OSTEM as well as other
sorts of activities that were pertinent to professional development with other
organizations. So it's useful to have those resources, as well as the corporate
sponsors and all that. But I think having faculty and staff really hits closer
to home because these are the people that you learn from, that you interact with
potentially on a day-to-day basis. And I think that's certainly a very powerful
tool in getting individuals to understand that they can be comfortable with
themselves, who they are, whether it be in academia, in industry, or in general.

GREEN: Absolutely. Do you have any stories that you would like to share with us
from OSTEM, from members that maybe this helped?

HERNANDEZ: Let's see, so I know an individual, uh let's call her Claire.

GREEN: Ok. Claire.

HERNANDEZ: Because that is the name of a trans individual in comic book that I
actually read, that I follow. But that's also a complete and utter digression.

GREEN: [laugh]

HERNANDEZ: So Claire. Claire, when I had first met her went by Clint. Clint and
Claire. So I had known her as Clint before. And this person was just someone
that I saw randomly in a dorm hall but was a friend of a friend. But
coincidentally at the time that I had started OSTEM, Clint had started
transitioning to Claire. So with OSTEM, as well as other organizations such as
the then LGBTA, Claire was able to be more comfortable with her identity as a
transgender woman. So having that community there, those people that empathized
with her, and are similar to her, it creates a support network for individuals
that go through anything like that, whether it be a transition or coming out of
the closet or both. I think that having the organization there creates a
community. And having the community there creates a support network for
individuals that are experiencing tough times. And so now, Claire is a very
confident woman. She is very outgoing and she's doing splendidly. She is going
to graduate, I believe, this year and she's going to go off and do incredible
things. I think it's with the help of the community that OSTEM, sort of
coincidentally I guess, built. She's more confortable and more strong individual
than before.

GREEN: That's wonderful, and it's also great to hear that the LGBTQ community is
being more inclusive of transgendered people. Because that is one thing you hear
a lot, that not all gay and lesbians are as accepting of trans, even though
everyone kind of gets lumped in together.

HERNANDEZ: Yeah. There has always been the notion of LGB groups, right, and then
you got the 'T' groups, and then you have the 'Q' groups, and then it just turns
into this mess.

GREEN: So there is a lot of fractionalization in the groups and it's nice to
hear that, at least on this campus, it's been inclusive. What about the space
outside this campus, outside of the school directly, Blacksburg, is that a
positive place you thought, coming from Arlington?

HERNANDEZ: You know, initially, I did not think so but then again that was with
very, very little information. As I staid here, for more time, as I got to know
the people, you realize that sure they might have their own view points,
somebody might be a Christian or Catholic, or some other sort of stereotypically
antigay religious affirmation, but as you get to know people more, you realize
that a lot of people are still accepting despite whatever prejudices you
yourself might think of based off of where they're from or what their background
is, right. That's a very interesting lesson that I learned over the past four or
five years, was that, although this area is quote on quote pretty red,  end
quote, the people here are still very friendly to you because at the end of the
day we're all people, right. It's not alienating to be lesbian, or gay, or
bisexual, or queer, or transgender, or anything like that. There are individuals
there that you are a human being, you're not a dick, so you deserve some modicum
of respect and politeness. And so, what I've seen, people tend to be pretty nice
individuals, once you get to know them, regardless of whatever predispositions
you may have of their background.

GREEN: Yeah. I think Blacksburg is kind of a unique microcosm in this Southwest
Virginia area.

HERNANDEZ: Certainly, yes.

GREEN: I don't know if you've heard anything about that from people that are
coming from this area to Blacksburg, if they think it's different than coming
from Northern Virginia?

HERNANDEZ: Yeah. College towns, in themselves, are very interesting because
there's always this afflux, well there's an influx and there's an afflux of
individuals, right. People come in. People go out. They bring their viewpoints,
their beliefs, their backgrounds with them. And with each individual, a little
bit gets left here in Blacksburg, well not necessarily left, but it alters the
landscape or how people think. So you've got people coming in from all over the
place. You experience a lot of different viewpoints. And I think people here in
Virginia Tech in particular really do embrace each other, as quote on quote 'the
Hokie Nation' because we're all just people at the end of the day trying to get
along. And it's not fair to discriminate against somebody else based off of some
arbitrary qualifier, such as sexual orientation, gender identity, race, sex, any
of that. It's silly, and a lot of people here do realize that because you've got
people from all over the place coming to this town to better themselves.

GREEN: Absolutely. We all get to leave our imprint, hopefully. It sounds like
you've left a pretty big one here actually on the community, which is great!
Going back to the campus, you mentioned in a blog post, on Gobbler Connection,
that Virginia Tech has 'Safe Zones,' which is a program which designates faculty
and staff areas that are LGBTQ friendly. I have never heard of that before.

HERNANDEZ: Really?

GREEN: Can you explain that?

HERNANDEZ: Ok then. So here's a shout out to a certain individual, her name is
Catherine Cortrupi, and I believe that she really spearheaded this notion of the
Safe Zone movement. So the idea behind a Safe Zone; it's an individual or it's a
space where individuals are free to be themselves without fear of
discrimination. You don't have to worry about being targeted because of your
sexual orientation, your gender identity, your gender expression, your sex, your
race, any of that. It's a 'Safe Zone.' And so how it works is individuals apply
for certification to be a safe zone. They go through trainings. And admittedly
it does eat up a bit of time but I think that it's valuable for the community,
for faculty, staff, and even students who, students can also apply for this
program, to let others know that they are a 'Safe Zone.' They are safe
individuals to speak with. Because although you may have the belief that nobody
should be discriminated, it doesn't mean anything if nobody knows about that, if
you keep it to yourself, because you sort of mask your support of the community
by not being visible about it. So the Safe Zone provides visibility, and I think
that's the most important thing, is that it provides visibility of safe spaces
and individuals to the community, so that we know who we can talk to and be open with.

GREEN: So this is additional training that faculty and staff go through. Education?

HERNANDEZ: Yeah education. Things like trans issues, STIs, depression, things
that aren't necessarily LGBTQ specific, just a series of topics that are deemed
important to providing a safe space for discussion.

GREEN: And you said, this was 2013 again, that the College of Engineering only
had fifteen such Safe Zones, compared to the Liberal Arts College that had
forty; has that changed?

HERNANDEZ: I believe that has changed. So I've been in discussions with a
certain Associate Dean of Student Affairs in the College of Engineering, who I
will not name. And no, I mean this individual has been really supportive and
they're fantastic. Cause this individual was somebody who I talked to when I was
first trying to set up OSTEM. And so, what has been said in the past is, and I
will go on record for this because I think it needs to be put out there, that
I've been told that professors are too busy. They don't have enough time to
participate in the Safe Zone Program. They are supportive but there's just not
enough time to go through the training because it does take a little time. You
know, that's an incredibly valid point. For the most part, I understand the
rationale behind that. But at the same time, the visibility is really just
what's so important. And even if you may be a supportive individual, I think the
visibility is the kicker in changing the climate within this university. There
are a lot of very supportive individuals here at Virginia Tech, but there's less
visibility compared to other universities such as the University of Maryland,
right, which has over thirty organizations last I checked. Or like even the
University of Texas at Austin. They have all sorts of clearly visible
organizations to help support LGBTQ individuals. That was something that
Virginia Tech, the College of Engineering lacked. Which is why the Safe Zone
Program exists. But since then, I would like to say that things have changed.
I'm going to be honest, I haven't checked up in a while. But I know that overall
the climate has been improving pretty drastically, in terms of the visibility. A
lot of the work that John Gray Williams over int Career Services has done to
promote, I guess, openness, to inspire leadership within the community,
something very nebulous like that. But I mean let's face it; I was down here
this weekend because of an event that he organized, which was a networking event
for LGBTQ students, alumni, professionals, faculty, staff, right, to increase
visibility. Which is the key factor here.

GREEN: Is that something we can follow up on or that students can look up; who's
a designated Safe Zone?

HERNANDEZ: Yeah sure. So last I checked, the Safe Zones where being marked on a
Google map, with lots of little pins on a little pin board. Ever since then, I
don't know if there is an official registry of who is safe zone certified or
not. You may want to talk with somebody at MPS (Multicultural Programs and
Services) about that. Because I think that Safe Zone, the program, falls under
the jurisdiction of the LGBTQ coordinator there.

GREEN: Well we will definitely follow up on that, and I'll let you know.

HERNANDEZ: Because I think it would be great to see if we have that sort of
visible metric. I know that ever since I made those remarks at the Aspire!
Awards reception back in 2013, I know that for example the Smith Career Center
has gotten better certifications for how much they support the LGBTQ community
through this national organization called Out for Work. Out for Work gives
career centers at universities one of four classifications: bronze, silver,
gold, or like gold plus, something like that, A+gold, I don't know. It's really
good is what it is. And so prior to all of this stuff, me talking with John
Gray, starting OSTEM, getting the Aspire! Award, Virginia Tech's Smith Career
Center was at a bronze certification, right. And so how it sort of works is if
you have the gold plus certification you've got 100 out of 100, that's your
score. If you have gold, it's like 90 to 100, or 90 to 99, silver is like 70 to
90, and then bronze is like you applied.

GREEN: [laughs]

HERNANDEZ: And you didn't get one of the other three ones. So it was cool that
we have a bronze certification but it means nothing, if it's sort of the catch
all, if it's the default, if it doesn't denote that we've made any sort of
excellence in that regard, aside from applying for the certification. Since
then, I believe it was one or two weeks after that Friday, after the awards
ceremony, John Gray let me know that we got a silver certification, which was
actually surprising, and a great surprise. It was really nice. And then
recently, I believe that we now have a gold certification. So we're among the
upper echelon in career centers that support LGBTQ individuals. I think that the
amount of growth there has just been incredible. Like that's great.

GREEN: That's very encouraging. And I want to talk about the Aspire! Award and
what that meant to you.

HERNANDEZ: Ok. So I'll admit that it was a bit out of left field. John Gray,
among other individuals, nominated me for the Award for Creative Leadership. But
nobody told me about it!

GREEN: [laughs]

HERNANDEZ: So I get an email in February, March maybe, saying 'hey you've been
nominated for this award. We'd like to recognize you for your excellence in
Creative Leadership, etc. etc.' So for me, in a sense, it was sort of a
validation to myself that what I was doing, this work with OSTEM, was making a
meaningful impact on the university, that I wasn't just some kid making his own
special interest club just for the heck of it. That what I was doing was having
a real impact on the university. And that for me was, let's face it, it was
gratifying. It was awesome! Like, I felt so good about it, but I did not like
waking up at 8am to go to Owens Banquet Hall for that reception.

GREEN: [laughs]

HERNANDEZ: Because I hate waking up at anytime that isn't 10am, let's face it.
Aside from that, for me it was just nice having, you know, recognition. It was
nice for the organization, for OSTEM, to have that recognition by the university
that, yeah, now we're a player. We're taking steps to improve the climate,
improve the environment here at Virginia Tech. And it was a very satisfying
feeling. What I was specifically nominated for was the fact that I had founded
OSTEM, that myself as a queer person of color, as an individual in the STEM
fields, some of which are actually not very typically diverse. Computer Science,
my field, is a mild exception when it comes to sexual orientation, but otherwise
yeah, not terribly diverse. So being there to step out and say 'hey we can't let
this go on. We can't let Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics, the
four things that sort of drive progress when it comes to, you know, almost
anything really. They can't be dominated by conservative minded straight white
males and they're only 30s to early 50s, right. We can't let it all be Dilberts,
right. We can't let all STEM just be Dilbert, Dilbert, Dilbert, Dilbert.' There
needs to be some sort of diversity there, and to be recognized as somebody
fighting for that, that was very powerful for me. To say 'hey I'm putting my
neck out there to help better the environment for those that follow in my
footsteps, that tread the path of a queer individual in the STEM fields.' Being
able to make that environment better, that's what I was nominated for, and
having the opportunity to do that was very powerful.

GREEN: I hope that's a representation of a way forward for the school.

HERNANDEZ: Oh I absolutely hope so. Aren't we getting gender neutral, at least,
bathrooms in the near future?

GREEN: Someone mentioned that they hoped Virginia Tech would do that, but I
don't know if Virginia Tech has a plan yet to do that.

HERNANDEZ: Yeah. Um there's a digression that I won't go into, alright.

GREEN: [laughs] No, you can.

HERNANDEZ: Oh ok then, I don't know.

GREEN: State your piece. 

HERNANDEZ: This could be very dangerous because it
involves the Board of Visitors.

GREEN: Oh.

HERNANDEZ: Yeah. So do you know of an individual named Shelli Fowler?

GREEN: It sounds familiar but-

HERNANDEZ: Her wife, oh God, I'm a horrible person for forgetting her name, but
her wife came to the university several years ago, I think more than ten years
ago, to, you know, work as a professor, brought Shelli along with her, and the
Board of Visitors like terminated something. And it was basically really shitty
because it was like partner benefits and then suddenly no partner benefits. And
so the Board of Visitors, to my knowledge, has been very like, on and off. It's
very difficult to deal with them when it comes to university wide issues such as
gender-neutral bathrooms even. Like, don't even consider gender-neutral housing
because that's insane, right, but just gender-neutral bathrooms, of all things.
That in itself is a struggle. So it's sort of like issues with how the Board is
appointed and the refresh cycle of when board members leave and come on. It
becomes really tricky to build and retain momentum for initiatives such as
gender-neutral housing or bathrooms.

GREEN: I think historically, with almost all LGBT issues, it's always come from
the ground up, you know, it's always come from students and the public putting
pressure on the institutions that be.

HERNANDEZ: Yes! That's definitely it. And I hope that anybody that listens to
this very long winded discussion that, you know, you step up because it's all
about you. It's the grass roots movements. Because you can't really expect
anything to come down from the sky above, even though that's how gravity works.
It starts with us as individuals before we bring it to larger organizations, and
institutions, and even further up than that, like federal initiatives, national
initiatives. It all has to start with us as the individuals.

GREEN: I want to go back to a that statement you made earlier, referring to
yourself as 'a queer person of color.'

HERNANDEZ: Uh huh.

GREEN: Because you have to know that just using the term 'color' is very
deliberately vague.

HERNANDEZ: Uh huh.

GREEN: And I was wondering, if you see your ethnicity and your sexuality ever at odds?

HERNANDEZ: So the short answer to that is yes. The more detailed answer, which
is the digression that I said that I was not going to go into, but it appears
you forced my hand, is that in the Philippines, at least to my knowledge, in
the culture there, there is not a lot of understanding about non-cis-gendered,
or non-heterosexual individuals. The notion that gender and sexuality have to be
linked for individuals, for men in particular, that find themselves to be
homosexual, but due to societal pressures, they have to act and live as women,
right, almost like a forced gender dysphoria. I think that that's something that
I find very strange about Filipino culture. And I think that's certainly one of
the things that went through my parents' minds was that 'oh he's gay, what if he
wants to be a woman next.' I obviously wouldn't know if this is true because I
never asked them about that. But it's always something that's lurked in the back
of my mind. Because it seems that a lot of times, there's this very large
disproportion of individuals who identity as homosexual, or bisexual, that feel
almost as if they have to act femininely because that's the social standard
there. And so, with my parents' upbringing, it was difficult for them to accept
that I was at the time when I came out to them I was a gay individual, who did
not present femininely and was most certainly cis-gender. It was a hard thing
for them to,  sort of, resolve within themselves? I can't think of the right
word. English is such a frustrating language, you know. Anyway, it's funny that
you ask this question, because I did just come back from a trip to the
Philippines, a couple weeks ago, visiting the family, because my grandmother on
my father's side just turned ninety one. Happy birthday to her. So it was very
interesting being back in that environment of my family members who had not been
exposed to American culture, right, who were very classically Filipino. And so,
with all the guys you got to be the macho-man, you know, machismo. You know, all
the women are like very servile. Except that's less true for some of my
relatives. But it's about a half/half split. Anyway, and so it was strange being
there and really seeing this in action, where you've got, like, a bunch of
homosexual men who just act really girly. But they seem very uncomfortable with
it, but they do it anyway because that's the standard.

GREEN: I think that's an impression in the United States too, that gay men are
somehow more effeminate.

HERNANDEZ: I think here it's actually inverted. If you're a male who acts a
little more femininely, people presume that you are a homosexual. Over there
it's the other way round, where if you're a homosexual we presume that you're effeminate.

GREEN: Oh ok.

HERNANDEZ: Yeah very subtle inversion, but that's a pretty key difference.

GREEN: And I think you mentioned earlier about how in high school you felt like
you had to be very masculine, very macho, that that was part of your presentation.

HERNANDEZ: Yeah, I suppose yeah. I guess it was, yeah it was sort of that as well
as just sort of my lack of understanding of how gender roles came into the
equation as well as sexual orientation, sort of a byproduct of my upbringing,
right. And so, when I was younger I was like 'I know don't like sissy boys blah,
blah, blah.' Like it was dumb. It was really stupid. But it was how I was sort
of implicitly raised by my family.

GREEN: If we can go on for a minute to speak about the historical memory of the
LGBQ community here, before we talk a little bit more about the future, I want
to ask you, if you can, to reflect on the generations of LGBQ individuals that
have come to Tech before you. What do you think the differences are between your
experience, over the last four years here, and theirs? What kind of change we
have we had? Because I know you've researched it.

HERNANDEZ: So before I go into this question, I really have to ask: Is there any
particular reason why you are referring to the community as the LGBQ community
as opposed to the LGB 'T' Q community?

GREEN: No. I simply misspoke. I have it written down as 'T' here.

HERNANDEZ: Oh ok than. Yeah I was very curious about that.

GREEN: No, no, no. I'm not being specific or intentionally excluding anyone.

HERNANDEZ: No worries. So, to repeat the question you're asking me: sort of my
impression of generations past, what the climate was here before. And so I did
hint a little bit about this with Shelli and her partner, Dana I think was her
name. In the past things were not that great like when, I believe it was Lambda
Horizons that first cropped up in the late 70s, wait 79, when was that? Thirty
five years ago! There we go. Like thirty five years ago. I think it's thirty
five years ago! But I can't do the math right now. It's fourteen plus twenty
one, that's definitely thirty five. Alright, I did that. So thirty five years
ago, an organization that wanted to support LGBTQ individuals could not be
granted a space on campus to meet. Absolutely unacceptable. Heathenist!
Blasphemy! But it happened in 1979, if memory serves, with Lambda Horizons. And
that was sort of a key moment for the community where they could start
gathering. It began the visibility. There was no more secretive hush hush cabals
in somebody's dorm room or apartment. Now there's a organized visible space for
people to meet, and to grow the community. And from then on it's sort of gone
up. We've, it went from Lambda Horizons to the LGBTA, QGPA, LGBT caucus, right.
Having those three organizations being the central focus during those respective
periods of time. And then, we started having things like Freedom to Mary Day,
which I guess is no longer relevant. So a little background: Freedom to Mary Day
was an event that was also very subtle protesting, where members of the
community would go out to the plaza between Squires and Donaldson Brown, and
we'd announce vows to fight for marriage equality in Virginia. Lo and behold, we
now have marriage equality in Virginia. But you know, it's still events like
those, increasing the visibility, that have sort of been the theme over the
thirty plus years. Creating more visible spaces to affirm individuals of their identities.

GREEN: So we go from having an LGBTQ organization denied to your being awarded
for your work in OSTEM. So I think that is an indication of how far this school
has come in thirty five years, hopefully.

HERNANDEZ: Yeah. Gender-neutral bathrooms, gender-neutral housing.

GREEN: There we go. That's the next step to furthering equality here in the
school. Is there anything that you wish I had asked or you want to address?

HERNANDEZ: Well you know, since we talked about the past, let's talk about the future!

GREEN: Yes!

HERNANDEZ: Right. So once again to those listening, it is October 26th 2014

GREEN: [laughs]

HERNANDEZ: 5pm. And so, there's a lot of things going on. The landscape is
evolving here at Virginia Tech. Over with MPS, now that there are all these
organizations popping up left and right that support the LGBTQ community in
different ways. We're trying to organize under some flavor of umbrella in order
to pool resources and to strengthen the community. That didn't exist before.
Before it was Catherine Cotrupi, in her role as the LGBT coordinator at MPS,
sort of herding cats together, almost like. But now there is so much
collaboration between the organizations, like OSTEM and QGPA, they're having a
movie screening in the near future, jointly together, cosponsoring. You've got
all the organizations cosponsoring the Lavender Ceremony, which is an LGBTQ
graduation ceremony that happens the Thursday before graduation. So I think what
the future holds is just a lot of collaboration between individuals instead of
there being these isolated pockets of communities or individuals. Now we're
starting to come together to become one big central community. And then, you
know, we'll all bond together as part of the Hokie Nation, yay! And I know that
sounds really trite and dumb, and I said it in a very dumb and trite voice, but
in honesty, I think that's the direction that we as a university are going in,
is that we are collaborating more. We're becoming more cohesive as a community.
And I'm very excited to see, you know, come back in fifteen, twenty years to see
what the community is like, just as individuals who graduated in say 1983, they
come back, and they see that the landscape has changed so dramatically. I want
to see that for myself when I come back in fifteen to twenty years.

GREEN: I hope that does happen. I really do, and I hope that this is a part of
it: having everybody come out and contribute their voice to this project. And
again, we thank you so much for coming out.

HERNANDEZ: Oh thank you for having me.

GREEN: Absolutely, it's been our pleasure.

 
 

</transcript><rights>Permission to publish material from the Virginia Tech LGBTQ Oral History Collection must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech</rights><fmt>audio</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation>Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_HernandezDavid.xml</xmllocation><xmlfilename>Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_HernandezDavid.xml</xmlfilename><collection_link>http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/collections/show/86</collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>