<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT><record id="00015448" dt="2015-10-02"><version>4</version><date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2014-10-28</date><date_nonpreferred_format>2014-10-28</date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id>Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_WilliamsJohnGray</cms_record_id><title>Oral History with John Gray Williams, October 28, 2014 (Ms2015-007)</title><accession></accession><duration>01:48:51</duration><collection_id>Ms2015-007</collection_id><collection_name>The Virginia Tech LGBTQ Oral History Collection</collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Virginia Tech Special Collections</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewee>John Gray Williams</interviewee><interviewer>Whitney Wright</interviewer><file_name>Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_WilliamsJohnGray</file_name><sync>1:|29(5)|56(9)|73(10)|88(1)|102(1)|120(3)|135(2)|147(10)|160(11)|177(3)|190(1)|210(3)|223(4)|241(9)|256(4)|270(2)|284(12)|303(6)|315(12)|332(4)|347(12)|368(9)|390(18)|410(2)|430(5)|445(8)|461(3)|486(5)|504(10)|516(11)|532(9)|553(7)|567(5)|580(16)|596(6)|612(6)|626(8)|641(4)|655(13)|675(1)|694(5)|710(8)|729(2)|744(1)|756(1)|774(2)|791(2)|804(10)|819(6)|840(1)|854(1)|874(1)|889(6)|904(7)|918(11)|940(9)|953(4)|965(3)|977(8)|988(13)|1013(3)|1026(15)|1047(5)|1060(4)|1074(12)|1084(5)|1103(11)|1119(10)|1146(11)|1159(8)|1176(13)|1193(3)|1210(1)|1223(16)|1248(13)|1262(10)|1276(15)|1291(5)|1306(8)|1322(13)|1339(3)|1355(4)|1370(11)|1383(10)|1399(10)|1413(12)|1426(11)|1454(4)|1468(1)|1482(11)|1493(14)|1517(8)|1529(9)|1539(12)|1556(1)|1567(5)|1579(17)|1588(13)|1612(14)|1632(2)|1648(6)|1663(9)|1679(9)|1694(3)|1710(9)|1722(15)|1734(14)|1751(3)</sync><media_id></media_id><media_url>http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/files/original/3422/Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_WilliamsJohnGray_OralHistory.1.mp3</media_url><mediafile><host>Other</host><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>audio</clip_format></mediafile><language></language><index><point><time>1</time><title>Introduction</title><partial_transcript>Today is Tuesday, October 28, 2014, I, Whitney Wright, am conducting an interview and Damon Kinmond is the Sound Technician for Virginia Tech's Oral History Project.</partial_transcript><synopsis>An introduction to the interview with John Gray Williams.</synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>23</time><title>Description of family makeup and dynamics</title><partial_transcript>John Gray, thank you so much for doing this we greatly appreciate it. I guess my first question for you starting off is who was important to you growing up and also where are you from, originally?</partial_transcript><synopsis>Talks about the composition of his family growing up.</synopsis><keywords>Blended families;Born;Brothers;Dads;Genetics;Hampton Roads;Mothers;Parents;Siblings;Stepdads;Stepsisters;Virginia Beach</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>309</time><title>Realization of sexuality and choice to be closeted</title><partial_transcript>WRIGHT: Now, I wanted to ask you how do you identify yourself, and did you find... how early on did you
define who you were personally? WILLIAMS: As gay?</partial_transcript><synopsis>Discusses the self-discovery of his sexuality, the shock and fear of having it nearly revealed to his family, and his reasons for remaining closeted prior to college.</synopsis><keywords>childhood;closeted;fear;religion;sexual discovery</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>880</time><title>Pre-college education about LGBTQ history / Gay bullying in high school</title><partial_transcript>Do you, as far as the curriculum, what you learned in high school, do you think that maybe you'd have felt a little more comfortable...</partial_transcript><synopsis>Describes the lack of LGBTQ history in his high school curriculum and describes an effeminite openly gay student who was bullied at his high school.</synopsis><keywords>AIDS;bullying;education</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>1249</time><title>Learning about homosexuality while attending Tidewater Community College</title><partial_transcript>Okay, so this is very interesting, because you're from the Virginia Beach area. How did you end up at Tech...</partial_transcript><synopsis>Describes how he first learned about LGBTQ issues and history while attending Tidewater Community College.</synopsis><keywords>library research;sexual experimentation;transfer students</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>1542</time><title>Decision to transfer to Virginia Tech / Coming out as gay</title><partial_transcript>So was Tech one of the many schools that you researched and you found that it was the best?</partial_transcript><synopsis>Explanation of reasons for wanting to attend Virginia Tech. Description of coming out experiences with family.</synopsis><keywords>activism;first generation college students;LGBT family members;police arrest</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>2405</time><title>Degree path at Virginia Tech / Getting involved with LGBTA as an undergraduate at Virginia Tech</title><partial_transcript>No that was perfect. That was perfect. So you came out to your family, you're at Tech now, and then you're getting involved in...Was it called Hokie Pride at the time?</partial_transcript><synopsis>Talks about his choice of major while at Virginia Tech and making first contact with the LGBTA.</synopsis><keywords>college majors;Gobblerfest;landscape architecture;LGBTQ student groups;Student Work Fair;urban planning</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>2960</time><title>Activism with LGBTA and Soul Force / Encounter with police at the United States Naval Academy in Annapolis, MD</title><partial_transcript>It was really awesome to be in that kind of a space. So then
I...I'm the type of person to get involved really quickly. I went to every meeting.</partial_transcript><synopsis>Describes joint activism conducted by LGBTA and Soul Force across the region, including an altercation with police at the United States Naval Academy.</synopsis><keywords>activism;Corps of Cadets;Don't Ask Don't Tell;police;protests;Soul Force</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>3215</time><title>Intercultural and diversity climate at Virginia Tech in 2014</title><partial_transcript>So were there any activities on campus or any moments of protest on campus? I mean what was your experience here?</partial_transcript><synopsis>Digression about recent initiatives led by the College Republicans related to immigration issues.</synopsis><keywords>Alien Invasion;College Republicans;illegal immigration;undocumented immigrants</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>3358</time><title>Vandalism of the LGBTA office door / Start of the Give A Damn campaign</title><partial_transcript>WILLIAMS: Yeah, so the LGBTA office door was vandalized while I was student here. People basically ripped pages out of a Bible, like the Bible verses – they call them the Clobber Passages – there’s like eight verses in the Bible that deal with same sex sexual activity. I don’t even call it homosexuality or gay sex because those identities didn’t even exist in Biblical times. It’s purely like same sex interactions. They ripped the Bible pages out that had those verses in them and glued them to our door and highlighted or circled the passages, and they took a sharpie and wrote on the door &quot;God hates fags&quot; &quot;Fags burn in hell&quot; &quot;You’re going to hell&quot; and all that stuff. </partial_transcript><synopsis>Describes a 2005 incident of vandalism directed at the LGBTA office, Virginia Tech's response, and the LGBTA's response.</synopsis><keywords>hate crimes;religion;Safewatch Program;vandalism;Zenobia Hikes</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>3849</time><title>Inspiration to participate in pro-gay activism</title><partial_transcript>What do you think...and this is with any marginalized group...what do you think, or how did you feel, what prompted you, where did you find that strength to fight?</partial_transcript><synopsis>Discusses his reasons for becoming an advocate for LGBTQ issues.</synopsis><keywords>activism;defiance;inspiration</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>3976</time><title>Freedom to Marry Day at Virginia Tech, Spring 2006</title><partial_transcript>So how did these events...I know you mentioned the gay marriage, was that on campus?</partial_transcript><synopsis>Describes the Freedom to Marry Day event in Spring of 2006.</synopsis><keywords>activism;gay marriage;protests;same sex marriage</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink>http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/CT_LGBTQ/CT_Vol103_No76_2006_0212_pg1</hyperlink><hyperlink_text>See the Freedom to Marry Day photo and article here</hyperlink_text></point><point><time>4122</time><title>LGBTA name change to Hokie Pride / Transition from student involvement to faculty involvement</title><partial_transcript>WRIGHT: Alright, Hokie Pride. WILLIAMS: Like the current group? WRIGHT: Your involvement...well let's clarify that...When did it become Hokie Pride?</partial_transcript><synopsis>Talks about the name change from LGBTA to Hokie Pride and about coming back to the group after having left for graduate school.</synopsis><keywords>gay student groups;LGBT student groups</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>4283</time><title>Gay Awareness Week / Gay? Fine by Me Rally</title><partial_transcript>I became an officer and I became in charge of Gay Awareness Week, which is now Pride Week. And so I brought...I was in charge of an entire weeklong series of events where I brought a couple gay speakers to campus, and we actually had another protest. It was called the Gay? Fine by Me Rally where we had a generous donator...donor who donated a bunch of shirts that say “Gay.” Have you ever seen the gay fine by me?</partial_transcript><synopsis>Describes the Gay? Fine by Me Rally and Gay Awareness Week events at Virginia Tech.</synopsis><keywords>Crysta Highfield;Gay Awareness Week;Pride Week</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>4437</time><title>Post-grad involvement with LGBTA Relay for Life / Choosing student affairs and the University of Delaware for graduate school</title><partial_transcript>WRIGHT: So I want to get back to some of your
story and I know so... WILLIAMS: Oh, what time is it? Kinmond: It is 6:55. WILLIAMS: Okay. WRIGHT: Alright, so at some point you leave and was it going off to grad school or were you working?</partial_transcript><synopsis>Talks about being involved with LGBTA events after graduation and the decision to pursue a graduate degree in student affairs at another school.</synopsis><keywords>graduate school;Relay for Life;student affairs</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>4739</time><title>Diversity at Virginia Tech / Career services as a career focus / End of relationship / Return to Virginia Tech as faculty</title><partial_transcript>WRIGHT: Well, that's awesome and that gets us to here  your current experience here working at Tech. And I also want to ask you about the diversity on Tech's campus as well as student population, faculty population, administrators, and things and how does that...how did that effect...or how does that effect the gay and queer population here, or do you see a correlation between the diversity or even maybe lack of and if that kind of effects the atmosphere in a way here?</partial_transcript><synopsis>Discussion of diversity and representation of marginalized groups at Virginia Tech and decision to pursue a career in the student affairs discipline of career services. Description of long distance relationship ending, and the awkwardness involved in returning to Blacksburg after graduate school.</synopsis><keywords>Career Services;diversity;marginalized groups;minority groups;romantic relationships;Scott Burton</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>5223</time><title>Multicultural Programs and Services at Virginia Tech / Diversity issues in job search / LGBT networking reception / SafeZone</title><partial_transcript>WILLIAMS: They let me do lots of diversity and social justice stuff at my office. 

WRIGHT: Like what? 

WILLIAMS: So I'm the
liaison to Multicultural Programs and Services from our department so I'm the face of Career Services for MPS. </partial_transcript><synopsis>Describes his current job at Virginia Tech including a discussion of job related diversity issues, coordination of an LGBT networking reception, and his work with the SafeZone program.</synopsis><keywords>inclusiveness;LGBT Networking Reception;LGBTQ job search issues;Multicultural Programs and Services;SafeZone</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>5647</time><title>Reasons for participating in the project</title><partial_transcript>WRIGHT: Well I'm not gonna say last question because I'll probably ask a follow up but why did you choose to participate in this project? WILLIAMS: Cause I think my story is worth hearing. WRIGHT: And it is.</partial_transcript><synopsis>Explains his motivation for participating in the project.</synopsis><keywords>gay marriage;gay rights movement;millennials;same-sex marriage</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>5764</time><title>Positive experiences of being a Hokie</title><partial_transcript>WRIGHT: That's gonna be my, probably, final question for you, well second to last question for you. Can you share some of the positive experiences of being a Hokie, and even at your current position, and you're still a Hokie?</partial_transcript><synopsis>Talks about positive feelings related to Virginia Tech.</synopsis><keywords>community;inclusiveness;school spirit</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>5889</time><title>Representation of diversity issues in the classroom at Virginia Tech and in mainstream media</title><partial_transcript>WRIGHT: And then this will be my final question: was there anything that we didn't discuss that you would like to share?  WILLIAMS: Hmmm [Whispers] I don't know, possibly. [Laughs] Um...hmm...yeah I don't know. </partial_transcript><synopsis>Discussion of the lack of education about marginalized populations in general and LGBT issues in particular and how this led to an interest in social justice. Further discussion about colonialism, white privilege, and the long-term economic effects of colonialism on the economy of Africa.</synopsis><keywords>cash crops;colonialism;education;social constructs;social identities;social justice;white privilege</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>6290</time><title>Issues affecting the LGBT community after same sex marriage was legalized</title><partial_transcript>WRIGHT: Alright, this is my final question. WILLIAMS: This is so unrelated but...[laughs] WRIGHT: I promise you, this is my final question to you, throughout our interview, I think at least three or four occasions you mentioned the current issues for the gay community.</partial_transcript><synopsis>Talks about issues that continue to concern the LGBTQ community after securing marriage equality by relating the LGBTQ civil rights struggle to the civil rights movement in the 1960s.</synopsis><keywords>alphabet soup;bullying;gay marriage;interracial marriage;Loving v. Virginia.;marriage equality;post-racial;religion;same sex marriage;suicide</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>6517</time><title>Closing</title><partial_transcript>WRIGHT: Thank you. WILLIAMS: Yeah, thank you. WRIGHT: For your time. WILLIAMS: Happy to help. Let me know if this ends up in a gay history book or something. WRIGHT: Will do.</partial_transcript><synopsis>Closing of the interview with John Gray Williams</synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point></index><type></type><description>John Gray Williams is a Career Advisor in Career Services at Virginia Tech. From 2005 to 2008 he also attended Virginia Tech as an undergraduate student in the Bachelor of Arts in Public and Urban Affairs program. He has been active in LGBTQ activism since he first came to Virginia Tech, working on events such as the Freedom to Marry Day, Gay? Fine by Me Rally, and the LGBTA Relay for Life. As a member of the faculty, he has organized a yearly LGBTQ networking reception and has served as a trainer for the SafeZone program. In his role in Career Services, he is a passionate social justice advocate and works to help members of marginalized populations identify discrimination concerns in the job market.

The interview was conducted on October 28, 2014 at John Gray Williams’s home in Blacksburg, VA. The interviewer was Whitney Wright and she was assisted by Damon Kinmond. There was limited time for the interview and there are moments within the interview where discussion of the time and Williams’s evening plans can be heard. The interview lasts almost two hours. It begins with a description of Williams’s family and their social dynamics and proceeds into his early experience and understanding of his sexuality and his motivations for choosing to be closeted. The interview then moves into his time at Tidewater Community College where he was first able to research homosexuality and the history of the LGBTQ civil rights movement. He then discusses his decision to transfer to Virginia Tech to pursue a career in Landscape Architecture and his decision to come out to his family. A significant portion of the interview is concerned with his involvement with the LGBTA at Virginia Tech and the variety of protests and events he participated in while completing his undergraduate degree. Then, he discusses his decision to attend the University of Delaware to pursue student affairs while remaining close enough to Blacksburg to maintain a relationship with a student at Virginia Tech. He then describes his return to Virginia Tech as a faculty member and the work he has done to support the LGBTQ community and other marginalized populations since returning. Finally, he discusses broader issues affecting the LGBTQ community beyond the fight for marriage equality.</description><rel /><transcript>﻿Interview with John Gray Williams

Date of Interview: October 28, 2014

Interviewer: Whitney Wright

Assistant: Damon Kinmond

Place of Interview: John Gray Williams's residence, Blacksburg, Virginia

Length: 1:48:51

Transcriber: David Atkins

Whitney Wright: Today is October 28, 2014, I, Whitney Wright, am conducting an
interview and Damon Kinmond is the Sound Technician for Virginia Tech's Oral
History Project. Today we are interviewing Mr. John Gray Williams, and he goes
by John Gray, and we are meeting at his home at 611 Progress Street in
Blacksburg, Virginia and it's now 5:45. So John Gray, thank you so much for
doing this we greatly appreciate it. I guess my first question for you starting
off is who was important to you growing up and also where are you from, originally?

John Gray Williams: Okay, so I was born and raised in Virginia Beach, Virginia.
Grew up in a very middle class, suburban upbringing in the Hampton Roads area
and do you need any more details than that?

WRIGHT: Yeah, like your parents, any siblings?

WILLIAMS: Okay, yeah sure. So I'm from a blended family. So my mom and dad
divorced when I was six and I have a younger brother, biological full-blood
brother, who's six years younger than me. He was a baby when they divorced. So
then my mom remarried when I was eight, so then I got two older stepsisters.

WRIGHT: Did you live with your mother or your father?

WILLIAMS: My mother.

WRIGHT: So you lived with your mother.

WILLIAMS: Yes.

WRIGHT: And their names, if you don't mind me asking?

WILLIAMS: Yeah, sure, full names or just first names?

WRIGHT: yeah.

WILLIAMS: Maiden name for the mother? I mean I'm serious though. I don't know
how much detail to go into. So my mom is...her name is Deborah Evelyn Griffin
née Thorbeyonsin[?] My last name's Williams because that's my dad's last name.

WRIGHT: Okay.

WILLIAMS: My dad is John Lawrence Williams. So I'm not a junior because he's got
a different middle name. My brother's name is Scott Daniel Williams. And then
like I said my mom divorced and my brother and I went to live with her for two
years and then she got remarried to my stepdad Hugh Griffin and then I got two
older stepsisters, Jessica Griffin and Sheila Griffin. And then my dad got not
officially remarried but he has a girlfriend of 20 years, a partner I guess,
they've risen beyond the girlfriend level but they're not married. And he has a
daughter through her so I have a half-sister named Amber Williams. So, lots of
blending of the families. And what else?

WRIGHT: Who was important to you in that structure, like were you close to or
closer to any sibling, or it was a very close knit family?

WILLIAMS: No, pretty dysfunctional family.

WRIGHT: In what way?

WILLIAMS: [Laughs] Oh in my brother and I were always closer to my mom and the
sisters were always closer to their dad. We tried really hard to sort of work
against that a lot of times, you know. My stepdad was a good person, my mom was
a good person, but I think just being raised during those formative years with
the other parent, you know, my stepdad joined my life when I was eight so I was
always closer to my mom. My little brother kind of was in the middle because he
was only two when they got married, so he sometimes even referred to my stepdad
as dad. But I'm a momma's boy, to get to the answer that you're looking for,
definitely closest with my mom and my little brother because we had a lot in
common. I do really do think that genetics plays a huge role to some extent just
in the sense...

WRIGHT: Genetics in which way?

WILLIAMS: In the sense that my brother and I--our brains–we think so
similarly, we approach life so similarly, and I see a lot of my dad in him. I
see a lot of both my mom and my dad in both of us. And so even though my
stepsisters and I and him, for most of our lives lived in the same environment,
we're so different and I think that's partially because of genetics.

WRIGHT: In what way though, when you say different what are their personalities
different? Describe yourself, your personality compared to your siblings to get
a kind of an idea.

WILLIAMS: So my brother and I are really analytical. We're really driven. We're
hard working. We have good work ethics. We are very... he's super left-brained,
I'm like left- and right-brained, and I feel like my sisters are really
right-brained. They also have a lot more, I don't know they have a lot more
dysfunction in their lives. My older sister's been divorced, married and
divorced twice by the time she was thirty-five. The other one still lives at
home and doesn't have a job and she's thirty-two. They're just, their lives are
not, they're not good at managing their lives.

WRIGHT: Well that's very interesting that the family dynamics. Now, I wanted to
ask you how do you identify yourself, and did you find... how early on did you
define who you were personally?

WILLIAMS: As gay?

WRIGHT: Yes.

WILLIAMS: Okay. Don't worry, I know that's an awkward question to ask someone,
but it's not awkward to ask me that. So, yeah and I'm sorry, I can ramble on in
any direction you want me to go. So, in my life going back to a very early age,
I remember being in locker rooms as a little kid, like at the rec center, and
being fascinated by people who would shower naked at the rec center. You know
you go to the pool and gym then you come and shower. I always showered in my
bathing suit or in underwear. And then people would get naked and I just was so
fascinated at seeing other naked people because in my mind it was just like
naked, cool nudity. Not even thinking like – &quot;oh man,&quot; but then I got a little
older and some of my friends were like &quot;wouldn't it be cool if there was a peep
hole like through the wall into the girls locker room so we could actually see
what we want to see.&quot; And I just remember being like &quot;huh, that thought never
even occurred to me I get all the nudity I want right here.&quot; It sounds creepy
now because I'm an adult but this was in the brain of a seven or eight year old
kid. I was just fascinated looking at those naked men when I was a little kid.

WRIGHT: So you kind of had a sense at a very young age that...

WILLIAMS: The word gay, the identity of &quot;oh I'm, that means I'm gay and I'm
different&quot; was no way, not a part of it. For me at the time it was just like the
novelty of people who were so comfortable showing their penises in public, you
know what I mean. And then when I was in eighth grade, I discovered internet
porn and I mean when you're in eighth grade, I was like what, fourteen? I just
typed in &quot;free sex&quot; or whatever you know to type in to get porn, and it was men
and women and I was like &quot;whoa this is great.&quot;  Then I discovered bisexual porn
that had like two men and a woman and I was like &quot;wow that's even better, I was
like look at these guys are touching each other and they don't even care, he
didn't even care that...&quot; I don't know how graphic I can get but &quot;he didn't even
care that his penis just touched his penis. They didn't even care. That's so cool.&quot;

And then I slowly started to realize that I wasn't paying attention to the women
at all. And then I was like, &quot;what would happen if I just saw two men? That's
gay, is that gay?&quot; Make sure late at night, no parents are awake, and typed 'gay
porn' and the rest was history, so to speak. And then of course my parents found
the history files that I didn't delete and they confronted me. That was when I
was in tenth grade. So from eighth to tenth grade I'd kind of been figuring it
out, kind of coming to terms with the fact that I was gay, but I had never
really accepted it. It was just sort of like I'm just figuring it all out. And
then my mom confronted me because she found the internet history files and I
lied. I was like, &quot;Oh, I was just curious. I was just exploring a bunch of
stuff. I was just comparing sizes.&quot; That's what I said to her – &quot;comparing
sizes.&quot; Cause as you know, you need to watch two men having sex with each other
in order to compare penis size. [Laughs] That's the only way to do it. And so
she bought it because I think she wanted the conversation to just be over.

Well, she was cooking dinner at that time and she had run out of milk, she
needed milk for the recipe for whatever she was cooking, and I was in the tenth
grade and I had just gotten my driver's license. So you know if either of y'all
drove in high school, when you finally get your license the parents love it
'cause they're like sending you to do every errand on earth and you love it
'cause it's like &quot;Yes an excuse to drive!&quot; So she sent me to the grocery store
to get milk. The grocery store was like a mile away. I could've probably walked
but you know I drove to get the milk. And I lost it in the parking lot of the
grocery store.

WRIGHT: What do you mean lost it?

WILLIAMS: Broke down crying, inconsolable, couldn't breathe, hyperventilating,
type of crying. Because what I had known, again going back to being a little kid
kind of figuring that out in the locker room all the way up until I discovered
gay porn and had been secretly watching that for two years, I had never been
confronted with the reality of what that meant socially. You know, it was just
like my dirty little secret and now it wasn't my dirty little secret anymore. So
I had to wrestle with the fact that now they knew this thing I was, it was
beyond like ashamed of, it was like – No, no one can know about this and yet
someone does know. The cognitive dissonance of this thing I decided no one would
ever know and now someone knows.

And then of course I was raised in the Christian church, I was raised Methodist,
so wrestling with...I didn't go to a bible thumping, like super conservative,
super fundamentalist church. Where like the preacher wasn't up there saying,
&quot;Hellfire and brimstone gay sinners burn in hell,&quot; none of that, but it was
still like unspoken. I mean, I knew what the bible said, stone, if a man lies
with a man, stone him to death. You know, and so I was like &quot;but I didn't choose
this, God made me this way, and why did God make me this way if he didn't want
me to be gay?&quot; And why, I was just like, it was all happening at the same time.
The religious issues, the family issues, the social stigma, the I didn't choose
it, and I just cried in that car in that parking lot for like an hour. And
remember I was supposed to be getting milk.

So I finally, and this was before cell phones, so I finally drive back home with
the milk. The whole family has eaten dinner. My mom finished the recipe with
half and half that she had in the fridge. She just used like coffee creamer. She
was like, &quot;I didn't know where the hell you were and I needed to finish
cooking.&quot; She could tell, I tried my best to clean my face up but she could tell
I was upset. And so her and I walked into the kitchen and she came and she gave
me a hug and she said, &quot;no matter what I'll always love you.&quot; And I said, and I
tried to play it cool like &quot;Okay, whatever, I don't know why you said that. No
need to say that. I'm...&quot; That was in tenth grade.

WRIGHT: Why did you feel that like you just weren't, still at that point you
weren't ready to kind of...?

WILLIAMS: Because like, why like, if she caught me and told me she loved me no
matter what why didn't I just like come out?

WRIGHT: Yeah.

WILLIAMS: Because...I just wasn't ready. It's so hard to explain, I mean, I feel
like I should try to find a way to put it into words, but it was sort of like
that–here's how I would explain it–that moment for me was the first time
that I even accepted the possibility of what that meant--that I was gay. So it
wasn't like from eighth grade to tenth grade I was coming to terms with it, it
was like my beginning to come to terms with it started in the tenth grade with
that moment. Because up until then it was like, I'm not gay, I just like
watching, no I'm not gay. So from tenth grade...I mean I pretty much became
asexual. Because I, and people sort of asked me because I never dated girls, I
never tried to fake it or hide it or pretend to like girls.

WRIGHT: So what was your experience like in middle school, high school, your
interactions with your classmates and your teachers, and dealing with your
sexuality, or just trying to come into your own and understand it yourself?

WILLIAMS: Yeah, so I remember once a girl asked me out and...

WRIGHT: When was this?

WILLIAMS: This was in eleventh grade and, 'cause her friends told me she had a
crush on me and I was like &quot;oooo, that's fun,&quot; everyone loves being wanted,
right. But I was also a late bloomer, and I wasn't socially awkward but I was
just like socially neutral. You know what I mean? I wasn't a popular kid but I
got along with everyone. Like if I were to show you my high school yearbook I
had, I mean the pages are filled with signatures, because everyone knew because
I was like the class clown, the jolly guy, the guy that made people laugh, the
guy that was nice to everyone. But like, I didn't get invited to parties. I
didn't get asked out on dates. You know, everyone liked me but I wasn't anyone's
real friend.

And so I kind of coasted by with that, with that identity of like class clown,
everyone's friend, but I was not a sexual being in high school. So I think
people just–and I was chubby, I mean I'm still chubby, I say it like it
changed [Laughs], and so the expectation wasn't even there that I would have a
girlfriend. I think it helped insulate me, no pun intended. Because it was kind
of like, well he doesn't have a girlfriend because he's overweight. He has low
self esteem or people don't find him attractive or whatever. And so that kind of
insulated me. I didn't get too many questions about why I didn't have a
girlfriend, 'cause I think that's why people thought. Some people did you know,
&quot;When are you gonna start dating?&quot; But yeah...

WRIGHT: Do you, as far as the curriculum, what you learned in high school, do
you think that maybe you'd have felt a little more comfortable with maybe if you
had learned or knew about gay history or gay experiences, maybe if you'd have
learned about that within your curriculum growing up from middle school to high school?

WILLIAMS: Hmmm, yeah that's, well that's really speculative, but I can remember
from–what's it called? Family life? Health education, family life, where you
learn about the birds and the bees. I just always remember it was boys and
girls, boys are separated from girls because boys like girls and girls like boys
and you have to separate them when we're talking about sex. And I was never as
immature as other boys, in my opinion, and I wonder now looking back is that
because I was gay and didn't know it. I'm going back to like fifth or sixth
grade now, but I just never remember like, &quot;girls have cooties&quot; and you know I
just–I feel like I'm not answering your question.

WRIGHT: No, you are. That's actually very helpful. That's another, we learn
typically in health, we learn about boys and girls, we don't really learn about
same sex or anything of that nature.

WILLIAMS: Right.

WRIGHT: Now, and that's a valid point I'm glad you brought that up, now I was a
history teacher and so I'm wondering if maybe you would've learned about...I
guess a better question is–who was the first person that you found out or knew
that was gay? Do you remember? Like the first person was it someone in your
neighborhood, or someone you learned about in history, or can you remember that?

WILLIAMS: Wow...that's a tough one. I'm not necessarily saying he's the first
but he's coming to mind. There was an out gay kid at my high school and his name
happened to be Barry, which was very unfortunate because everyone called him
&quot;Barry the fairy.&quot; Including me, but I mean I never made fun of him to his face
but I just remember like he was just known, everyone was like &quot;that's Barry the
fairy.&quot; So I contributed to that oppression, so to speak, by endorsing that name
and using it. But I mean I was never someone to actively make fun of someone to
their face.

WRIGHT: Was it a situation where you weren't quite, because who hadn't come in
to your own yet, so you couldn't necessarily identify with him, is that kind of,
maybe had something to do with?

WILLIAMS: Yeah, well this is where gender complicates things because, or gender
presentation and gender expression, because he was very effeminate. You know, he
wore eye liner... &quot;Oh my god girl did you see...&quot; I mean he was like one of the
girls. You know what I mean? And I wasn't like that so I think it had more to do
with gender presentation and expression than sexual orientation. Although, he
was also gay.

WRIGHT: Now this sort of ties back to where I was originally going and this may
be very difficult for you to answer this because it's kind of difficult to
reflect back or put yourself back in that situation. But do you think,
potentially if you were learning about...of course this has something to do with
the position of outing...but there are some historical figures that we know were
part of the community and do you feel like if that was maybe discussed, and not
just as this person's gay but it's just a part of the curriculum, just like we
learned about Native Americans or Asians or Hispanics or blacks or women, if you
were to learn about this gay man or woman do you feel like that would've made
any difference in your educational experience, looking back?

WILLIAMS: I think definitely. I mean if...I'm thinking about Harvey Milk you
know...didn't know who that was until I got to college and that was later in
college. It would be awesome to learn about Harvey Milk alongside other Civil
Rights leaders. Learned about Martin Luther King, Malcolm X, Gandhi, Susan B.
Anthony, I'm trying...I could name a lot more but I'm trying to think about the
ones I learned about in high school. Yeah, that would be cool to see some gay
civil rights leaders. To get back to your other question, I'm thinking really I
think my first exposure to gay things in general, sadly enough, because I grew
up in the nineties, was AIDS related. I think my first sort of exposure to gay
people was through AIDS awareness and AIDS propaganda...

WRIGHT: Through the media or?

WILLIAMS: Yeah, because I'm 30 so I was born in 1984, which was right when the
AIDS crisis was starting and it kind of like... it came to a real head, it
peaked in the early nineties, which was right when I was coming of age. So I
just remember hearing a lot in the media about gay people and AIDS.

WRIGHT: Do you remember, like I can think of &quot;My So-called Life,&quot; I'm around the
same age as you, so was there anything that stands out to you during that time
period that kind of was dealing with, and I know you said AIDS, but just any the
community or AIDS was there anything that you remember, specifically?

WILLIAMS: Specifically with regards to AIDS?

WRIGHT: Yes:

WILLIAMS: Um...no not really, but when you said &quot;My So-called Life&quot; it triggered
something else in me. The Real World, Danny, that was one of my earliest
crushes, Danny from the Real World, New Orleans. I would love to know what year
that was, probably like 2000, 2001.[RW-New Orleans premiered in June 2000]
Also...so these are...so that was before I was out, that was in an interim
period. So I came out of the closet when I was 21. So there was a five year gap.
So I was 16 when my mom confronted me in the kitchen and I was 21 before I
actually uttered the words out loud &quot;I'm gay.&quot;

WRIGHT: Okay, so this is very interesting, because you're from the Virginia
Beach area. How did you end up at Tech and then what was the experience here,
and then I will kind of come to when you decided to come out, so I want to
figure out what led to that part?

WILLIAMS: So it's because my journey is not what you might be thinking. I was a
community college transfer, so I didn't come here when I was 18. I came out
because I was coming to Virginia Tech. Well that's not true, that's not why, but
that was why it happened when it did.

WRIGHT: So can we start from community college to...

WILLIAMS: Yes. So I was at community college and it was clearly, I was out of
the ruts of high school and I remember checking out books from the local
community college on homosexuality

WRIGHT: Which?

WILLIAMS: Tidewater–I remember checking out books out of the library on
homosexuality and researching it on computers there 'cause this again was 2002,
some people had laptops, but it wasn't like everyone everywhere had a laptop at
that time. So I didn't have a laptop so it was the family computer or a computer
at TCC. So I remember doing a lot of gay research and stuff there and just kind
of learning a lot more and getting more comfortable with it until it finally got
to the point where I knew I was gonna eventually come out. Like, I made up my
mind that I couldn't live this secret life. I didn't want to live a dual life. I
made up my mind that I wasn't going to be totally closeted, but I also wasn't
going to do this–I'm gonna live my gay life in secret and have boyfriends and
date people but no one in my real life's gonna know.

WRIGHT: So during this time period were you living, did you have that life?
Where you had your friends, your gay friends in your life?

WILLIAMS: Nope.

Wright So right now you're just exploring?

WILLIAMS: Right.

WRIGHT: Okay.

WILLIAMS: And I don't know if it's like a, in my mind I need to think more
critically about really what that was all about, but I kind of, almost like it
was a virtuous kind of thing. Where it was like–I'm not going to indulge. I'm
not gonna let myself, sort of like, have this gay life until I'm brave enough to
come out and own it and live it. I did experiment a little bit, I was a nineteen
year old and horny, right. So I did have a little fling here or there on the
side, but I didn't try to date anyone. There was no boyfriend. There was none of that.

WRIGHT: So, if you don't mind me asking, so you did have...there were sexual interactions?

WILLIAMS: Yes. There were sexual experiences that were of the hookup, the one
night stand type of variety. And they were all done through the internet, which
was probably dangerous looking back. Because it wasn't like I...'cause I came to
Tech – I'm not gonna fast-forward I just – here I became part of the gay
community so I got invited to gay parties and I knew gay people which led me to
other gay people, which led me to...I had plenty of one night stands here but
they were done more organically through people who I already knew or through
parties. But back then it was like gay hookup websites. So...shameful past.

WRIGHT: No, no, not at all, not at all actually.

WILLIAMS: Now I'm all about my sexual freedom. I don't want to ever...just do
what you gotta do.

WRIGHT: At some point...well how old were you, because community college, you
came to Tech at twenty one, so 19?

WILLIAMS: Three years there.

WRIGHT: Three years, okay.

WILLIAMS: And I did three years there because my mentor there convinced me that
I should get my associate's degree before I transferred, because originally I
was just going to transfer with whatever credits I had. And she was like, &quot;A:
you're going to have a tougher time getting in because with the matriculation
agreement if you have an associate's degree and above a 3.5 you have a
guaranteed admission to any state school. So if you don't do that then they're
going to be evaluating you a lot more, with a lot more scrutiny. And, God forbid
something happens at Tech and you don't graduate at least you have your
associates to fall back on.&quot; So she convinced me to stay and get it which led me
to being there for a third year.

So now we're back to me coming out, so I'd had a few flings here and there, I'd
done a lot of research, I read a lot of books, and I decided as I was
researching schools to apply to I was looking at the LGBT student organization
here on campus, which is now called Hokie Pride, back then it was the LGBTA, and
like they had all these pictures of like these gay parties that they had or
these big gay events, and all these links to resources. They're like &quot;We have a
weekly fun meeting and we also have a weekly support group meeting for people
who are just coming out.&quot; I'm like that's perfect. That's just what I need. So I
was starting to really fantasize, not in a sexual way but like in a... I was so
excited to be coming some place that had gay people who were out that I could
get involved with in that community.

WRIGHT: So was Tech one of the many schools that you researched and you found
that it was the best?

WILLIAMS: No. It was...Tech predated any of that research. I wanted to come to
Virginia Tech. And then, thankfully, I found this gay community there. It was
like Tech was the one driving the ship. That decision was driving the ship and
then the gay was like the icing.

WRIGHT: So what was it about Tech that wanted you, like that was your ideal as a
kid school, or...?

WILLIAMS: It was. I am a first generation college student. My dad didn't even
graduate high school. My mom graduated high school but no college. But growing
up my granddad loved watching college football and he rooted for Virginia Tech,
and I mean I was a little kid. He didn't go to Virginia Tech. He just rooted for
Virginia Tech. So I had positive memories associated with Virginia Tech as a
little kid. And he passed away when I was in sixth grade so that kind of went
away but I'd already been, it was in my mind. And then I figured out...I figured
out that I wanted to be an architect when I was in high school. Well there's
only two public schools in Virginia that offer architecture – Virginia Tech
and UVA, and again, somewhere back in my mind I thought Virginia Tech was the
better school because that's who granddad rooted for. So I just kind of never
really considered UVA. And again I wasn't looking at George Mason or JMU or ODU
because they didn't have architecture. So that's what kind of led me on this
track to Virginia Tech,.

WRIGHT: And it so happened that they had this great community so that's awesome?

WILLIAMS: Right.

WRIGHT: Okay. So what were some of your experiences once you made it here? You
made your decision, you got in, you're at Tech, what was life like here? Were
you on campus? Were you off campus?  You're an older student so what was your...?

WILLIAMS: Yeah. I was off. Can I pause just one second on that and back up just
one sec?

WRIGHT: Yeah.

WILLIAMS: It was my decision to come to Tech that drove my coming out because I
was like I'm not going to go away and do the double life thing.

WRIGHT: Okay, so you came out before, literally right before you got to Tech?

WILLIAMS: Yes, yes. Because I didn't want to come here be involved with all
these groups and all these fun things and then have to go home and be closeted
again. Another important thing, probably relevant, is that I have, well I have
three other gay family members, but at the time I only knew about two. My mom
has a gay sister who's a lesbian and she had, I have a cousin, her niece that's
lesbian. And both of them came out before me. So in the deep recesses of my mind
I already knew my mom would be okay with it. Which makes it that much more weird
and complicated that it was so hard to come out because I saw my mother accept
and love other gay family members, but I still couldn't come out.

WRIGHT: So when you say that they came out before you, this was years prior to
you coming out? So you saw your mother and your family go through that and you
saw that it was positive?

WILLIAMS: Yes.

WRIGHT: Yes, okay.

WILLIAMS: It wasn't without speed bumps, for sure. It wasn't as positive for
everyone. Like there were some family members who still don't associate with my
aunt Linda. [Whispers &quot;Ah stupidity&quot;] I remember when my mom's brother and his
wife, so my aunt through marriage, told my mom, shunned my mom, admonished her
because she went to visit Linda and her new partner, Carolyn, because she said
that by visiting in their home we were condoning that lifestyle. And these are
things that a fifteen year old gay closeted kid is hearing, you know &quot;condoning
their lifestyle&quot; and but then I saw mom say &quot;I don't care if I'm condoning, I
don't care what I'm condoning. I'm not going to not see my sister.&quot; So the
reactions I got from my mom were always sort of like coming from a place of
neutrality towards sexual orientation and emphasis on family. Like, I don't care
if she's gay or straight. She's my sister and I'm going to visit her. So it was
never super-affirming like, &quot;Linda's who she is and she's going to love who she
loves and screw you for thinking it less than.&quot; So I never saw that like
affirming side of my mom. Where she was really affirming our gay family members
but it was always more like a, &quot;I'm not gonna let that get in the way.&quot; So deep
down I knew my mom would be okay with it but at the same time it wasn't
something to be celebrated either.

So I kept having these false starts. Once I got accepted or was planning to go
to Tech I was like 'I gonna tell her, but I gotta find the right time. So I'm
going to tell her in the morning when she's fresh but it's gotta be after the
morning coffee, right?' [Wright coughing] You can get your cough out. And then
I'd like 'oh no, you know my brother was running late for school and now she's
stressed out 'cause he woke up late and it's like I'm not telling her now.' And
then I'd say 'okay I'm gonna tell her after dinner and oh no she's, her favorite
TV show comes on and she, this won't work. Okay, I'll tell her tomorrow before
dinner, oh no she's stressed out because dinner's taking too long to cook.' Like
I had...'I'm gonna tell her in the car, oh no like there's a lot of traffic
she's stressed out.' I had all these I'm gonna tell her and then not because of
something. So she took me out to a restaurant to celebrate me getting into
Virginia Tech, 'cause like I said I have three siblings, the two older
stepsisters and the younger brother, and the two older stepsisters were like,
she basically...do you, do either one of you...I'm sorry you aren't supposed to
be a part of the interview, do you have a lot of siblings?

WRIGHT: I have one older brother.

WILLIAMS: One older.

Damon Kinmond (Sound Technician): And I have one older brother.

WILLIAMS: Okay, so you might experience it a little bit but when you're one of
four one-on-one time with a parent is pretty rare. So my mom was like, &quot;It's
just you and me. We're going out to lunch to celebrate you getting into Virginia
Tech.&quot; We're there and she's like, &quot;I'm so proud of you.&quot; She's like, &quot;I feel
like you're the only child I did right by.&quot; Because Sheila at that time was
getting divorced with a guy that she'd met on the internet when she was eighteen
and it was like she was starting her life over because she had nothing. She
married someone who was still living with his parents. I mean at 26 he still
lived with his parents. And so she married a loser then got divorced and then
Jessica was like dropped out of college, moved back home, didn't have a job,
struggled with alcoholism. And then my little brother has Asperger's, so it was
a real struggle for him in high school. My mom was worried that he wasn't even
gonna graduate high school. 'Cause he's really smart, and I know I said we're
close now as adults, but as growing up he was difficult.

So anyway, I was like the straight A kid, the one getting Honor Roll, the one
who's doing all the right things, and so she sort of like showered me with these
compliments. You know like, &quot;You're the only child I feel like I did right by,&quot;
&quot;You're the only child who is like stress free my whole life and now you're
going to Virginia Tech, I'm so proud. You're just the only kid who turned out
normal.&quot; And I was like [high pitched noise] &quot;eeeeee...nooooo why did you have
to say that? Sorry, why did you have to say that?&quot; So I let her know that I
wasn't as normal as she thought that I was and so I referenced the porn that she
found five years earlier and I said, &quot;Remember when you found those history
files five years ago?&quot; And she didn't miss a beat. Guess what she said. She
said, &quot;What? But I thought you were just comparing sizes!&quot; Five years later
[snaps] like instant recall. I was like &quot;You believed that. You forced yourself
to believe that because you wanted to believe it because that's the most dumb
excuse.&quot; So she left. She went to the bathroom, and like I said, we were in a
restaurant and you know what happens when someone goes to the restroom, the food
always comes immediately and then you can't eat it 'cause you're waiting for
them and you don't want to be rude. Well, I'm waiting and waiting and waiting,
and the food's getting cold, and I'm like &quot;come on,&quot; and she finally comes back
after like fifteen minutes in the bathroom. Her mascara's like all running down
her face, her hair's disheveled, it's clear she's been bawling her eyes out in
the bathroom. And she sat down and she was like, &quot;John you're my son and there's
nothing you could ever do to make me love you any less.&quot; And then we ate. And
then I came to Virginia Tech. And I've never been in the closet since.

WRIGHT: Did you share that...that's a beautiful story...did you have that same
experience with your father? Or your siblings?

WILLIAMS: Whoa...my...so I didn't tell my stepdad because I told my mom she
could tell him. Like I said, I'm a momma's boy, so, and as you collect more oral
histories I'm sure you'll see this, some people have different approaches. Some
people tell their best friend first and then they tell a sibling, or they tell
other gay people, or they live like the secret gay life for a while and build
their confidence and they go to a support group. I made this decision to come
out to my mom without telling another soul. She was the first person in my life
that I actually said that to. 'Cause I'm like...I was all about starting from
the top. If she knew and still loved me and was okay with it, then everything
else was gonna be fine. I could care less what my other siblings thought because
they at least weren't gonna mistreat me 'cause mom wouldn't stand for it. I
didn't care what my dad said. You know for me it was like let's start with the
hardest conversation and everything else is gonna be like butter. So she told my
stepdad and my stepsisters. She wouldn't let me tell my brother because he
wasn't mature enough to handle it. So that was a battle that lasted for about a
year, where she wouldn't let me tell him because he wasn't mature enough, he
wasn't mature enough, and that whole year I was here at Tech getting involved. I
became an officer in the LGBT organization. I got arrested by going to an LGBT
protest. I was involved in a Freedom to Marry Day protest on the Drillfield. My
picture was on the front page of the newspaper for participating in a gay wedding.

WRIGHT: Let's get into all that too.

WILLIAMS: Oh okay and I'll go into more details but the whole point is that all
that's going on. I started dating somebody. My life is super gay and then I go
home and it's right back in the closet because even though mom, stepdad, and
both stepsisters know, baby brother doesn't know so I can't talk about it. So
finally she's just like, &quot;you just don't understand him like I do, he's not
mature enough to handle it, he's too little,&quot; plus the Asperger's. And I'm like
you know what, I finally sat her down and said, &quot;I realize he's your son and you
do know him and you understand him very well but I'm his brother. It's not like
he's your son and I'm your son and there's no relationship between us. I get him
too. I understand his quirks. I know what he can and can't handle. He's fifteen
years old. He probably has gay friends at school. He can handle it.&quot; She's like,
&quot;No, he's not ready.&quot;

Well I disregarded her commands and I told him. And he started laughing and
said, &quot;Is this a test? Are you testing me to see if I'll still accept you?&quot; And
I was like &quot;Uh...no.&quot; And he didn't believe me at first and so I finally told
him. I also told my dad too. Like I said my parents were divorced, so I told my
dad on New Year's Eve in 2005. Because in 2005 I came out to my mom in March of
'05 right after I got my acceptance letter to Tech. And so my whole first
semester at Tech, my dad didn't know. I was doing all the gay things and he
didn't know, because I didn't live with him and it was easier to hide it from
him and he doesn't have Facebook. He still doesn't have the internet. My dad
lives in like 1980.

So finally I, I set up these weird arbitrary rules for myself where I was like
2005 is my year of coming out. I'm not gonna let 2005 roll into 2006 without
being out to both parents. So on New Year's Eve my dad and I went out to
breakfast at Hardees. We got biscuits and he actually broached the subject,
inadvertently, 'cause he...whenever we were hanging out and we hadn't seen each
other for a while he would ask me about all my mom's siblings. My mom had seven
siblings and I think he missed them. He missed having that big family 'cause he
only had one sibling and his sister lives in California. So I think he missed
having that big family that came along with my mom as part of her package. Her
package [Laughter]. So he would always ask about all her siblings. Well he asked
about aunt Linda who at that time aunt Linda had only been out for probably
about five or six years. My aunt Linda was married to a husband, a man, for
thirty years and had kids by him. So he asked, &quot;Is Linda still a carpet
muncher?&quot; And I was like, &quot;Uh... that term's offensive dad.&quot; He was like, &quot;Oh,
what are you a spokesperson for lick sisters now?&quot; Like dropping another slur.
And I'm like, &quot;Oh my god dad that's really offensive you shouldn't say that.&quot; He
was like, &quot;you know I'm just playing I think Linda's great I just wanted to know
how she was doing.&quot; And so that got the conversation going. And I was like, &quot;You
should know Linda's not the only one in the family who's gay.&quot; [Laughter] And he
was like, &quot;What?&quot; And I was like, &quot;Well...I'm not straight either.&quot;

It was really hard to say that I'm gay. It was easier to say I'm not straight
than to say I'm gay, same thing with my mom. Now I don't have a problem saying
it but at the time I did. So I came out to him and he asked, just like my
brother, &quot;Is this some sort of test?&quot; I was like, &quot;No.&quot; &quot;A test to see if I'm a
good parent or not?&quot; I was like, &quot;Well I guess in some respects it is a test,
but it's not just a test.&quot; And he said so like, &quot;What do you call yourself now?
What do you preferred to be called?&quot; And because my dad and I have this kind of
relationship and we're jokesters I was like, &quot;Well I prefer the term
fudge-packer.&quot; Just to go along with his carpet muncher, lick sister thing
earlier. I was like I prefer the term... He was like, &quot;Oh, I see you've got
jokes. Well do you know this one? How do you get four gay guys on one barstool?&quot;
Do either one of y'all know?

KINMOND: No

WILLIAMS: You have an idea?

WRIGHT: I think I have an idea.

WILLIAMS: You turn it upside down. [Laughter] And so that was how I came out to
him. It ended with us telling each other whatever gay jokes we'd heard about.
Alright, so I'm sorry I went all over the place.

WRIGHT: No that was perfect. That was perfect. So you came out to your family,
you're at Tech now, and then you're getting involved in...Was it called Hokie
Pride at the time?

WILLIAMS: No it was LGBTA.

WRIGHT: No it was not it was LGBTA. So you're getting involved in that. Before
we get to that though I do want to ask you, you mentioned that Tech, their
Architecture program, what exactly was your major while you were here?

WILLIAMS: So I came in...so Architecture is what put Tech on the radar for me,
but I changed my mind before I actually transferred. I found Landscape
Architecture. So I transferred in as Landscape Architecture, and then I changed
out of that my first semester here because that's not a transfer friendly major.
It's a five year design program. So you have to have ten semesters of studio.
And so I was thinking I have my Associate's so that's gonna shave off two years
so I'll only be here for three years for this five year degree. And they're
like, &quot;Uh...actually you're still gonna be here for five years because you have
to take ten semesters of studio, the difference is you're gonna have ten
semesters of nine credits instead of a full course load. It's not a transfer
friendly major. What I'd recommend is that you transfer in to a more transfer
friendly major and then go to grad school for Landscape Architecture&quot; So that's
what I was gonna do. Excuse me, so I transferred into Urban Planning. And then
the goal was Urban Planning and then grad school Landscape Architecture and then
Virginia Tech screwed me over.

WRIGHT: In what way?

WILLIAMS: [Laughter] They didn't screw me over, they cancelled their Master's of
Landscape Architecture program at the Blacksburg campus. They moved it to the
Northern Virginia campus. There were two different levels. If you had a
Bachelor's in Landscape Architecture you could go in the fast track two year
program which they still offer in Blacksburg. But if you come from a non-design
field, like I was coming from Urban Planning, you had to do the three year
program which included extra studio. No longer offering that in Blacksburg, you
can only take that in Northern Virginia. Plus they weren't offering the first
year of design studio in the Northern Virginia campus. They had a great new
partnership with George Washington University where you would actually take a
year of classes at George Washington that would transfer automatically back to
Virginia Tech. Well, do either one of you know how much tuition is at George Washington?

WRIGHT: Mmhm.

WILLIAMS: It's about four times what it is at Virginia Tech. And I was like that
was my option. My whole plan, my whole plan when I transferred into Urban
Planning was, I'm transferring into this so I can go to grad school here, get my
master's, and live my life. So that totally threw everything out of whack –
for the better. I can go on on my career journey, or I can stop and we can talk
about other things.

WRIGHT: I want to get all that. It's your story.

WILLIAMS: Okay.

WRIGHT: How 'bout this – I do want to talk about your community involvement in
being an activist and the arrest and your protest. I do want to talk about that.
So I definitely want that on tape. Can you kind of share some of that information?

WILLIAMS: Sure. So I came to Tech and I hit the ground running. Am I close
enough to the mic? Okay. I remember I got here and I couldn't wait to get
involved. Since I lived off campus, since I was a transfer student, I moved here
like August 1. Right, as soon as my lease started in my apartment I was here in
Blacksburg, which was three weeks before school started. So I would go, almost
daily, into Squires and walk by the LGBT office to see if anyone was in there
because they said they would have sporadic office hours during the summer. That
students who were here over the summer would like staff the office and so I kept
going to see and no one was in there, no one was in there, no one was in there.
Finally, like the week before school started I went by there and someone was in
there. And I walked in and it was Toby and he was playing Super Mario Brothers
on the old, old Nintendo, and I walked in and he's like &quot;hey, give me just one
second!&quot; I mean, in his sassy gay voice. And I was like [whispers] &quot;oh my god
it's a real live gay person.&quot; You know it was a gay person that I sought out, it
wasn't like &quot;Barry the Fairy&quot; who I was avoiding, or gay people I'd seen on TV,
it was like a gay person who was...they're gonna become my friend. So I went in
and I sat down and it was really awkward because he kept playing. He literally
was like 'I'm finishing this level before I interact with you.' So he's playing
this Super Mario level and I'm just sitting on this couch surrounded by rainbows
and gay books and pictures of gay people and more rainbows and you know,
activists, feminists, queer buttons, and little signs everywhere and I was just
like marveling at all of that.

WRIGHT: Alright, so Squires is our community center, our gathering place on
Virginia Tech's campus, but where in Squires was the...?

WILLIAMS: Hidden away, tucked away in the back corner, the third floor, at the
end of the hallway on the third floor, where the other multicultural
organizations are. Some people joke that that's where Virginia Tech hid them. So
the Black Student Alliance, the Asian American Student Union, the Latino
American Student Association, and the LGBTA and HILEL, all their offices were in
the back corner of the third floor. Let's put all of the diverse kids together,
so that's where all this went down. So then I met Toby and we started talking
and he's like, &quot;Hey, you ought to come to this...&quot; it was the precursor to
Gobblerfest, what is now Gobblerfest, previously...were you here previously to
Gobblerfest, either one of you?

WRIGHT: No, this is my first semester here. Can you tell us what Gobblerfest is?

WILLIAMS: It's basically a student organizations fair on steroids, where they've
turned it into a carnival. But all the student organizations and all the
departments on campus come, they have a table set up and they showcase either
their office or their work. And now they have moon bounces and Ferris wheels and
all this fun stuff going on on the drill field, but it used to be inside. It
used to be in Squires Commonwealth Ballroom and it was much smaller and much
tamer and it was just called the Student Work Fair, it wasn't called
Gobblerfest. I think it's better now, but he recommended that I come to that.
He's like, &quot;We're gonna have a whole bunch of resources there, but actually
that's not why you should come 'cause all the resources we're gonna have their
you can get right off that table right here in this office. But you should come
so you can meet other people.&quot; Like I said he was the only one in the office
that day. So I went there and...

WRIGHT: What was his position, I'm sorry, Toby?

WILLIAMS: Yes Toby. He's just an officer. I don't remember if he was the Vice
President. You can look that information up I'm sure, but he was an officer in
the club at the time. So I went to the Student Work Fair which is where I met
Michael Sutphin, my roommate, for the first time. We didn't become friends that
day but it's where I first met him. And it happened to be the birthday of one of
the other officers in the club and so somehow I charmed someone into giving me
inside information and they told me that that officer was having a birthday
party that night. It was like a Friday, and so they gave me the address. And I
was like, &quot;Oh my god a gay party, a gay party, my very first gay party.&quot; I spent
like hours getting ready, make sure I have the perfect outfit, make sure my hair
was perfect, all this stuff.

So we went to this gay party and I mean it was...earth shattering. I just can't
explain. I don't know if either one of you identify as queer but it was one of
the highlights of my life. To walk into this party...and I mean I had been to
parties before, I went to some parties in high school, parties at community
college, it was actually my first Virginia Tech party so I guess I had never
been to a real college, college party, but to walk into a space where boys were
making out with boys and girls were making out with girls and like people were
sitting on the couch making out, people were dancing together, and you know
every gender bending thing. You know, guys wearing...there was this one dressed
up as a drag queen and the issue is like it wasn't weird. It wasn't out of the
ordinary. There was no like, &quot;Oh my look at that it's two guys making out over
there.&quot; It was more like &quot;Oh my god look at those straight people. Who invited
them?!&quot; It was an all gay space. That's the value of an all gay space, you know,
just like if you're in an all black space you know it's like...just imagine...I
mean I'm reading you as black. I assumed that you identify that way...I don't
know how you...I don't know but...

WRIGHT: Maybe for just today. [laughing] I'm joking.

WILLIAMS: Just imagine if you had gone through your whole life and you had never
been in a room with all black people...

WRIGHT: I can imagine...

WILLIAMS: ...and then all of a sudden it's like &quot;Oh my god...there's no white
people here. This is wonderful.&quot; You know [Laughter] and so that's like what it
was like. It was like I found my people. It was really...

WRIGHT: I can imagine, yeah.

WILLIAMS: It was really awesome to be in that kind of a space. So then I...I'm
the type of person to get involved really quickly. I went to every meeting. I
went to the Thursday night group fun meetings. I went to the Monday night
support group meetings and I went to all the activities and events they had. And
the organization at that time was getting involved with a group called Soul
Force. Ever heard of them? You can look them up if you want. They're kind of
defunct now 'cause times have changed from nine years ago. But it was a group of
basically Christian identified LGBT folks who would go around to Christian
organizations trying to educate them about LGBT issues. From the perspective of
– &quot;Hey I'm not some angry militant atheist Christian hatin' gay, I'm a
Christian and I'm gay and let me help educate you out of the Stone Age.&quot; So they
went to universities like Liberty, and the one in Virginia Beach...Regent, and
we would have protests where we would march on their campus protesting.

Because you can get kicked out of those schools for being gay. Like you can't
get, not that Virginia Tech's the most gay friendly place, but you can't get
kicked out for being gay here. You can get kicked out there. And then they
expanded that to any institution that had some sort of anti-LGBTQ policy, which
basically includes all the military academies. And Virginia Tech's lucky they
didn't get targeted because of the Corp of Cadets 'cause the Corp of Cadets has
to adhere to DOD standards, Department of Defense, which at the time had the
&quot;Don't Ask Don't Tell&quot; policy so theoretically you could get kicked out of the
Corps. You couldn't get kicked out of Virginia Tech but you could get kicked out
of the Corps based on the &quot;Don't Ask Don't Tell&quot; policy. So where, the time I
said I got arrested was at the Naval Academy. We took this bus trip up to the
U.S. Naval Academy.

WRIGHT: Which one?

WILLIAMS: In Annapolis. And we were prevented from entering. They barred...they
said...well they couldn't like lock the gate because it was the middle of the
day. People had to come and go. And so they wouldn't let us in. They had police
there, they didn't have riot gear. I don't think the fifty of us were that much
of a threat, but I mean we were lined up all the way outside of the gate. And
they said if we entered we would be arrested and we entered anyway. We entered
the campus.

WRIGHT: So all fifty of you entered the campus?

WILLIAMS: Not all fifty of us made it in because once they started to
realize...they arrested about twenty people and then they realized no one was
stopping. We didn't care. I mean it was like a civil rights event. It was like
peaceful resistance.

WRIGHT: What year was this, semester, give me a ballpark...?

WILLIAMS: It was spring of 2006, my second semester here. We walked in and it
was like a typical peaceful resistance type of arrest. They weren't handcuffed,
they did like the plastic wrist ties, you know hands behind our backs, and they
put 'em on every single person who walked through the gate and sat us down. Put
'em on, sit us down, put 'em on, sit us down, put 'em on, and you know we are
not resisting because that's the whole point. Until they realized that it wasn't
scaring anyone off, everyone just kept coming in and kept coming in. And so
finally they relented and they were like, &quot;Ok fine. We don't have the time or
the jail cells. We don't have time to deal with this or the capacity.&quot; So those
of us they'd arrested, they let us go and they let us onto campus but with very
strict rules. We weren't allowed to go into any residence halls or academic
buildings. We could only go into the student center or dining halls. We weren't
allowed to be disruptive. We weren't allowed to pester people or whatever. We
weren't allowed to march around and chant, hold up signs, it was like you can
come and you can go be peaceful and talk to people in public spaces and that's
it. And we were like okay, compromise. So I say I got arrested because a police
officer put handcuff like things on me but I didn't actually go sit in a jail
cell. But I still like to say I got arrested because I didn't care I was ready
to go to jail. Bring it on. [Laughs]

WRIGHT: So were there any activities on campus or any moments of protest on
campus? I mean what was your experience here? I know you said you found that
community here but did you ever encounter any adversity dealing with your
sexuality on campus?

WILLIAMS: Yeah, I mean plenty. There's lots of...whenever we would have
something on the Drillfield, either a Christian organization and sometimes the
College Republicans...God I just didn't understand, College Republicans nowadays
are still stupid, racist idiots, sorry should that be off the record? Like their
stupid alien invasion crap. Have y'all seen the ads for that? They're hosting an
event either tonight or tomorrow night and it's called &quot;Alien Invasion: Why
Illegal Immigration Will be the Undoing of America.&quot;

WRIGHT: Yes, I did hear about that. For the record can you just kind of explain
what that is, if you don't mind? Give us an idea about....the atmosphere.

WILLIAMS: So it's 2014 and the College Republicans and a couple of other groups
are endorsing this keynote speaker who's coming to talk about immigration
issues. And immigration is a fine topic of conversation, but it's called &quot;Alien
Invasion.&quot; That's an othering term and it's very offensive and it's clearly
racist. And it's targeted at Latino and Hispanic folks because this country is
built on immigration and you don't hear about anyone talking about people
emigrating from Europe or Canada. It's like &quot;No, we've got to block that scary
Mexican border.&quot; So it's a really racist, horrible event that's being
proudly...I can't believe that people put that on a flyer, you know, and are
advertising how illegal immigration, and that's also very othering – to use
the term illegal to refer to another human being as being illegal – so it's
basically an anti-immigration keynote speaker.

WRIGHT: Thank you for sharing that.

WILLIAMS: I went off on a little rant.

WRIGHT: No it gives an idea of the culture and the atmosphere that's on Tech at
the present day because you are working, you do work for Tech currently?

WILLIAMS: Yeah.

WRIGHT: That's very important. But to get back to your experience, can you
share, do you feel comfortable sharing any, the few occasions or the many
occasions where you felt alienated?

WILLIAMS: Yeah, so the LGBTA office door was vandalized while I was student
here. People basically ripped pages out of a Bible, like the Bible verses –
they call them the Clobber Passages – there's like eight verses in the Bible
that deal with same sex sexual activity. I don't even call it homosexuality or
gay sex because those identities didn't even exist in Biblical times. It's
purely like same sex interactions. They ripped the Bible pages out that had
those verses in them and glued them to our door and highlighted or circled the
passages, and they took a sharpie and wrote on the door &quot;God hates fags&quot; &quot;Fags
burn in hell&quot; &quot;You're going to hell&quot; and all that stuff. So I mean that was real
vandalism that had to be scrubbed off the door and the Bible pages were glued so
people had to scrape the glue off and stuff. The university didn't respond to it.

WRIGHT: In what way? What are you...one how do you feel about that and what
would like for the university to respond to and then what did they actually do?

WILLIAMS: Okay, so the funny thing is, I was such a rabble-rouser, I was never
fearful because of that I was never like, &quot;Oh my God it's so scary and
homophobic and oppressive.&quot; I was more like, &quot;Fuck these people.&quot; I was like,
&quot;Hell yeah, bring it on! I'm ready. Bring us the fight.&quot; So we went to the
administration and were like, &quot;Look at this rampant homophobia.&quot; I won't say we
played it up, because I mean it was true. Can you imagine that happening to a
Christian organization on campus? Where, I don't know someone ripped out pages
of a Wiccan book and glued it to their door and were like, &quot;Christians don't
understand there's more than one God...&quot; I don't know what the equivalent would
be. So we went to the administration and their response was &quot;Sorry we don't have
any cameras in that portion of the building, so unless you can produce for us a
suspect there's nothing we can do&quot; And we're like, &quot;what?&quot;

A year prior to that, the Black Student Alliance door, which is right next ours,
was vandalized in an even more grotesque way, in my opinion. Similar things like
sharpies writing the &quot;N&quot; word on the door and things like that, but the people,
they had smeared fecal matter on the door. And the university initially tried to
give them the same bullshit like, &quot;Sorry, this is horrible but...&quot; whatever, but
there was no public statement, which is kind of the most important thing. And
then, because of the way hate crime laws are written to include race but they
don't include sexual-- now they do include sexual orientation, there was someone
from the FBI's Hate Crimes Unit came to campus to um...someone from the NAACP
Roanoke Regional Office came down, and there was a big investigation and all
this stuff with the university was trying to save face. You know like, &quot;Virginia
Tech's not racist and that's bad.&quot; After other outside parties got involved they
reacted. Well we didn't have any of that to go on, and so what we started was a
campaign. And I normally wear a bracelet but it broke two weeks ago. I've had
this same bracelet for nine years and we termed it the &quot;Give A Damn&quot; campaign.
Because we wanted – it's really problematic that we framed it in this way
'cause I never want to pit one oppressed group against another oppressed group,
but everyone was kind of like this just happened right next door to us last year
and Virginia Tech you reacted this way. And now it's happened again and you're
doing the same thing where you're reaction is not reacting only this time we
don't have the backing of the FBI's Hate Crimes Unit or a group like the NAACP
to come in and...

WRIGHT: And make you do something.

WILLIAMS: Yeah. So we started this &quot;Give a Damn&quot; campaign where we had students
from all over campus submit anonymously if they wanted or they could submit it
with their names, stories of incidents of bias against them. And we delivered
them all to the administration being like, look at all these different things
that your current students have happen to them...

WRIGHT: I have a question. Now was it...did the stories that they're sharing,
and I think that's a wonderful idea, the stories they were sharing was it
dealing with like student to student interaction or was it professor to student
interaction or was it...?

WILLIAMS: All the above.

WRIGHT: All of the above.

WILLIAMS: And it didn't even have to be and interaction. It could be just
something that they witnessed, like if you saw hate speech scrawled in a
bathroom stall, you could report that. If you overheard a conversation between
two other people that you weren't involved with, you could report that. And so
we delivered all that to the administration and at the time the Vice President
for Student Affairs was Zenobia Hikes, and she was not only Virginia Tech's
first female Vice President for Student Affairs in that role, she was the first
black Vice President, so she got like the double minority card going on and it
was awesome. And she started here right when I did, so that might have, my whole
experience as a student at Virginia Tech was sort of framed by having this
really powerful, respectful – she was respectful and respectable woman of
color in such a high leadership position at the university and she really cared
about the LGBT students because her daughter was lesbian.

And so she would come to our meetings, she would check in with us. Once I became
an officer...I'm getting a little bit ahead of myself...but she would always
check in with me like, &quot;John Gray how are things on campus? What do you feel?
Have things improved?&quot; She would check in with any LGBT students about the
climate. So she was a rock star. She passed away in 2008. But we took all these
reports to her of homophobia and incidents of bias on campus and we're like,
&quot;This is happening. What happened on our door is just the most recent, but this
kind of stuff happens all over campus all the time and y'all aren't doing
anything about it and we want you to give a damn.&quot; So we had these bracelets
made that said &quot;Give a Damn&quot; on them, which is kind of a little bit taboo. And
we presented that to her and remarkably, at a university with this much
bureaucracy, she instigated or instituted what we call the Safewatch Program,
which no longer exists. It's since been dismantled. But in the span of one
semester she took a legitimate complaint issue and created a program to deal
with it.

WRIGHT: So in 2006 to get a timeframe, in that semester...

WILLIAMS: '05

WRIGHT: '05

WILLIAMS: Fall of '05.

WRIGHT: My goodness, fall of '05. So you started off going, okay. That's awesome
too. So in '05 how did you know or how were you able to identify her as an
advocate, someone who would support you and not try to dismiss you or try to get
you to leave the university, because typically that's the response – maybe
this isn't the best school for you – so how did you find, what...? How did she
position herself to make sure she was someone who who'd advocate for you on your behalf?

WILLIAMS: I was relying on the expertise of other students. At that time I
wasn't an officer yet, so I was relying on the expertise of others. Like
Michael, he was actually the president of the organization, my roommate, when
I...at this time. 'Cause like I said, I transferred in but he came in as a
freshman. The leadership of the other student leaders who had been around for a
lot longer really spearheaded this &quot;Give a Damn&quot; campaign. I was just there to
help rally the troops. So I think they had insider information that she was a
supporter and she just to me always seemed really approachable and really
friendly. I didn't know that she had a lesbian daughter until much later.

WRIGHT: What do you think...and this is with any marginalized group...what do
you think, or how did you feel, what prompted you, where did you find that
strength to fight? To say that this is not acceptable and we're going to do
something about it, because it is sometimes easier to be quiet. Well maybe not
easier because emotionally you go through your...it's tough emotionally to be
quiet, but as far as maintaining harmony, it's easier to be quiet. So where did
you find that inner strength to say that you know we're gonna do something about
it, I'm gonna be a part of it?

WILLIAMS: It's a hard question to answer because I really don't feel that it
required inner strength. Not to be altruistic and humble brag or anything like,
&quot;Oh I felt like it was just the thing to do.&quot; But, I mean I'm really extroverted
so for me it was like something to do. And I think also it was the pendulum had
swung back. I use this analogy a lot, I also at the time had a lot more rainbow
– had gay shirts, had rainbow bracelets, although I'm still wearing a rainbow
bracelet right now, but I had so much pent up repression from not being able to
tell anyone or act or do anything for so long, that I got here, had that
transformative experience of being at an all gay space at that party, that the
pendulum swung and now it was like 'I'm here, I'm queer, come for me.' And I
also, I liked the thrill. I liked the edginess of it. You know, I like the fact
that I could've got arrested. I liked the fact, I liked arguing with people. For
me it was fun it gave...it was like it was fun because it was important, but it
also, we needed people like me who are outgoing and willing to fight the fight
because there are a lot of people who are still closeted and can't fight the fight.

WRIGHT: So how did these events...I know you mentioned the gay marriage, was
that on campus?

WILLIAMS: Yeah, the Freedom to Marry Day.

WRIGHT: The Freedom to Marry Day. So let's talk about that a little bit and then
we'll get into Hokie Pride.

WILLIAMS: Okay. So Freedom to Marry Day happens in February every year and so
the LGBTA organized mock marriages, although we were conditioned not to call
them mock marriages because that implies you're making a mockery of marriage.
Although now my views on marriage have changed somewhat because I think it's
patriarchical and oppressive in a lot of ways. And sometimes it bothers me. I'm
worried that because now we have same sex marriages in so many states that
everyone's gonna be like, &quot;Ok, fight for your rights is over. Gay people are
equal. Everything is great.&quot; It's like, no gay people still kill themselves at a
rate of 3 to 1. They're still victims of way more hate crimes. They get bullied.
Anyway, getting off subject.

WRIGHT: We will get to that.

WILLIAMS: Freedom to Marry Day...I wanted to participate in the protest, so I
participated as one of the two gay, there were two gay male couples, like two
guys and two guys, and there was a lesbian couple, then there was a bisexual
couple, which the bisexual couple just looked like a straight couple 'cause, I
mean, that's just what it looks like. We actually shared a kiss. We read our
vows, our vows at the wedding were like our statement of affirmation of our
fight for civil rights. So we all were asked to write a little speech about what
we were gonna do to fight for equality. Then we kissed each other, but not like
a wedding kiss but just like a peck on the cheek. Well the CT was there. They
took a picture of me and Brennan[?] Bell, that was his name, kissing and it made
it in the front page of the CT. So, oh I should go get that for you I think it's
up stairs in my closet...sometime.

WRIGHT: When we wrap up we would like to take it with us and actually we can get
a copy and they'll call and release, so thank you for offering that.

WILLIAMS: I mailed that home to my mother, by the way. A copy of that, the front
page of the CT I sent that home with her, to her. Because I was like, &quot;Look at
me mom I made front page news! And there I am kissing a boy.&quot;

WRIGHT: Well how did that...what year was that, that you participated in that,
just for the record?

WILLIAMS: Spring of '06.

WRIGHT: Spring of '06.

WILLIAMS: Oh, that's what got me on the College Republicans. They were there
protesting that, which got me on the whole rant about the alien invasion thing.

WRIGHT: Alright, Hokie Pride.

WILLIAMS: Like the current group?

WRIGHT: Your involvement...well let's clarify that...When did it become Hokie
Pride? And when did you become I guess when did you become more involved in it,
you know the transition from the group you were a part of to what it is today?
So if you could just kind of walk us through it.

WILLIAMS: Yeah, it became Hokie Pride this semester. It just became Hokie Pride.
And the transition was a name change, that's all. So the transition of the group
was quite unremarkable. But I mean, I was in it as a student and now I'm a
faculty member here, so my interaction with it is somewhat, it's still a social
group for me because I just sort of aged out of it. It wasn't like I was gone
for 20 years and came back. So, you know, when I graduated I still had friends
in the organization and then by virtue of them I became friends with the younger
people in the organization and I just kept going. So people who were like
freshmen when I was a senior were like seniors when I came back from grad
school. So it's like now no one in the organization was in the organization when
I was a student, but those people, the people who were seniors, the freshman
when I was a senior that were seniors when I came back, introduced me to younger
people  so now those people are the seniors, you know what I mean? It's
like...so I have a friendly relationship with a lot of the gay undergrads here
because they're friends with people I'm friends with.

WRIGHT: Now there is an interesting transition in your life because you did
leave and then come back, but before we get into that aspect was there anything
that happened on campus that you'd like to share, that you'd want us, that would
be beneficial for us to know?

WILLIAMS: So well the &quot;Freedom to Marry Day&quot; thing happened every year. The
College Republicans were out there protesting us, a variety of Christian
organizations were out there protesting us with signs where they had like Bible
verses spray painted on signs. There was a...I remember one time we made fun of
them because there was a misquote, like they misspelled a word, and then there
was another one where they had a quote but then the Bible verse they had cited
was the wrong one. It was like you know &quot;from Ezekiel 13-1&quot; and that wasn't
actually the Bible verse that they had written. We made fun of them for that
kind of stuff. So the big noteworthy things were like the &quot;Give a Damn&quot; campaign
like with the vandalism, which turned into SafeWatch program, the &quot;Freedom to
Marry Day,&quot; the protests at other universities, um let's see...I guess for me I
became an officer and I became in charge of Gay Awareness Week, which is now
Pride Week. And so I brought...I was in charge of an entire weeklong series of
events where I brought a couple gay speakers to campus, and we actually had
another protest. It was called the Gay? Fine by Me Rally where we had a generous
donator...donor who donated a bunch of shirts that say &quot;Gay.&quot; Have you ever seen
the gay fine by me?

WRIGHT: I have not.

WILLIAMS: It says &quot;Gay? Fine By Me.&quot; We had someone donate like 100 of those shirts.

WRIGHT: What year was that and do you remember who the donor was?

WILLIAMS: The donor was actually a recent grad.

WRIGHT: Okay, can I ask the name?

WILLIAMS: Yeah, Crysta Highfield. You might want to interview her too. She
identifies as a member of the community. She lives in San Francisco now,
but...or Berkeley technically, but if you ever wanted to do a phone interview
with her. So she donated these shirts and so we had tons and tons of people come
out for like a big photo op and had a big protest. Well it wasn't a protest
because it was just a rally. It was all positive. It wasn't in reaction to anything.

WRIGHT: So it was more of like awareness.

WILLIAMS: Yeah, it was called &quot;Gay Awareness Week.&quot; So probably about 40 of us,
maybe 50, posed on the steps in front of the bookstore, between the library and
the bookstore, with a bunch of rainbow flags and stuff and we're all wearing
these shirts. And all the shirts were different colors so it was like a rainbow.
And you know that made it into the CT and I remember taking out a full page Gay
Awareness Week ad in the CT 'cause I had under spent my budget and it was like
you either spend the money or it goes away. So I took out a full like two color
ad in the CT that talked about Gay Awareness and I had like statistics and
stuff. I have that somewhere too. I don't know where exactly that is. I'm not
sure I know where the other one is, I might have to get those to you later. But
I had stats out there like, &quot;Pause and take a moment, look around the room,
count ten people,&quot; in my mind I was envisioning someone seeling this like
looking around the room and counting okay, &quot;statistically speaking one of them
is gay.&quot; You know, &quot;1 in 10 people are gay. So there's people that you know that
might be gay that you don't even know.&quot; And then I put some statistics about
hate crimes and about suicides.

WRIGHT: So I want to get back to some of your story and I know so...

WILLIAMS: Oh, what time is it?

KINMOND: It is 6:55.

WILLIAMS: Okay.

WRIGHT: Alright, so at some point you leave and was it going off to grad school
or were you working?

WILLIAMS: So I left Virginia Tech campus as a student but I got a job in Urban
Planning. Because remember I said they threw my whole grad school plan went out
the window?

WRIGHT: Yeah.

WILLIAMS: So I was like 'well I might as well just get a job with my bachelor's
degree while I figure out what I want to do.' You know, start paying off my
student loan debt. So I started applying for jobs in Urban Planning and I
actually landed one here in Blacksburg. So that's how my story gets a little
bit, I mean my life is my life, it's not that murky but in terms of I stayed in
Blacksburg but no longer as a student but I was still intricately involved on
campus. So while I couldn't officially be a member of the organization anymore
because I wasn't a student, I still attended all the meetings. And I actually
was the team captain of the first ever LGBTA Relay for Life team. I have a thing
with t-shirts. I designed these like rainbow t-shirts and we had a Relay for
Life team. And part of that was because I obviously value the fight against
cancer and I like Relay for Life but also because of visibility. To like be like
'hey look, here's gay people doing a good thing and contributing to a good
cause. You know, we're not just all here having sex and having gay parties and
what all the stereotypes people associate with us.' So I actually did that as a
community member because I was technically not a student anymore.

So that was for two years that I was involved, but not as a student. Then I quit
that job because I was sick of it, I hated it. And in the back of my mind all my
social justice work, so in addition, I should say all my LGBTA activism led me,
opened my eyes to the whole notion of privilege and oppression, and social
justice, and learning about what other underrepresented groups experience. You
know it was very easy for me to draw parallels between the LGBT community and
people of color, or religious minorities and all that. And so I was like I want
to do this forever. You know I went to social justice conferences and trainings
and all this stuff and so I was like why am I doing this job I hate and I'd had
this seed planted in my mind about possibly going into Student Affairs from my
mentor, who was the advisor to the LGBTA while I was a student here. She just
kind of sat down and said &quot;John Gray...somebody has to make this happen. You
know I have a job right and I get paid?&quot; and I was like, &quot;Of course,&quot; &quot;well have
you ever thought out how I got here?&quot; I was like, &quot;No I never did&quot; because you
ask the average student, if you ask them &quot;Who works at the University?&quot; Their
number one answer they're gonna say professors. They don't think about how many
other people make this place run.

And so she opened my eyes to the profession of Student Affairs and that was
before I even graduated. So this whole time I'm in this job here in town, the
urban planning job, that I wasn't liking, I'm like Student Affairs, you should
go to grad school. And I'd already thought I was going to grad school for
Landscape Architecture so in my mind I was already prepared to take the GRE and
like I was already grad school mindset but it just shifted from landscape to
Student Affairs. And I decided to leave Blacksburg because Virginia Tech has a
Student Affairs graduate school program but I wanted to get a different college
campus experience, especially for that. 'Cause if you're gonna go to school to
learn how to work with college students, you should experience a different
college campus.

So I was in a relationship at the time, my first and only serious relationship
of my life, that lasted for about two years, we were in that relationship at the
time so I decided my grad school choices were...had to be within driving
distance. So I drew about a six hour radius around Blacksburg and so the
furthest Southern school I applied to was Georgia, and so I went like University
of Georgia, University of Tennessee, Ohio State, Penn State, on down around to
University of Delaware and then some things in between. And I ended up going to
the University of Delaware. But what really drove that was I want to do social
justice work on a college campus. So everywhere I was applying, I was applying
for assistantships in Multicultural Offices, Diversity Inclusion Offices,
whatever, LGBT Centers. I wanted to do that work. The fact that I ended up being
a Career Counselor, have I even said that's what I do now?

WRIGHT: We haven't gotten there yet.

WILLIAMS: Okay, that wasn't on my radar at all. I was like I want to do social
justice work and I want to do it on a college campus and that's what ultimately
led me to this profession.

WRIGHT: Well, that's awesome and that gets us to here – your current
experience here working at Tech. And I also want to ask you about the diversity
on Tech's campus as well as student population, faculty population,
administrators, and things and how does that...how did that effect...or how does
that effect the gay and queer population here, or do you see a correlation
between the diversity or even maybe lack of and if that kind of effects the
atmosphere in a way here?

WILLIAMS: So are you basically asking in general is the fact that Virginia Tech
is not a very diverse place does that have any effect or like are you looking
for specifically does it have a negative effect or...?

WRIGHT: Well how do you take it? 'Cause it...I'm hesitant to say Tech isn't diverse...

WILLIAMS: Right, I'll say it. You want me to say it? Tech's not diverse.

WRIGHT: [Laughter] Ok so Tech's isn't diverse. And so how do you believe, or do
you believe that it kind of has or does it have an effect on marginalized or
minority groups?

WILLIAMS: I know that word seems so out of fashion nowadays. Okay, so I'll get
to that in just a second. So I ended up, I couldn't get an assistantship in any
diversity or multicultural office but I got one in Career Services at the
University of Delaware. So that's why I ended up in this field because I had two
years of  assistantship in the Career Center there, which made me fully equipped
to be a career counselor. That's what I'm doing here.

WRIGHT: Which department?

WILLIAMS: In Career Services, which is located at the corner of Washington and
West Campus across the street from McComas. But see, the wonderful thing about
Student Affairs is because Student Affairs is pretty open-minded, liberal,
Student Affairs is like the liberal bubble within the university. In the same
way that the University itself, as conservative as it is, is still liberal
compared to...the Town of Blacksburg is more liberal than you know, Giles
County. And when I say liberal I don't mean necessarily politically, even though
that is...I just mean more diverse, more inclusive, more open-minded than some
of the surrounding areas.

WRIGHT: But it could be worse.

WILLIAMS: Right it could be worse. I mean it's not like it's DC or Berkeley,
sorry, but it's also not you know, West Virginia. And so I was applying for jobs
all over the country and then an opening came up here and I just threw my hat in
the ring. I didn't really want to come back to Blacksburg. I had ended my
relationship by the way. Long distance killed that, which is kind of bittersweet
in some respects because if I'd known I was gonna be coming back to
Blacksburg...like I was thinking I'm done with Blacksburg, I'm going to Delaware
for two years for grad school, and then I'm gonna go to California, to Colorado,
to New York, whatever. And he was still here and he was a senior and he had to
go to grad school here for two more years and then it was just like...it was
like this isn't...who knows where we're going.

WRIGHT: Do you mind sharing that? I mean two years is a long time of your life,
do you mind sharing any aspects of that relationship and...if you want to share
his name that's fine as well?

WILLIAMS: Oh yeah I will share his name. You should interview him too. His
name's Scott Burton and we actually met, so this is kind of funny, I didn't
think about that, we met at that Relay for life event that I organized. His
father passed away from cancer and so he walks in Relay for Life for his dad and
he was there at that event that I organized. So I wasn't even a student and he
was a student at the time and we met there and kind of just became friends. And
we didn't do anything that year and then the whole summer we were kind of just
flirting a little bit on Facebook and then that fall semester started and I
found out he lived in the apartment building right next to one of my best
friends and we ran into each other, like accidentally. And it was kind of like,
&quot;Oh hey, you live here?&quot; and it was like, fast-forward, we hang out more, we
hang out more, and now we're dating. So that was my most serious relationship.
That lasted for...we dated for a year here in Blacksburg, and then we dated for
another year long distance. But yeah, that was my first ever real relationship.
I had dated someone for about a month before and it was significant at the time
for me because it was my first relationship...relationship – we dated for a
month and he was crazy. [Laughter] Sorry is that a trigger word for you?

WRIGHT: No...it's just...I know what that can potentially mean, so it's like...

WILLIAMS: Well 'cause I was 22, he was 19. Anyway, I was...that at the time I
counted it but now I don't really count it.

WRIGHT: Okay.

WILLIAMS: But Scott, that lasted for two years and you know, he came to visit me
in Delaware three times. We basically saw each other every month. Every other
month one of us would make the trip. So I actually came to Blacksburg a lot even
though I wasn't living here, which added to the weird lack of...there was no
real break 'cause I was here every other month. And then I moved back here and
it was almost like I never left. Some people were like, &quot;Where have you been? We
haven't seen you around as much.&quot; I was like, &quot;I moved.&quot; &quot;You moved away? But I
still saw you all the time.&quot; I'm like, &quot;Yeah I was here every other month,&quot; or
more frequently than that if there was some sort of special event. Anyway, our
lives were going in different places because I was potentially doing a national
job search, he knew he was gonna be in Blacksburg for at least 3 more years,
plus he had a special grant that was going to require him to stay in Virginia to
teach because he's a public high school teacher in Roanoke, right...currently.
Because of the grant he had that paid for his grad school he had to commit to
teaching in the state of Virginia in exchange for that grant.

WRIGHT: Now is he openly gay?

WILLIAMS: Mmhm. Yeah that's kind of a deal breaker for me. I can't get, I
can't...that's why the first relationship failed. I can't do the closet. It's
too hard for me to do because I'm such an open and genuine person–that sounded
arrogant, &quot;I'm so genuine&quot;–but I can't fake it. I can't like, because it was
too much demands with the other one, he was like, &quot;Okay, this group of friends
knows that I'm gay, this group of friends thinks I'm bisexual, and these people
don't know. And my brother knows but my sister doesn't know and my parents don't
know. So if my brother's around its okay but if my sister...&quot; And it was just
like &quot;Dude, I'm just, I'm out, I'm done with..eeww.&quot; which goes to show I should
be sympathizing with him. That's the oppression that LGBT people experience.
It's not all about just like hate crimes. Sometimes it's just like having
to...having such a complicated, socially nuanced life of what spaces are you out
and what spaces are you closeted? So I don't like to play that game anymore. So
I can only get in a relationship with somebody who's out totally.

So long distance didn't work and then lo and behold, we break up and then lo and
behold I graduate and move back here and I was like &quot;Oh my...&quot; So I moved back
here while he was still here in grad school so it was like &quot;Heeeeey, you want to
try to date again?&quot; No I'm kidding,  there were other reasons we broke up, it
wasn't just long distance. So I came back here and now the great thing about
Student Affairs is that it's really open-minded and really inclusive. And so I
get away with a lot. They let me do lots of diversity and social justice stuff
at my office.

WRIGHT: Like what?

WILLIAMS: So I'm the liaison to Multicultural Programs and Services from our
department so I'm the face of Career Services for MPS.

WRIGHT: What is MPS just so we know?

WILLIAMS: Multicultural Programs and Services.

WRIGHT: Okay, MPS...M?

WILLIAMS: Oh yeah...MPS. So it's my job to do outreach to the different student
groups that fall under that, which Hokie Pride is one of them, Black
Organizations Council, Black Student Alliance, Asian American Student Union, you
can find all that online. So I do special outreach to them to make sure that
they're aware of what Career Services offers and also to do some specialized
tailored programming to them.

WRIGHT: So what do you mean when you say outreach and the programs offered, what
does outreach look like or consist of and what are the programs that you offer
to these groups?

WILLIAMS: Okay, so part of it just getting our name out there. Letting them know
that Career Services exists, because a lot of people don't know we exist,
because we're not like a fun department. We're not like, people know about
Student Activities, people know about Rec Sports, you know, 'cause those are the
fun things. People know about Dining Services because they eat. But Career
Services a lot of people don't think about until someone points it out to them,
or they Google &quot;I need help with my resume&quot; and we pop up. So just letting them
know we exist. We can help you with your job search. We can help you choose a
major. We can help you explore careers. We can help you with interviewing
skills. So kind of like making them aware of our services but also, I work to
present presentations–that was redundant–to present to them on either what I
call the bread and butter topics, which are like how to write a resume, how to
interview, how to search for a job, like doing outreach, bringing a workshop to them.

And what I'm currently developing, which hasn't--it's been so busy that it's
been hard to do--I wanted to develop some really specialized tailored things
basically about issues that underrepresented groups face in employment. Like
with the LGBT community, like you can legally be fired for being gay. So how do
you talk about your LGBT involvement on a resume, you know, if you're not trying
to be out? Or if it comes up in an interview where someone asks about your
spouse how do you--technically those questions are illegal but, how do you
navigate that? And then of course with the student groups for students of color,
like you know, it's illegal to discriminate based on race, only you know it
still happens. So how do you navigate that on a job search? Dealing with
sensitive issues about like how are you going to present your name on your
resume? Like it's really kind of tragic that some students feel pressure to
change their name on their resume if they have an ethnic sounding name.

WRIGHT: Ethnic, yeah bunny ears ethnic, quotations.

WILLIAMS: Like Jose changing his name to Joe, or whatever. Or, you know, I knew
someone who was named Alicia but it was spelled A-L-I-S-H-A, considering
spelling it A-L-I-C-I-A. You know, because it's like the white way to spell it.
So just addressing some of those really nuanced issues or ways that you can
research to see if a company's inclusive. You know, how to weed through a
diversity policy, like does it have any teeth or is it just a front? You know,
look at the diversity of the administration at the organization. Is it a bunch
of old white guys or do they actually have diversity? Those things are still in
development 'cause they have to be done right. And I've only been the liaison
there for one year so I'm still getting that stuff off the ground, but I also,
my office, I came out in my job interview, accidentally almost, well they asked
me because they knew I was a student here–so I wasn't an internal candidate
but I was kind of internal-esque, and they basically said, &quot;As a former student
here, you have more insight into Virginia Tech than the other candidates we're
interviewing for the position, in what ways do you think Virginia Tech can
improve? What areas do you see Virginia Tech need to improve?&quot; And so of course
my answer was diversity, right. And I talked about all my LGBT involvement and
in that I was like, &quot;So I'm gay, so I was really involved in the LGBT group when
I was a student&quot; blah blah blah. And then afterwards I was like, &quot;Oh my god I
just said that, why did I talk about that?&quot; [whispered] And it was actually at
the big group presentation where I had presented on a topic to the entire staff.

WRIGHT: What did you present?

WILLIAMS: What did I present?

WRIGHT: Yes.

WILLIAMS: I had to talk about how the five aspirations for student learning.
Have you heard of them?

WRIGHT: No.

WILLIAMS: In the Division of Student Affairs we have these five aspirations for
student learning. Basically they're tenets that we want every Virginia Tech
graduate to leave with these five things. Things that you learn outside the
classroom: curiosity, integrity, civility, courageous leadership, and a
commitment to &quot;UT Proism&quot; you know, the motto. And so the prompt was &quot;how do you
see career development work fitting into that model of those five things?&quot; We
had to talk about how it fit into that. But then afterwards it was like Q&amp;A. You
know, like ask me random questions, well the point was you're supposed to ask
questions about my presentation but it was a free-for-all. People could ask me
anything they wanted. So they asked me the question about ways I think Virginia
Tech needs to improve and I answered with that.

Just this past Friday, for the third year in a row, I've organized an LGBTQ
networking reception, where I bring in alumni, LGBT alumni, LGBT professionals
from the community, LGBT faculty and staff, with LGBT students to meet at the
Career Center and have a big LGBT networking reception, where we talk about
things like being out in the workplace, or coming out on the job, and all those
topics related to employment and LGBT, where students can ask real, live
professionals, people who are LGBT identified who are in the workplace, what it
was like for them, or what it currently is like for them. And so my office
sponsors that. So I get to run these gay programs. I'm the liaison to MPS. I am
a SafeZone trainer on campus, so LGBT Safe Zones I help facilitate and get other
faculty and staff members trained up to be a SafeZone. I sit on the diversity
committee. So I get to, even though I'm not working in the multicultural or
diversity inclusion realm, I get to do a lot of those things anyway because my
office is really supportive of it.

WRIGHT: Well I'm not gonna say last question because I'll probably ask a follow
up but why did you choose to participate in this project?

WILLIAMS: 'Cause I think my story is worth hearing.

WRIGHT: And it is.

WILLIAMS: Because, I'll tell you why, because I know that, I think, oh I love
talking, I think I was at Virginia Tech at this really awesome critical juncture
where when I came to college in 2005, gay marriage, and this, gay marriage
should not be the litmus test for gay equality, but you could get married in one
state when I came to college, and that was Massachusetts. And now you can get
married in 30 states. And so the current college students and people moving
through Virginia Tech now and onward, millennials, you know like they've had
access to the internet and they've seen the gay rights movement and they've seen
the fight for equality since they were in middle school. And so now it's like
run of the mill, like there's lots of people fighting the good fight for gay
rights and it's very visible now. And you're also gonna interview people from
the before times, you know, people who were here in the 60s and 70s and 80s and
90s when they viewed it as being way more oppressive and way more homophobic and
really negative. And I think that I...I think my story is gonna be somewhat
unique, I guess you'll be the judge of that, in the sense that I experienced a
lot of negative things but I'm a really positive, optimistic, upbeat person and
I just want to make sure you don't get a lot of &quot;Oh my god it was so hard and it
was so horrible,&quot; because those are valid stories, everybody's story is valid,
but just know that I enjoyed my time here a lot.

WRIGHT: That's gonna be my, probably, final question for you, well second to
last question for you. Can you share some of the positive experiences of being a
Hokie, and even at your current position, and you're still a Hokie?

WILLIAMS: Yeah, I mean, yeah it's also weird finding a new identity for myself
here. So, I love Blacksburg. I love the small town feel that it has. I love how
it's generally a pretty warm and friendly place. But I have passing privilege in
the sense that I'm gay but not everyone knows I'm gay. I'm not like 'Barry the
Fairy,' I'm not particularly effeminate. I do talk with my hands a lot, but I
have passing privilege in the sense that I don't ever feel unsafe walking down
the street. I'm a big guy so people aren't gonna mess with me and I don't look
gay–whatever that is. So I don't ever really feel unsafe here. I'm not
answering your question am I? I love the sense of community. I love the school
spirit. I love the colors. I love the fact that for me Virginia Tech is where I
became, Virginia Tech's where I learned how to be who I am. Because everything
up until Virginia Tech was the closeted John Gray, and everything after Virginia
Tech was John Gray the gay person, John Gray the activist and the social justice
fighter, John Gray the professional. Like everyone blossoms in college, but I
mean I really blossomed in college. And you know, it's big enough that there are
pockets of people, everyone can find their people here 'cause it's big enough.
So even though it's not the most inclusive place, it's so big that like there
are gay people.

WRIGHT: And then this will be my final question: was there anything that we
didn't discuss that you would like to share?

WILLIAMS: Hmmm [Whispers] I don't know, possibly. [Laughs] Um...hmm...yeah I
don't know.

WRIGHT: Well, if you have more time.

WILLIAMS: What time is it?

WRIGHT: It is...this is going 7:30ish. Is that what you have?

KINMOND: 7:20.

WRIGHT: 7:20.

WILLIAMS: 7:20 okay 'cause I was like oh crap 7:30, I mean I, its okay if I'm a
little late to dinner. We're going to Mellow Mushroom so I know they're gonna
have to wait. I know there's gonna be a wait there.

WRIGHT: Okay, well I do want to ask you this, because it deals with education
and I know I said that was the final question but I like, I'm very inquisitive
and you're a very interesting subject, and I hate to use/refer to you as subject but...

WILLIAMS: Thank you, thank you.

Wrights: So

WILLIAMS: Put me in a test tube. Put me in a glass jar on a shelf.

WRIGHT: [Laughter] What was your as far as your educational experience? I know
your undergraduate degree was dealing specifically with Urban Planning but you
did have to at some point take your Gen Eds. And at some point did you, running
back to the teacher in me, did you ever kind of learn about gay experiences at
Tech? 'Cause I know in middle, high school it's kind of touchy you can't really,
but in college, was that an open discussion in your academics?

WILLIAMS: Sometimes I made it part of the discussion. I mean it's so bizarre.
I've never thought about it. You're forcing me to think about something I never
thought about. 'Cause in my opinion, it was always just like well, I came out
and once I was out I was out. But it was like I came out guns blazin', ready to fight.

WRIGHT: And when you say ready to fight what does that mean? Were you...what
does that mean?

WILLIAMS: I was just instantly ready to fight for gay rights. I was like &quot;I'm
gay and this is bullshit.&quot; Like gay kids shouldn't be killing themselves because
people pick on them and gay people should be allowed to get married and they
should be able to hold their hands with their partner in public without being
harassed. I also sometimes wonder how my brain is hardwired for certain things
that like, God forbid you don't get exposed to them. Like for me, social justice
is not only a passion but it's an intellectual fascination. I'm so fascinated by
social constructs and social identities. I almost majored in Sociology.

WRIGHT: So do you think, and just from my interpretation of what you're saying,
do you think it was the lack of what you saw is what prompted you to want to
fight? So is that a good...?

WILLIAMS: Mmm...lack of...what would it be the lack of?

WRIGHT: A lack of equality. A lack of hearing about yourself in the classroom,
I'm adding to this so correct me if I'm wrong, but do you think that led to...

WILLIAMS: In society in general, not necessarily that I would even pinpoint
Virginia Tech because there's always pockets. There's a class on LGBT, there's
like a course. I think they're trying to get a major started right now or a
minor, a minor. But for me actually, I think part of my social justice, I can't
separate out the gay from the social justice to some extent. I took the most
transformative class I've ever had in my entire life–Nations and
Nationalities. It's an undergraduate class that Edward Wiseman teaches and in
that class we read three books but only two of them are sticking out in my mind
right now. One was a book about the Holocaust, and just reading, I mean I
learned about the Holocaust in high school, but learning about it and having to
write a 10 page college-level critical reflection, like no bullshit's gonna pass
like it did in high school, about the Holocaust was opening my eyes and seeing
how...and in the book it talked about how gays were treated in the Holocaust as
well as Jews. And then another book called The Bluest Eye, have you heard of it
by Toni Morrison?

WRIGHT: I've heard of it.

WILLIAMS: Yeah, I think it's on the bookshelf. I'm pretty sure it's up there
somewhere. And it's called The Bluest Eye and it's about a little black girl who
sees how good her white friend has it and has blue eyes. And she thinks that
this girl has everything because of her pretty blue eyes. And so this girl longs
for the day that her eyes will turn blue. She's like 'I'll just wait til my eyes
turn blue and then my life will be perfect' and like she almost goes crazy.
Like, she gets so delusional dreaming about the day that she gets her blue eyes
like her friend and it's just heartbreakingly tragic. It's like willing the
unwillable. So that class and the conversations that happened in that class, and
hearing the people in that class who were ignorant [whispers]as fuck[?] and then
hearing other people in that class who were way more enlightened than me discuss
this, it was just really eye-opening for me. And then I took a class on
international development, in which I learned that colonialism is the worst
thing that's ever happened to this planet. [Laughs] And I mean, I'm not someone
who--I try to avoid having white guilt or male guilt because I didn't choose to
be either of those things, but I mean holy crap that was hard to learn about
colonialism and how I benefit from it to this day. Well we all do, even folks of
color or women, if you're living in America, you're benefitting from
colonialism, you know. It's like...

WRIGHT: I can understand that argument, as a black woman I can reason through
that argument. [laughs]

WILLIAMS: Yeah, right, well clearly we're all more complex. We are oppressed and
privileged at the same time. And in, I guess what I was getting at, when I
learned that there are just tens, hundreds of thousands acres of really arable
farmland in parts of Africa and other parts of the developing world that are
used to grow cash crops instead of food, so you have people starving and getting
paid pennies on the dollar to grow things like tobacco and peanuts, so that they
can sell them to Europe and to the United States for huge amounts of money,
instead of growing food for the people to eat, and it's just like such a broken system.

WRIGHT: Alright, this is my final question.

WILLIAMS: This is so unrelated but...[laughs]

WRIGHT: I promise you, this is my final question to you, throughout our
interview, I think at least three or four occasions you mentioned the current
issues for the gay community. Of course in Virginia we're now allowed to get
married, but can you speak on some of the other issues, some of which you
mentioned, as far as suicide higher than other groups, can you care to share?
And then I'll…

WILLIAMS: Yeah. So you know, marriage equality is great and all, but marriage
equality really benefits, you know, the upper class gay people. There're a lot
of issues that LGBT youth face with bullying, especially trans members. There's
the L--I hope that you get to interview some trans folks 'cause trans issues are
really different from gay and lesbian issues, but the higher suicide rates, the
constant reinforcement that the lifestyle you're living is a sin. So even if you
have legal protections in the form of being able to get married, its like if
you're a kid and you're growing up in church and you hear every day that you're
gonna burn in hell when you die, I mean, that kid doesn't care if gay people can
get married. They're going to hell. It's like really, really bad and the fact
that a lot of times, you know, gay people can still get fired, you can get
legally fired for being gay. Homelessness--gay people getting kicked out. Like a
teenager comes out to his parents and they kick him out of the house.
Homelessness, suicide, there are a lot of issues, I mean most of the issues that
I'm thinking of are referencing LGBT youth but that's like the most critical
time in life because that's when people find out they're gay because you hit
puberty and secondary hormones start kicking in. You know, like I said when I
was a little kid I was intrigued by the naked men in the locker room but it
wasn't until puberty that I became aware, self-aware that I was gay. And that's
when teenagers need the most support of any group. You know, well except maybe
like infants, because there's so much turmoil in their life at that...oh my God
I would never relive… When people who said that high school were the best
years of their life, and no offense if it was for either one of you, but I'm
just like 'ugh now I feel sorry for you.' 'Cause it was not the best time of my
life. So yeah, that's when I say I don't want people to be like &quot;Well now that
we have equality.&quot; I mean the same thing happens with issues for people of
color. It's like &quot;We have a black president, what's the problem?&quot; Post-racial,
here we are. And it's like no, just because...it's like we've had interracial
marriage since 1969, the Loving vs. Virginia, do y'all know that case?

WRIGHT: Of course.

WILLIAMS: I love the name, Loving versus Virginia, and Virginia is for lovers.
It's like oh, so now that that happened interracial couples walking down the
street holding hands don't get stared at, or gawked at, or have people say
things like, &quot;date within your own race&quot; or &quot;protect the races&quot; and all that
stupid crap. So just because we have marriage equality doesn't mean that gay
people are suddenly gonna be treated equally.

WRIGHT: And to wrap this up, I mean you did a great job of comparing, 'cause it
does transcend the issues with the LGBQT, and I'm sure I'm missing some other
letters of the community...

WILLIAMS: Alphabet soup.

WRIGHT: With people of color and people who are poor, those issues do transcend,
so I think you definitely did a great job of kind of wrapping that up. Thank you.

WILLIAMS: Yeah, thank you.

WRIGHT: For your time.

WILLIAMS: Happy to help. Let me know if this ends up in a gay history book or something.

</transcript><rights>Permission to publish material from the Virginia Tech LGBTQ Oral History Collection must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech</rights><fmt>audio</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation>Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_WilliamsJohnGray.xml</xmllocation><xmlfilename>Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_WilliamsJohnGray.xml</xmlfilename><collection_link>http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/collections/show/86</collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>