<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT><record id="00015439" dt="2015-10-02"><version>4</version><date format="yyyy-mm-dd">2014-10-29</date><date_nonpreferred_format>2014-10-29</date_nonpreferred_format><cms_record_id>Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_KilkellyAnn</cms_record_id><title>Oral History with Ann Kilkelly, October 29, 2014 (Ms2015-007)</title><accession></accession><duration>01:05:40</duration><collection_id>Ms2015-007</collection_id><collection_name>The Virginia Tech LGBTQ Oral History Collection</collection_name><series_id></series_id><series_name></series_name><repository>Virginia Tech Special Collections</repository><funding></funding><repository_url /><interviewee>Ann Kilkelly</interviewee><interviewer>Amanda Lilly</interviewer><file_name>Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_KilkellyAnn</file_name><sync>1:|22(4)|30(6)|41(2)|51(1)|64(3)|72(5)|81(5)|90(10)|103(6)|112(12)|126(9)|143(5)|157(2)|166(7)|174(14)|186(3)|199(4)|206(1)|216(8)|224(12)|234(6)|242(13)|255(7)|266(15)|285(9)|313(6)|326(15)|339(1)|347(6)|356(7)|364(9)|373(13)|381(14)|391(8)|407(2)|422(13)|436(10)|452(8)|459(11)|467(9)|479(9)|489(7)|503(2)|519(2)|529(1)|537(6)|546(5)|553(10)|564(10)|573(8)|580(10)|591(3)|600(6)|609(3)|619(7)|629(5)|645(6)|653(10)|663(2)|677(3)|687(8)|694(15)|704(6)|716(11)|729(13)</sync><media_id></media_id><media_url>http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/files/original/3413/Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_KilkellyAnn_OralHistory.1.mp3</media_url><mediafile><host>Other</host><host_account_id></host_account_id><host_player_id></host_player_id><host_clip_id></host_clip_id><clip_format>audio</clip_format></mediafile><language></language><index><point><time>2</time><title>Introductions and Upbringing</title><partial_transcript>Amanda Lilly: Okay this is Amanda Lilly with Dr. Ann Kilkelly on October the 29th 2014. We are in her office in Henderson Hall and it’s about two in the afternoon– a little bit after two. So thank you for doing this [laughter] once again. I guess I will start out with the first question, which is: can you tell us your name, date and place of birth and about your family and how you were raised?
Ann Killkelly: Okay well that could take us all day [laughter]. Ann Kilkelly, middle name Maureen. I grew up in a little town on the St. Croix river in Minnesota, Bayport Minnesota, on a very beautiful wild river. My parents were (what I would call) working class in some ways, but slightly upwardly mobile. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>309</time><title>Early Awareness of Social Justice and Liberalism</title><partial_transcript>I guess I was raised with a pretty ferocious sense of justice about people that were poor, especially in people that were unlike other people. The race thing was kind of a deal in our town cause it was mostly Scandinavians and the few Irish families were looked on pretty much as suspiciously colored people. You know, the Irish were categoried as colored people at one point in history– but it wasn’t like that, but it was a fierce consciousness of our working class origins, of our need to assert our rights in a way that was somewhat compatible with 1950s thinking [laughter]. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>460</time><title>Early Activism</title><partial_transcript>I was a Vietnam protestor, I was also very much involved in the Catholic church’s anti-war stuff that happened and I graduated in 1969. So that was the major, major time of the political conventions and you know student protests stuff and I was very–on one hand I was really very naïve and really younger than most people and fairly innocent of many things, yet I had a certain kind of radical politics. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>685</time><title>Marriage to husband</title><partial_transcript>LILLY: That's good. And you said you went to the University of Minnesota for your Bachelors and the University of Utah for your Graduate?

KILLKELLY: Yes. Very good [laughter]. Good memory. Yes I did go. Once I graduated and I got married right after that--by the way to somebody I didn't even like. Part of it was my father was quite sick, he had had a major stroke and he subsequently died like right after my wedding and by that time I knew I was making a horrible mistake. I was also really young, I graduated at I don't know, I was nineteen or twenty. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>992</time><title>Personal identity</title><partial_transcript>LILLY: I guess one of the things I would ask is how do you identify yourself now? 

KILLKELLY: Sexual orientation? That's complicated because I was a very confirmed heterosexual for most of my life, as was the expectation. That I never questioned it and I was very pretty when I was young and I didn't have a very good self-image, but I acted out the highly feminine role, I think, and that began to degrade because the women's movement was growing and I was much more, much more aware of feminist stuff. I found that in Germany, when I had a lot of time to read and raise a child, I read Adrienne Rich and I read all the early feminists so my sense of the breadth of what sexuality meant opened up in a big way for me then. I always thought of myself as someone who was open to most possibilities in that range, in that spectrum, but still not outside of the heterosexual boundary. But seeing other things and understanding sexuality in a different way. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>1336</time><title>Views on the institution of marriage</title><partial_transcript>This is my feeling and I think that the political piece of it about marriage and all of that is important for a certain kind of legitimation, but I have critiqued the hold of Christianity over marriage and you know what I'm talking about, I'm sure. I can't do it, because I think the institution is the problem, but certainly people who want to be in that system should be able to be. So you know, it's that shifting your politics around to be intersectional and to balance a lot of different balls. You know I did teach in, or I said I was the head of Women's Studies for seven years and was in that department for a long time. So I've made it my business really to include that in my teaching and as my own understanding shifted over the years of those issues and what part of me was relevant. So before I came here and when my son was small, it was very much about motherhood. I thought about motherhood and I was very influenced by Adrienne Rich and Motherhood as Institution. Do you know that book at all?</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>1531</time><title>Coming out at Virginia Tech</title><partial_transcript>LILLY: So you started at Tech in '92.

KILLKELLY: Yeah '91, '92. 

LILLY: '92, and that's when you met your current partner. Did you have--correct me if I'm wrong, when you married when you were young, did you have a child with your husband?

KILLKELLY: Mhmm, yes I did.

LILLY: So you have a total of three children?

KILLKELLY: No I only have one [laughter].

LILLY: Oh okay, I thought--</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>1880</time><title>Changing attitudes at Virginia Tech in the early 1990s</title><partial_transcript>But at Tech, I think at that point, which would have been '93, '94, really was changing in terms of the visibility of LGBTQ people. Not a lot, but you could see it, you could perceive it the university was changing and Virginia was so repressive in those days. It's a miracle we can even marry in Virginia even if I don't want to. It was in the air, the issues were. There certainly weren't classes, there wasn't a caucus. I think there was a women's network that I belonged to and there was a group of gay women, or lesbian women that were a community, but we didn't feel like we belonged exactly to that community partly because of our position in the university. But partly because of the way we identified, which was much more open I think. Nonetheless, it was a huge change in our lives to be together, but we were very lucky. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>2090</time><title>Scandal with the Board of Visitors</title><partial_transcript>KILLKELLY: When did Shelli [Fowler] and Karen [DePauw] come here? Do you remember the date?

LILLY: I think it was 2002-2003.

KILLKELLY: Yeah, by that time there was sort of a critical mass, I think, of people who went to bat for them. It wasn’t just sexuality, but it was this outrage that they would do this in a closed rather than an open–I forget the name of the committee, it’s an executive committee of the Board of Visitors and they made the decision closed session, which is not legal. Those sessions are supposed to be public. 
</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>2253</time><title>Take Back the University March</title><partial_transcript>KILLKELLY: This is when the protest, when Carol and I organized the protest, and she collected a lot of letters and then we did this Take Back the University March with duct tape on our mouths and academic regalia and what not.

LILLY: Wow. 

KILLKELLY: There were only about thirty five of us, there weren’t many, but we walked in our regalia over and we stood in front of Burruss Hall and various things. It got some play in the newspapers, although they all said “it’s too bad hardly anybody came” [laughter]. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>2356</time><title>The Principles of Community and other Struggles with the BOV</title><partial_transcript>KILLKELLY: they approved putting the language in the Principles of Community. I helped start that Principles of Community stuff and we fought about that issue, we just fought to get to be included, for sexuality to be one of the terms or whatever the term of the moment was and we could not get it through the board. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords>LGBT Rights;Principles of Community</keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>2629</time><title>LGBTQ community and university organizations</title><partial_transcript>LILLY: So not really at Tech, but just in Blacksburg in general, since you've moved here in the early '90s and to now. Has there been any communities or safe spaces for the LGBTQ community in Blacksburg, that aren't necessary part of the university, that you have been a part of, or that has been a safe space. Especially in the early '90s, because now I'm pretty sure it's probably a lot different now or maybe more.</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>2919</time><title>Shamrock bar</title><partial_transcript>LILLY: So I guess now I'll ask you about the Shamrock Bar and performing there. That's in Bluefield right?

KILLKELLY: Right and it's sort of--I can't even remember if it's Bluefield West Virginia or Bluefield Virginia because the line goes right through. 

LILLY: Is it still there?</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>3612</time><title>Importance of discussing LGBTQ issues</title><partial_transcript>LILLY: So I guess to kind of wrap up, is there anything that you would want people to know if they listen to this. Is there a message that you want to give people in the LGBTQ community or just in general. Is there anything that you think- any advice, any kind of message?

KILLKELLY: I'm not a believer in single messages but, [laughter] which will come as no surprise, but one thing that I really believe is that education on these issues is absolutely important because nobody gets the depth of the systemic issues. </partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point><point><time>3895</time><title>Closing</title><partial_transcript>LILLY: Alright I guess we will stop there thank you so much for doing this.

KILLKELLY: No problem it was fun. And I am just so thrilled that it's happening. It is very moving to me that someone like David is doing what needs to be done in a very systematic and complex way, you know. So that we're not just saying &quot;oh what we need are a few more gay people here, some representative there,&quot; but somebody who's paying attention to what people are experiencing. So I am so grateful to him.</partial_transcript><synopsis></synopsis><keywords></keywords><subjects></subjects><gps></gps><gps_text></gps_text><hyperlink></hyperlink><hyperlink_text></hyperlink_text></point></index><type></type><description>Ann Kilkelly is a Professor of Theatre Arts and Women's Studies at Virginia Tech. She teaches a variety of performance and theater classes, women's studies seminars and undergraduate courses about community and culture, and tap classes. Since coming to Virginia Tech, she has been an advocate for traditionally underrepresented populations and she served on the Commission on Equal Opportunity and Diversity from 2005-2008.

The interview was conducted on October 29, 2014 in Henderson Hall at Virginia Tech. It begins with a description of Kilkelly's upbringing and early involvement with activism. It then covers her marriage and her own description of her personal identity with respect to societal labels. Next, the inverview addresses the racial and LGBTQ climate at Virginia Tech, how it has changed over time, the scandal relating to Shelli Fowler's hiring, and the development of the Principles of Community. Finally, there is a description of drag shows at the Shamrock bar and Kilkelly's views on why it is important to discuss LGBTQ issues.</description><rel /><transcript>﻿Interview with Ann Kilkelly

Date of Interview: October 29, 2014

Interviewer: Amanda Lilly

Place of Interview: Henderson Hall

Length: 01:05:40

Transcriber: Bryanna Tramontana

Amanda Lilly: Okay this is Amanda Lilly with Dr. Ann Kilkelly on October the
29th 2014. We are in her office in Henderson Hall and it's about two in the
afternoon-- a little bit after two. So thank you for doing this [laughter] once
again. I guess I will start out with the first question, which is: can you tell
us your name, date and place of birth and about your family and how you were raised?

Ann Killkelly: Okay well that could take us all day [laughter]. Ann Kilkelly,
middle name Maureen. I grew up in a little town on the St. Croix river in
Minnesota, Bayport Minnesota, on a very beautiful wild river. My parents were
(what I would call) working class in some ways, but slightly upwardly mobile. My
mother, her father, my grandfather, was a wild boxer and sort of a really crazy
plumber and swimmer and lots of physical stuff, and my mother was a lot like
that and she was also very independent minded and rebellious and known around
town as somebody you didn't want to mess with on political issues or--I would
say she's an activist, but we wouldn't really have used that term. But she was
very very profoundly interested in civil rights, well I wouldn't call her a
feminist either; she did take matters into her own hands. I wrote a story about
her called 'Revolution,' about when she and her friend Elvira took apart a stove
piece by piece and hauled it to the junk yard because it wasn't working properly
and she was fed up. Never told my dad. And we were not very wealthy people at
all, and he [Kilkelly's father] was very habituated to his perfect time
schedule, having lunch at a certain time. So they took a sledgehammer and a
pickaxe and demolished the stove, got a friend with a car, hauled it to the junk
yard and then brought cold cuts home, which was huge. That's why I called it a
revolution because that was like--anyway that's my mother [laughter].

My dad would have called himself 'lace curtain Irish' and I'm like second
generation, we're not sure, or third generation Irish. Not having much money,
the family was an old family and so there was a lot of sense of we're genteel
people even though we're not wealthy. So I grew up with that on that side with a
lot of sense of propriety about what it meant to be a woman, and much more
scrupulous Catholicism. My mother was kind of a wild card, a convert who
converted to Catholicism because she wanted to have a crucifix [laughter] and
not for any reasons of faith, but for the fact that she had seen in the movies
that it kept away vampires. So that's that, so what else--let's see what else.

I went to school there, but I was quickly transferred to other schools that were
bigger, in a larger city and eventually college. My education was very tended by
my sister who was much older than I, eighteen years older, and at that time was
a school teacher. And she taught me to read when I was really young, like three,
and I went subsequently to school early, and then I went to high school early
and then I went to college early, and so forth. So that was a huge priority in
my family was education, and I was the first one to get a Ph.D., I think, in the
family. Unfortunately, neither my mother nor my father were alive when I
finished all that, but I think it's owing to them that I probably did, more to
my mother. So that's--what else did you ask me with that question?

LILLY: How you were raised.

KILLKELLY: I was raised to be pretty independent because my older siblings left
home, and I was the forth, and they were by that time really enjoying having
their own lives and having friends and playing cards--they were very social
people. I guess I was raised with a pretty ferocious sense of justice about
people that were poor, especially in people that were unlike other people. The
race thing was kind of a deal in our town cause it was mostly Scandinavians and
the few Irish families were looked on pretty much as suspiciously colored
people. You know, the Irish were categoried as colored people at one point in
history-- but it wasn't like that, but it was a fierce consciousness of our
working class origins, of our need to assert our rights in a way that was
somewhat compatible with 1950s thinking [laughter]. My mom did not make a very
'Leave it to Beaver' housewife image, very athletic, very wonderful dancer,
brainy, read tons of books--tons. Neither one of my parents had a college
education, but my mother read five, ten books a week. So I was raised to read, I
was raised to be good at math, I was raised to dance and sing, even though I
never got to play an instrument, because all of that disappeared as time went
on. So, I was raised by a Minnesota democratic liberal-- Democratic Farmer
Liberal party in Minnesota, which was really a unionized-- a pro union thing.
It's quite characteristic of the upper Mid-West, especially Minnesota, so
politically, all was very liberal.

What else can I say? I was editor of the school paper. I was Minnesota 1962
State Champion in Water Ballet. I learned to cook very early and did, and I went
to the University of Minnesota for my B.A., majored in English, but did a whole
lot of dance and a whole lot of theater as well. And I graduated Magna Cum
Laude, or one of those three, I think it's a Magna, and got married right away
to a--I was a Vietnam protestor, I was also very much involved in the Catholic
church's anti-war stuff that happened and I graduated in 1969. So that was the
major, major time of the political conventions and you know student protests
stuff and I was very--on one hand I was really very naïve and really younger
than most people and fairly innocent of many things, yet I had a certain kind of
radical politics. My brother Dan, who also died when I was quite young, was a
history, not professor, but he studied history at college and when I was in high
school he--you don't mind a little story do you?

LILLY: No, go right ahead.

KILLKELLY: When I was in high school, maybe even junior high, he came home one
day as he often did and said &quot;I wanna take you to something.&quot; And I would go
anywhere that he wanted to go and it was usually the zoo or something really
cool. However, this time he brought me over to the University of Minnesota,
Northup Auditorium. Huge, huge, like Burruss, and I think sat like four thousand
people. The speaker was George Wallace, the Governor of Alabama, famous racist
politician, legacy of unbelievable stuff in the South. So George Wallace was
speaking and he told me nothing, I knew nothing about George Wallace at the time
and he told me, he said &quot;I just think this is something you really need to
hear.&quot; So we went over to Northup Auditorium and there were protestors
everywhere, students with these black arm bands and signs about racism and all
kinds of stuff. And then we went in and he [Wallace] made this highly rhetorical
southern lecture, which I thought was so elegant in my naiveté. So when we went
out he [Dan] said &quot;well what did you think?&quot; and I said, &quot;Oh I thought it was
really interesting and I don't quite understand it, but I thought he really
spoke beautifully and there is some sense in this alabaster cities he was
talking about&quot; and he just looked at me and he said &quot;don't you ever forget what
I'm gonna say now. He is talking about white people and black people and he is
responsible for the suppression of black people and you see all those people who
are protesting? That's why they're protesting.&quot; So he said like &quot;you better get
smart.&quot;-literally- and he started giving me books so I had that, and my
upbringing was like having six parents and then having them all go away. So from
baby, sort of pampered baby to very isolated and on my own. So it was both things.

LILLY: So were you the youngest?

KILLKELLY: I was youngest by- my closest sibling, my brother Dan, the one that I
was talking about, was twelve years older than I am, and then one sister
fifteen, one brother eighteen.

LILLY: Wow.

KILLKELLY: And I was like their responsibility. My parents were very loving, but
they were a little bit handsoff with me, which I think was probably a really
good thing. Stuff I wouldn't let my kids do [laughter] or kid. It was a little
town, everybody watched out for other people.

LILLY: That's good. And you said you went to the University of Minnesota for
your Bachelors and the University of Utah for your Graduate?

KILLKELLY: Yes. Very good [laughter]. Good memory. Yes I did go. Once I
graduated and I got married right after that--by the way to somebody I didn't
even like. Part of it was my father was quite sick, he had had a major stroke
and he subsequently died like right after my wedding and by that time I knew I
was making a horrible mistake. I was also really young, I graduated at I don't
know, I was nineteen or twenty.

LILLY: Oh wow.

KILLKELLY: My family was really concerned given how sick my dad was, that I
would be taken care of, and so they really pushed me. I don't blame them at all,
but they really thought the answer was for me to go ahead and get married and
what not. So I did that. And then I spent a year in Graduate School at the
University of Utah studying English, but also dancing and doing Theater
History--I always did that combination. After the first year, my husband was
transferred, assigned, to Torrejon Spain.

Here's another story for you, you'll like this one. So this is 1969, so he's
been doing--he has a background in meteorology, studying meteorology [sic
metallurgy?], very talented and was on his way to Graduate School in that and
got hired by Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing, three M, which was a young
company then and they were looking for young smart kids to make copper coins; to
bid for that so he worked on that bid. And they didn't get the bid and he
subsequently changed to psychology and prepared to be a graduate student when he
found out from his mother--who knew somebody on the local draft board--that he
better be careful because Vietnam was happening. So we debated, would we go to
Canada? Would he go to prison? Or go to war? I was much more ferocious about
that than he was, but he was also pretty anti-war. So in the middle of this an
Air force recruiter sort of got him convinced that he could be a psychologist in
the Air force, which was complete B.S. I mean, they'd tell any lie to get people
to enlist, but he enlisted as an officer so he didn't see combat in Vietnam, so
that was the one thing that was okay about that arrangement, and then we were
spent to Spain. Meanwhile, when he filled out his application form he cited his
work experience and abbreviated Metallurgy to MET. And the Air Force made him a
weather man. Meteorology, Metallurgy. He knew nothing about weather, and he had
to get a masters degree, without any preparation for that at all, in six months.
Because it was like the novel Catch 22-- sorry man you're in the Army, or Air
force. So it was an amazingly difficult thing and then he was an officer and he
was assigned first to go to Spain, Torrejon Spain, and predict the weather.
Which he never was very good at, he mostly called me and said, &quot;which way is the
wind blowing?&quot; [laughter] Anyway, the story of my marriage goes on and on, but
we went back to Utah after that year. I finished a masters and started a Ph.D
then. But we'd been in Europe, well Spain then Germany, we'd been in Europe for
four years I guess. I taught for the Air force, taught high school equivalency
English and then I was an agent for a Danish furniture company and traveled all
over and sold furniture.

LILLY: Oh wow [laughter].

KILLKELLY: I had to do something, then I had Dan, he was my son who was little.
So that takes me up to return to the United States, husband can't get back into
Graduate School, I get into Graduate School at the University of Utah again and
graduate later. And when I graduated, I split up with my husband. And then
there's years after that, but you should direct me to another question.

LILLY: I guess one of the things I would ask is how do you identify yourself now?

KILLKELLY: Sexual orientation? That's complicated because I was a very confirmed
heterosexual for most of my life, as was the expectation. That I never
questioned it and I was very pretty when I was young and I didn't have a very
good self-image, but I acted out the highly feminine role, I think, and that
began to degrade because the women's movement was growing and I was much more,
much more aware of feminist stuff. I found that in Germany, when I had a lot of
time to read and raise a child, I read Adrienne Rich and I read all the early
feminists so my sense of the breadth of what sexuality meant opened up in a big
way for me then. I always thought of myself as someone who was open to most
possibilities in that range, in that spectrum, but still not outside of the
heterosexual boundary. But seeing other things and understanding sexuality in a
different way.

I actually only started to identify as a lesbian when I met Carol, coming here
and that was in 1991, but I had been the director of a Women's Studies program,
before that I had been teaching Women's Studies. I've been around women and I
knew at that point then that it was a matter of what happened next for me and I
was more and more bonded to women as friends. So, even though I understand the
argument, I am not a person that would say I was born one way or the other-- I
know that I was not. And I really happily went into a relationship with another
woman and we happily, but with difficulty came out very clearly, and openly and
have not really looked back on that. She was someone who was bisexual, but at
that time was married and she was an elder in the Presbyterian Church. It was a
big deal, I was one administrator and she was an Associate Provost and it
created quite a little stir among those people who cared. So identification
is--I identify with the LGBTQ category, if I had to pick one I'd probably say Q.
But I have theoretical issues with all kinds of things, which I'm sure you're
aware of, but that's theory, that's different from the way you live your life.
So I live my life with one partner, a woman, and our children are both grown up
and they're both healthy.

And Women's Studies had a whole lot to do with my understanding of all that, of
really watching the dynamics of what played out, especially with the few people
I actually knew that were out at Virginia Tech. When I came, I was bringing a
male partner that I had been with for a number of years, but the university
failed to actually support-- this is a fierce irony. I had asked for him to be
brought here on a partner hire, and there were several people including the then
Provost, that were really supporting me in that, but by a series of what you
would find extremely bizarre incidents-- some man that is still around was a
friend of somebody on the Board of Visitors who had the ear of the then
President James McComas. And the Board of Visitors wrote a letter and said, &quot;you
cannot hire the partner, that it is Virginia Tech's policy.&quot; Apparently they had
just made the policy really clearly, just then, on that we do not hire the
partners of unmarried couples. So that gives you a measure of how things have
changed, so they wouldn't give him the job even though everyone had vetted him
and approved it. The Board of Visitors would not. As it turned out, it was for
me the better thing that happened because I met Carol and etc. So I hope that
gives you a picture--I think it's complicated. I try to say to my students that
I think the question of sexuality is too complicated for anybody to say
absolutely on a spectrum what they are, you know--

LILLY: I agree.

KILLKELLY: This is my feeling and I think that the political piece of it about
marriage and all of that is important for a certain kind of legitimation, but I
have critiqued the hold of Christianity over marriage and you know what I'm
talking about, I'm sure. I can't do it, because I think the institution is the
problem, but certainly people who want to be in that system should be able to
be. So you know, it's that shifting your politics around to be intersectional
and to balance a lot of different balls. You know I did teach in, or I said I
was the head of Women's Studies for seven years and was in that department for a
long time. So I've made it my business really to include that in my teaching and
as my own understanding shifted over the years of those issues and what part of
me was relevant. So before I came here and when my son was small, it was very
much about motherhood. I thought about motherhood and I was very influenced by
Adrienne Rich and Motherhood as Institution. Do you know that book at all?

LILLY: I haven't read it.

KILLKELLY: She's a poet, a lesbian poet, she's so important. And she wrote this
book of essays called On Lies, Secrets and Silences and she talked a lot about
the institution of marriage and it's oppressive structure for women. But she did
it autobiographically with really talking about having a different structure of
raising her sons, she had three boys by herself and this was like--it completely
opened my eyes. So anyway, I like to think of it as complex rather than having a
clear answer.

LILLY: I understand, I completely--

KILLKELLY: I doubt I'll ever have another partner, but I don't know what's going
to happen in the next-- the few years, the twenty years or so I'll be here [laughter].

LILLY: [Laughter]. I completely agree because I identify as bisexual so I
understand how--and sometimes I think that the labeling is not always good.

KILLKELLY: I think it comes back to hit you in the face.

LILLY: Yeah.

KILLKELLY: You can argue that people can't help it, that they have no control
over it. You're taking a certain kind of agency away from them in a big way, I
think. I know a lot of gay people who would disagree with me radically because
that sense that I am who I am--

LILLY: Of identity--

KILLKELLY: Of identity, but I don't know I'm more of a post-modernist or
materialist feminist, I don't see it that way. I see it as very contingent.

LILLY: So you started at Tech in '92.

KILLKELLY: Yeah '91, '92.

LILLY: '92, and that's when you met your current partner. Did you have--correct
me if I'm wrong, when you married when you were young, did you have a child with
your husband?

KILLKELLY: Mhmm, yes I did.

LILLY: So you have a total of three children?

KILLKELLY: No I only have one [laughter].

LILLY: Oh okay, I thought--

KILLKELLY: Well no I have two because of my partner's daughter I would count in that.

LILLY: Oh okay, I was thinking that--

KILLKELLY: I know I loop around; I have no sense of the chronological, that's a
lousy historian.

LILLY: So when you came here and you met her you said that you and her came out
together as a couple. What was that like? Did your colleagues, did they treat
you differently, did the university treat you differently, or her?

KILLKELLY: It depends on how you look at it. I mean, but for the most part, our
closest colleagues were very helpful and both of us were tenured professors,
both of us had reputations in the university for doing some good stuff and so I
would say we were both pretty respected. But as the director of Women's Studies,
I was already the enemy in some places and that was said very clearly. People
made sure I knew that someone had said that about me [laughter]. So it wasn't
that big a leap because people probably assumed that I was a lesbian anyway, but
they didn't because they remembered this deal with my partner, it was really a
mess. But I don't know--where was I going with that? Give me your question again?

LILLY: It was how were y'all treated differently by people in the community,
your colleagues and the university in general?

KILLKELLY: Well yeah on some level I think what happens to a lot of gay and
lesbian, LGBTQ people, what happens to a lot of them is failure to thrive. I
think it's not--I know there's a ton of overt hostility and discrimination, but
I think in the university system, the most powerful thing is silence. Is having
not supportive community, is having people not acknowledge. And that, I think,
in terms of your progress through the system, I think has a subtle, but strong,
impact on people. I know that, it's odd that when you do that you don't know who
knows and who doesn't for one thing, and also other people don't necessarily
know in the institution, so you don't know what people know or what they're
saying. I always had the sense that-- even though I always faired very well in
the university- I was promoted and all that-- I always had the sense that there
was this opposition out there that I lived with. And I think Carol felt that
too, only Johanna, her daughter, was just like ten when this happened. But I
will say that turned out well also, but it was very very hard, this being a
close knit community. But what we did was we set ourselves up deliberately to go
to people before some rumor mill got to people, we went and said, to our deans,
to the provost, that we're with each other and it's very important that we have
your support, it's very important that you understand that the way people treat
us might not be the same. We did that with a lot of people that were in
supervisory positions to us and also people in-- she was a member of the
Presbyterian Church, which she left because at that very time they had
determined that weren't going to ordain elders that were gay. So she, in protest
basically, left that and I think also happily, 'cause that went with the whole
picture. With the family and the religious credibility and all that. So yes I
think people talk, but I wouldn't say--I mean I think on the other end of that
the bonds you make with people in those circumstances make you a much richer
person. I think I had the intellectual understanding to, both of us did, to know
what the underlying issues were, the assumptions and stuff. Because people
generally find me approachable people would come and ask me questions and the
kind of questions they asked were the ones that, &quot;what is this really about? Do
you hate men? Do you not like men?&quot; You know that sort of thing. People will say
really stupid stuff, and you know it happens all the time. So yes definitely.
And our families.

But at Tech, I think at that point, which would have been '93, '94, really was
changing in terms of the visibility of LGBTQ people. Not a lot, but you could
see it, you could perceive it the university was changing and Virginia was so
repressive in those days. It's a miracle we can even marry in Virginia even if I
don't want to. It was in the air, the issues were. There certainly weren't
classes, there wasn't a caucus. I think there was a women's network that I
belonged to and there was a group of gay women, or lesbian women that were a
community, but we didn't feel like we belonged exactly to that community partly
because of our position in the university. But partly because of the way we
identified, which was much more open I think. Nonetheless, it was a huge change
in our lives to be together, but we were very lucky. We were smart about the way
we did it and our children were fantastic. Because we raised them to be that way
partly, but also because they had support from other parents. So yes, but also
have good fortune on the other side of that too, I think we're a lot of people's
favorite lesbians [laughter], cause we're nice. And people always think I'm
straight because of my curly hair [laughter], anyway.

LILLY: You said this was around '93, '94. Is this before the Safe Zone started happening?

KILLKELLY: Well before it, but things like that were starting to come up and the
big issues for me then were racial, racial stuff of all kinds with football
players being--or with the football program being sort of attacked for very good
reason, but also in a racist way over a very serious rape incident that
happened. It became a very famous case--Christy Bronkowski [sic Brzonkala].

LILLY: I think I remember that.

KILLKELLY: Probably, you might. So we were talking openly in Women's Studies,
that we knew the critique that black women had made of white feminists and a lot
of people had started writing about these issues. So the issue was more out,
much more out, people were starting to talk about marriage, were starting to
talk about rights. Not that they had them, but that the questions were in the
air. Not too long--when did Shelli [Fowler] and Karen [DePauw] come here? Do you
remember the date?

LILLY: I think it was 2002-2003.

KILLKELLY: Yeah, by that time there was sort of a critical mass, I think, of
people who went to bat for them. It wasn't just sexuality, but it was this
outrage that they would do this in a closed rather than an open--I forget the
name of the committee, it's an executive committee of the Board of Visitors and
they made the decision closed session, which is not legal. Those sessions are
supposed to be public.

LILLY: Actually we can probably go into that if you want.

KILLKELLY: Sure, might as well.

LILLY: So what exactly happened with Shelli Fowler and Karen DePauw?

KILLKELLY: You don't even want me to try to answer that do you [laughter]? I
mean you know some of the facts right?

LILLY: I know that there was a spousal problem with hiring Shelli because she
was--Karen was hired right?

KILLKELLY: As a Dean, right.

LILLY: It was a problem with hiring Shelli because they were together, so that's
what I've got in a nutshell.

KILLKELLY: Yes. So they could tell you specifically to be accurate, but I will
tell you what I know abou that in a nutshell if possible. It would have to be a
big nut. When they came, after Karen was hired, there was a period of time where
the English Department was vetting Shelli and had agreed to bring her in with
tenure, wanted to hire her and were excited about it, was all set to go. The
last stage of all this was like in June of the year they came. Where the Board
of Visitors, the same Board of Visitors made that decision that they would not
hire Shelli and it just blew up. For some reason, they decided to stay and
fight. If you know Shelli, then you know she's a real activist. Do you guys know her?

LILLY: No, I don't know her.

KILLKELLY: If you get a chance, take a class from her because she is really
special, so is Karen I think. This is when the protest, when Carol and I
organized the protest, and she collected a lot of letters and then we did this
Take Back the University March with duct tape on our mouths and academic regalia
and what not.

LILLY: Wow.

KILLKELLY: There were only about thirty five of us, there weren't many, but we
walked in our regalia over and we stood in front of Burruss Hall and various
things. It got some play in the newspapers, although they all said &quot;it's too bad
hardly anybody came&quot; [laughter]. But then a lot of stuff happened because of all
the letters. The shocking thing that happened in June happened when they were
moving here and but they still had the option of not coming and they decided to
be here. So that went on in various political issues that sort of involved them.
I can't remember how to reconstruct it, but it was about taking on the Board of
Visitors. Which was directed by a guy named Rochovich [sp], who's notorious and
who did a lot of anti-affirmative action work, and specifically anti-gay work in
Virginia many years ago. He is a real deal, but he's gone from the Board now and
the Board has changed spectacularly; they approved putting the language in the
Principles of Community. I helped start that Principles of Community stuff and
we fought about that issue, we just fought to get to be included, for sexuality
to be one of the terms or whatever the term of the moment was and we could not
get it through the board. They also, for a short time, wanted to vet every
decision we made about every speaker in class. I got a call from a Congressman
because we were doing women's month and Barbara Ehrenreich, I think it was her,
came to do a lecture on the sexual politics of meat. The other speaker they
identified was one Thank God I'm a Lesbian Mother, which was presented by the
religious program and gender studies. And they threatened us, well they didn't
threaten us directly, but there were all these editorials saying if Tech turns
on the lights for these things we should not put one penny of the state's money
into any of this. Fortunately those things didn't happen, but we were still in
the culture wars.

LILLY: Yeah.

KILLKELLY: So what happened then was through various administrative maneuverings
Shelli was given a full-time job by the unit that she is still in, which has
changed names, and given the status of a tenured faculty rank and all that, and
she was also working with the English, but she did not get a tenure track job in
English, and that's what she was prepared to do with a African American
literature and critical pedagogy and all of that. I think both of them have been
incredible agents for change in the institution. They were very very brave. They
had hate mail, they had death threats. It was really ugly and they just walked
through it and it was an amazing thing to see.

LILLY: I think what shocked me about it was when it happened in 2002-2003
because I was thinking that's so into the twenty-first century that this is
happening. I wanted to ask, at that time, did Virginia Tech have anything or any
sort of language in their hiring that no discrimination against sexual
orientation or gender at the time?

KILLKELLY: People had tried to get it and were also trying to get partner
benefits and all that. The conversation came up--well the irony of the situation
I described, was that they shut down a hire of a heterosexual kind in my case
and that became the defacto reason or the explanation.

LILLY: Oh because you weren't married.

KILLKELLY: Yeah, right. So it had a pretty bad effect on that, which was the
irony of ironies. And then when the Principles of Community were developed there
were several different attempts to include that language and the first time the
Board had approved it is this year.

LILLY: Really.

KILLKELLY: About how many months ago? I don't know, three or four months. Isn't
that incredible?

LILLY: Yes that's very incredible.

KILLKELLY: As I think of social change like that and social justice as something
like steering a houseboat. You may make a tiny adjustment and after three hours
the back end swings a foot in that direction. It's like way behind the
consciousness of many people.

LILLY: So not really at Tech, but just in Blacksburg in general, since you've
moved here in the early '90s and to now. Has there been any communities or safe
spaces for the LGBTQ community in Blacksburg, that aren't necessary part of the
university, that you have been a part of, or that has been a safe space.
Especially in the early '90s, because now I'm pretty sure it's probably a lot
different now or maybe more.

KILLKELLY: I think it's fine. I never call anything a safe space, so I will try
to answer that in the spirit which most people take it. A PFLAG [Parents and
Friends of Lesbians and Gays] chapter started here and so initially when we had
the PFLAG chapter initiated it was mostly LGBTQ people that were attending the
meetings, so telling our stories and doing things like that. Once it became an
actual PFLAG thing we backed away from it because we thought it was really,
really important for the parents and friends to have their own space, to be safe
talking about it with each other. I've done a lot of work on the academic level
I think. Not as much as I would like to I've never taught a class or course
studies, which I could do. Just partly circumstances.

I'm trying to think of other things. This was the university though, I was on
the commission for Equal Opportunity and Affirmative Action. I don't know if
they call it that still. It's a university committee it oversees a lot of
different initiatives, so these subjects came up pretty frequently and there
started to be a little opening for the discussion of the issues, but actually I
got off the committee because as far as I was concerned, it was going backwards
in terms of Women's Studies and wasn't doing anything like enough. I have
sometimes participated in caucus events, that has helped a lot. I do a lot of
work with Jean Elliott, not a lot, but I do stay close to her projects and help
her with her projects. Sometimes behind the scenes. Other organizations and
community groups I would say no. Partly because we don't, very comfortably, fit
into the women's community. Partly, it's an odd thing because we feel completely
supported politically and personally, but the lesbian culture in Blacksburg,
it's not that it didn't appeal to me, it isn't that I didn't love a lot of the
people, but we had these major full-time jobs. We were very visible within the
institution and that socializing wasn't something we do with anybody. As far as
attending events in the community, performances. At one point I wrote--I
interviewed a lot of people, faculty and staff and had planned to make a piece
called 'Power Outage' and never did that for various reasons, I was disgusted
and cynical probably [laughs] to do that, so I didn't put myself out in that
way. And other people have done a lot too, so for me I don't feel like I have to
kind of carry the burden of being a leader in relation to that issue that I used
to feel. [phone rings] That's Carol.

LILLY: So I guess now I'll ask you about the Shamrock Bar and performing there.
That's in Bluefield right?

KILLKELLY: Right and it's sort of--I can't even remember if it's Bluefield West
Virginia or Bluefield Virginia because the line goes right through.

LILLY: Is it still there?

KILLKELLY: No, not as it was. I don't know what the state of it is right now
because the building next to it was collapsing. When it was there--when the
Shamrock was operating as a bar. Carol was getting her hair cut and her
haircutter, who is a dear friend, his partner grew up in Bluefield, and as a gay
teenager he found the Shamrock Bar, which was where gay people went then. And
for a time also the African American community had its own place in the same
building. Early before the Shamrock came about there was a largely African
American bar that gays went to also. So Carol got really interested in this
story of this woman Helen Compton [sp] who was about sixty-five, seventy then.
She died maybe five years after that. Grew up in coal fields of West Virginia
and had stories about the Klu Klux Klan burning crosses on people's yards when
they found out somebody was having an extramarital affair, but also one of her
stories says the way she found out about gay people was that she saw these two
guys kissing and told her dad and he said oh yep there will be a cross burned
sometime soon.

So she decided that she was going to make a bar and a place where people could
be and feel safe. She herself sat at the door with a gun in her lap and watched
the street to make sure--she was an amazing character, amazing. If you ever want
to see a video, Carol would probably show it to you. She made this video 'It's
Reigning Queens in Appalachia.' So what happened, as Miss Helen told it, was
that she was sitting around with a group of men, and she was a lesbian, although
not openly out even in that community. Even though everyone knew, she didn't
even tell her son, straight ahead. Anyway it's crazy, but Miss Helen determined
she was going to have a place, she was gonna open a place that she would say
'the gays' would be welcome. And so she started this bar that was sort of a
lunch room during the day and actually there were some female prostitutes that
worked there. Sometimes business men in the community would come there for lunch
and a little something else, so it was this odd local joint during the day, but
at six o'clock it would become a gay bar. Helen would say, well right about five
o'clock every night, she'd say, &quot;I'd say 'well you know, in a little while it's
gonna get awful noisy in here, these young people, they just make so much noise
and I really think you should….'&quot; Basically she made them leave, but with that
little trick. So they're sitting around there talking, she's talking with a
group of men, gay men, and they're saying, they're talking about how much they
love wearing their mother's clothes and Helen says &quot;you wanna do that here?&quot; and
they said &quot;Lord yes Miss Helen, we'd like to do that!&quot; That's an exact quote
from her [laughter]. So she said, &quot;well you can do that here.&quot; So these guys
went out and started collecting--I mean apparently they'd come back from the
grocery store with cucumbers and cauliflower and just all kinds of vegetables
and they'd go to the thrift stores and had a very hard time finding shoes --it's
a whole story. So they started performing and having drag shows there very often.

In this process of getting to know our hair dresser and his partner and finding
out about Helen, Carol went and met Miss Helen and talked to her about it and
said what she wanted to do this project where she took photographs of the drag
queens and that she would interview her and interview the drag queens and she
subsequently did. So I went along, of course, to most of these things and helped
her with whatever was needed. The place was- it was really a dive; it had kind
of a nice bar, but they had made these homemade chandeliers out of aluminum
foil, all this fringe, but the place had the atmosphere of like a, when there
was a drag show, like a community basement or a church basement. It had a little
railing, and when people went up to stuff money into somebodies outfit in the
cleavage it was sort of like communion [laughter]. So we hungout with the drag
queens and she would take photographs in the dressing rooms while they were
getting dressed. I ended up being a judge for a Miss Gay Virginia, which was a
drag queen. And they tried to do a Mr. Shamrock and have the women do it, but
Helen couldn't get the women to dress up. So she liked us so much because we
played music, and she said &quot;what I want for my birthday is for you to come up
here and perform and get the women to perform.&quot; So we rounded up the women that
we knew which we knew and liked very much, so many of them, and they complied,
and I did a Motown performance. I studied Motown with a major Motown
choreographer actually, part of it was that he was a tap dancer too, so I got
the original Temptations backup choreography for 'Ain't too Proud to Beg' and
taught it to them.

LILLY: Oh that's awesome.

KILLKELLY: We put on suit jackets and mustaches including Carol's daughter who
was like thirteen at the time [laughter] and we just had a blast, I mean it was
a lot of fun. Largely speaking, I would say, safer than a lot of spaces I have
been in. Not safe either because up in that neck of the woods there's a lot of
gun violence and stuff.

LILLY: Yeah, maybe just more comfortable than other places.

KILLKELLY: Yeah. It was interesting that way and it was very eye opening to
watch this whole costume construction process and the make-up. I don't know if
you saw the photograph of one of the drag queens with hair--what was his name
her name? Miss Nikki was what he/she went by and applying make-up but doesn't
have the wig on, doesn't have the jewelry, doesn't have the fingernails yet, so
it's this transitional moment that's just really interesting. So that's the
story, and this went on for quite a while. She made the video, the photographs
went to the Smithsonian Archives and people have studied them and we still--Miss
Helen died and when she died she had a surreal funeral, but Carol had gone to
see her a lot because they got pretty close as well as the men, and we don't see
them much anymore because there was another gay bar there that a lot of the
people went to. The man who owns it was an early attendee at the bars saw it in
a different location, but the place just deteriorated because the building next
door was already collapsing. You should see the picture of the front door, it's
just this really kind of wrecked section of town- it's on main street, right by
railroad tracks, totally visible, it just has this little tiny sign that says
'Shamrock' and there's a cardboard cutout of a Shamrock on the door and that's
it. The windows are not- you can't see in, although Miss Helen could see out.

LILLY: Now I think the closest bar, they do Gay Miss America there, is The Park
in Roanoke. I think that's the closest one to here or to this area.

KILLKELLY: There's one in Johnston City, there's the big one in Johnston City
because we went around a lot to gay bars, then to drag shows to sort of study
drag shows. And our curiosity about that continues, but we really don't go out
to any bars. We didn't before that and we don't now, we're not bar people
[laughter]. But it was quite a chapter and it was amazing learning and the
video's lovely. You may want to see it.

LILLY: Yeah, I'll make a note of that.

KILLKELLY: I mean maybe you're interested outside this project. It's an amazing
thing that she did. It's a little rough now, because she wasn't working
digitally entirely. Now of course she could correct all the sound problems and
stuff and have better equipment, but it's an amazing piece of work.

LILLY: So I guess to kind of wrap up, is there anything that you would want
people to know if they listen to this. Is there a message that you want to give
people in the LGBTQ community or just in general. Is there anything that you
think- any advice, any kind of message?

KILLKELLY: I'm not a believer in single messages but, [laughter] which will come
as no surprise, but one thing that I really believe is that education on these
issues is absolutely important because nobody gets the depth of the systemic
issues. I mean, the culture is so saturated with heteronormativity and even
people in the community need that recognition of what the systemic--I think that
for the sense of isolation and the kind of dangerous isolation that is true for
so many. One way to understand that, that I think is really important, is to go
find classes. We have one, but go find that class, but also, I think, women in
Gender Studies is absolutely, really critical for people to know that in the
world or a world that's larger than this little place, that there are all kinds
of people that are talking really seriously, in very comic ways and in
performative ways and all that, that are talking about these things. That it's
not, they're really not by themselves, but it needs to be studied because if
it's not, then I think our assumptions we go to default a lot. We don't examine
some of that stuff. So that's not exactly advice, it's just a strong
recommendation that people find out historically what's been happening around
here, what's been happening in the rest of the world. So that they're equipped,
actually, to deal in a much more open way. Now, we're going to have these
conversations in a much more open way and it's not gonna go well a lot of the
time and the change is slow. So I think that information and study and finding
the people that really can help you with that aspect of it and art, I think art
is-- performance all that, I think that's key. Because it has a way of creating
a space where things can be said that can't always be said in a serious way, not
in a--I don't mean that in a serious way, I mean that just aren't said usually,
with a structure of metaphor things can be looked at in a deep way without
people feeling endangered or exposed too much, but they have the opportunity to
enter into a world that way. I don't know if you know Jeff Mann, I hope someone
is interviewing him.

LILLY: I have talked to him I know who he is, English right? Yes I've talked to him.

KILLKELLY: Yeah, he's wonderful and he has a lot to say on that subject. But I
think using the arts--I don't like the word using, but working in the arts as
way to really expand communities that understand and care about these issues and
plus it's very pleasurable you know, potentially. Even if it's about bad stuff,
even if it's people telling stories, horrible stories, it's still in the realm
of metaphor so that people can look at it with a different framework. To reframe
your experiences is absolutely important, to tell stories for example. Yeah
that's what I would say, tell stories.

LILLY: Tell stories.

KILLKELLY: Dance, tell stories. Most of us dance.

LILLY: Alright I guess we will stop there thank you so much for doing this.

KILLKELLY: No problem it was fun. And I am just so thrilled that it's happening.
It is very moving to me that someone like David is doing what needs to be done
in a very systematic and complex way, you know. So that we're not just saying
&quot;oh what we need are a few more gay people here, some representative there,&quot; but
somebody who's paying attention to what people are experiencing. So I am so
grateful to him.

LILLY: yeah I'm glad he's doing it too.

KILLKELLY: You like that he's your teacher?

LILLY: Yeah [laughter]. I'm really glad I took this class.

</transcript><rights>Permission to publish material from the Virginia Tech LGBTQ Oral History Collection must be obtained from Special Collections, Virginia Tech</rights><fmt>audio</fmt><usage></usage><userestrict>0</userestrict><xmllocation>Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_KilkellyAnn.xml</xmllocation><xmlfilename>Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_KilkellyAnn.xml</xmlfilename><collection_link>http://digitalsc.lib.vt.edu/collections/show/86</collection_link><series_link></series_link></record></ROOT>